<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">The Noble Dhāraṇī</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Essence of Immeasurable Longevity and Wisdom</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">The Translation</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">$1 [220.b][62.a] Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$2 Thus did I hear at one time.</s>
    <s id="5:2">The Blessed One was seated at the bank of a pool by the Ganges river#10 with a great monastic saṅgha of five hundred monks [62.b] and a great saṅgha of bodhisattvas.</s>
    <s id="5:3">The Blessed One addressed the monks,</s>
    <s id="5:4">the monks gave the Blessed One their full attention, and the Blessed One [221.a] said to them:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">$3 “A perfect buddha,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">The Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">Lives to the west of here</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">In the realm of Sukhāvatī.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">$4 “Those who recite his name</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Will be reborn there.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">At the moment of death they will see</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">The teacher with his monastic saṅgha.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">$5 “There are no women there,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">And no gestation in a womb.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">Beings with great magical power</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">Are born there from lotuses made of jewels.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">$6 “As soon as one thinks about</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">Food, clothing, medicines,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">Robes, bedding, and alms bowls</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">They instantly appear.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">$7 “The buddhas dwelling in all ten directions</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">Sing the praises of Sukhāvatī.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">Since the Buddha is inconceivable,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">The Buddha’s Dharma is inconceivable,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">$8 “And the Noble Saṅgha is inconceivable too.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">When one has generated faith in the inconceivable,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">The ripened result is inconceivable—</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">One is reborn in a pure realm.#11</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">$9 “Monks, the Thus-Gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Aparimitāyus’ palace, called Having a Retinue, is ten thousand leagues wide.</s>
    <s id="30:2">He was born into a kṣatriya family.</s>
    <s id="30:3">Monks, the Thus-Gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Aparimitāyus’ father was a universal ruler named Most Gracious, and</s>
    <s id="30:4">his mother was named Splendorous.</s>
    <s id="30:5">His kṣatriya queen was named Gracious Protector.</s>
    <s id="30:6">Monks, the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus’ son was named Moonlight, and</s>
    <s id="30:7">his attendant’s name was Stainless Renown.</s>
    <s id="30:8">Monks, the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus’ disciple foremost in insight was called Pinnacle of Grace, and</s>
    <s id="30:9">his disciple foremost in miraculous powers and foremost in great endeavor [63.a] was named Great Array.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="31">
    <s id="31:1">$10 “Monks, the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus’ Māra was called King of Offerings, and</s>
    <s id="31:2">the name of his Devadatta was Gracious Gift.</s>
    <s id="31:3">[221.b] Monks, the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus’ great gathering of hearers contains sixty thousand great hearers.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="32">
    <s id="32:1">$11 “Monks, all the beings who think well of him</s>
    <s id="32:2">should bear in mind the name of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus, practice for ten days with an undistracted mind that recollects the Buddha, and continually think of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus who dwells in the realm of Sukhāvatī.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="33">
    <s id="33:1">$12 “They should also continually recite the dhāraṇī of Śrī Amṛta­dundubhi­svara­rāja.#12</s>
    <s id="33:2">If all beings, three times a day and three times a night, prostrate with the five points of the body to the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus while thinking of him,</s>
    <s id="33:3">after ten days they will have a vision of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus and</s>
    <s id="33:4">[after ten days] they will have [a vision of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus and] a vision of all the blessed buddhas dwelling in the ten directions.</s>
    <s id="33:5">If they dedicate all their roots of virtue to rebirth in the realm of Sukhāvatī,</s>
    <s id="33:6">when they die the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus will be present before them, and</s>
    <s id="33:7">they will be reborn in the buddha field of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="34">
    <s id="34:1">$13 “Monks, this is the dhāraṇī called Amṛta­dundubhi­svara­rāja:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="35">
    <s id="35:1">tadyathā śavale avale sañjale nirdeśe nirjāte nirukte nirmukhe jvala­paricchedani sukhavati­nirdeśe amṛte āyurgarbha#13nirhāni amṛte ayuḥ­prasādhane nirbuddhi ākāśa­nirdeśe ākāśa­nirjāte#14 ākāśa­nirkuśale ākāśa­nirdarśane ākāśādhiṣṭhāne sukhavati ādhiṣṭhāne rūpa­nirdeśe catvāri­dharma­prasādhane catvāri ārya­satya­prasādhane catvāri­mārga­bhavana­prasādhane#15 bala#16vīrya­prasādhane dharmācchedane kuśale kuśala­nirdeśe kuśala­pratiṣṭhāne buddhākuśale viśuddha­prabhā#17sa dharma­karaṇe[63.b]nirjati nirbuddhe vimale viraje rājase rasāgre rasāgrabale rasāgrādhiṣṭhite kule pratikule vikule dānte sudānta#18citte supraśānta­citte supratiṣṭhite sule sumukhī­dharme ca dharme bale ca bale anuśābale buddhākāśa­guṇe buddhākāśa­nirguṇe amṛta­dundubhiḥ­svare svāhā</s>
  </p>
  <p id="36">
    <s id="36:1">$14 “Monks, faithful [222.a] sons or daughters of good family who recite this Amṛta­dundubhi­svara­rāja dhāraṇī as it has been taught should dress in clean clothes and,</s>
    <s id="36:2">in a place that is pure and unspoiled, make offerings of flowers and perfumes to the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus.</s>
    <s id="36:3">They should imagine the lotus seat at the seat of awakening and the perfect Bodhi tree.</s>
    <s id="36:4">They should arouse longing to be there, and</s>
    <s id="36:5">if they have such longing and faith they will be reborn in the buddha field of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="37">
    <s id="37:1">$15 “Monks, the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus’ king of trees is the tree called Radiating Jeweled Lotus, and it is covered in flowers and fruit.</s>
    <s id="37:2">The lotus seat, which is pure, bright, and fine, is called Brilliant Light Ray.</s>
    <s id="37:3">The Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus is seated there surrounded by many precious jewels.</s>
    <s id="37:4">The bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara is to his right,</s>
    <s id="37:5">the bodhisattva Mahāsthāmaprāpta is to his left, and</s>
    <s id="37:6">they are all surrounded by an incalculable gathering of bodhisattvas.</s>
    <s id="37:7">Faithful sons or daughters of good family who have great devotion, faith, and reverence will be reborn there.</s>
    <s id="37:8">They will take miraculous birth on great lotuses made of the seven precious jewels situated on the great golden ground.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="38">
    <s id="38:1">$16 “Monks, any monk, nun, male lay practitioner, or female lay practitioner who bears in mind the name of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus will never have to face any dangers from fire,</s>
    <s id="38:2">[“Monks, any monk, nun, male lay practitioner, or female lay practitioner who bears in mind the name of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus] will never have to face any [dangers from fire,] dangers from water,</s>
    <s id="38:3">[“Monks, any monk, nun, male lay practitioner, or female lay practitioner who bears in mind the name of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus] will never have to face any [dangers from fire, dangers from water,] dangers from poison,</s>
    <s id="38:4">[“Monks, any monk, nun, male lay practitioner, or female lay practitioner who bears in mind the name of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus] will never have to face any [dangers from fire, dangers from water, dangers from poison,] dangers from weapons,</s>
    <s id="38:5">[“Monks, any monk, nun, male lay practitioner, or female lay practitioner who bears in mind the name of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus] will never have to face any [dangers from fire, dangers from water, dangers from poison, dangers from weapons,] dangers from yakṣas, and</s>
    <s id="38:6">[“Monks, any monk, nun, male lay practitioner, or female lay practitioner who bears in mind the name of the Thus-Gone Aparimitāyus] will never have to face any [dangers from fire, dangers from water, dangers from poison, dangers from weapons, dangers from yakṣas, and] dangers from rākṣasas,</s>
    <s id="38:7">[64.a] except for those that arise due to the ripening of previous actions.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="39">
    <s id="39:1">$17 When the Blessed One had spoken these words,</s>
    <s id="39:2">the monks, the entire retinue, and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said. [222.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="40">
    <s id="40:1">$18 This concludes the noble dhāraṇī “Essence of Immeasurable Longevity and Wisdom.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="41">
    <s id="41:1">Colophon</s>
  </p>
  <p id="42">
    <s id="42:1">$19 Translated by the Indian preceptor Puṇya­sambhava and the translator Patsap Nyima Drak.</s>
  </p>
</text>
