<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">The Threefold Invocation Ritual</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">$1 [1.b] I take refuge with sincere devotion and reverence In the highest guru, the unsurpassed Three Jewels, And the greatest of them all, the sublime supreme lord.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">$2 Brahmā and Śakra—lords of heaven and earth, Source of all beings’ wealth, and protectors Of the Dharma, the supreme teaching;</s>
    <s id="3:2">great kings Dhṛtarāṣṭra,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">$3 Virūḍhaka, Noble Virūpākṣa, and Kubera;</s>
    <s id="4:2">World protectors Indra, Agni, Yama, Nairṛta, Varuṇa, Vāyu,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$4 Vaiśravaṇa, Īśāna, and Pṛthivīdevatā;</s>
    <s id="5:2">The Sun, Moon, grahas, nakṣatras, the elephants of the quarters, And the general, minister, and queen;</s>
    <s id="5:3">the guardians of the directions,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">$5 Each with their full retinue of queens and princes;</s>
    <s id="6:2">Renowned great commanders of the gods Such as Viṣṇu, Gaṇapati, Nandi, and Kārttikeya;</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">$6 Great and powerful Mahākāla, Mahābala, Jambhala, Padma, and Mahāpadma, Śaṅkha and Mahāśaṅkha, Pūrṇa and Supūrṇa,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">$7 Sugrīva, Pūrṇabhadra, Maṇibhadra, [2.a] Kumbhakarṇa, Ghaṇṭākarṇa, Trikarṇa, Mahākarṇa, Sañjñeya and Sañjaya,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">$8 Jinarṣabha, Āṭavaka, Haimavata, Sātāgiri, Pāñcika, Pāñcāla­gaṇḍa, Pāñcālaka, Daśagrīva, Vibhīṣaṇa, Meghanāda, Gagana­ghoṣa,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">$9 Triśirṣaka,#4 Sāgara, Nanda, Upananda, Anavatapta, Manasvin, Vāsuki, and the hosts of grahas;#5 Rṣis, vidyādharas, gods of the rains and harvest,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">$10 Gods of the road, of the day, the night, conjunctions, lunar phases, and moments;</s>
    <s id="11:2">Powerful beings such as Hanuman and the like;</s>
    <s id="11:3">Vāgīśvarī, Svaraghoṣā, and Sarasvatī;</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">$11 Vatsavatī, Śrīmati,#6 Mārīcī, Gaurī, Guardian of Speech, Gangā, Yamunā, Hārītī, Śaṅkhinī, Pārvatī, Durgā, and Kālī;</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">$12 The seven mothers, the seven sisters, and the four sisters;</s>
    <s id="13:2">Great goddesses and great yakṣiṇīs Such as Mahākālī and Ekajaṭī and so forth;</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">$13 Great rākṣasīs and great piśācīs Revered for their youthful forms, nurturing, and magical powers, Awesome in their great hides and praised in battle by the army of the gods;</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">$14 Marvelous, renowned great lay practitioners, Young gods and nāgas, Young vidyādharas and ṛṣis,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">$15 And their five hundred kinsmen, all of them venerated by monks;</s>
    <s id="16:2">This entire group of resplendent youthful ones Including the young yakṣa Tiraka and the like;</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">$16 Gods and nāgas who are lords of all beings;</s>
    <s id="17:2">Yakṣas, gandharvas, uragas, asuras, Garuḍas, kumbhāṇḍas, rākṣasas, kinnaras,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">$17 Bhūtas, piśācas, local deities, and evil spirits;</s>
    <s id="18:2">All you wise ones who have entered the path of compassion, All you who are held by the hook of the vidyāmantra , listen to me. [2.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">$18 May (insert name), a person blazing with good fortune Who has heard and recited the names Of the Three Jewels with their vowels and consonants</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">$19 Have a prosperous and long reign,#7 Serve and venerate the Three Jewels, which possess immeasurable Benefits and good qualities, have faith in the scriptures,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">$20 And, of course, study and practice the Dharma.</s>
    <s id="21:2">Upon death, may (insert name) depart for the divine pleasure groves With their vast bounty of scriptures.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">$21 This one who is conscientious and devoted is crowned With the teachings of the sun-like omniscient Dharma lord, The supreme radiant jewel that crowns the king of the gods Who brings victory in battle over the asuras and hosts of Māra.#8</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">$22 Approach,#9 children of the Victors!</s>
    <s id="23:2">Knowing that#10 we and all beings are already beyond suffering and</s>
    <s id="23:3">thus not fearing that sentient beings will fail to transcend it, may we still insatiably cultivate the accumulations of merit and wisdom.</s>
    <s id="23:4">May we know that things are intrinsically conditioned, yet not dismiss their characteristics.</s>
    <s id="23:5">May we not reject the form body of a buddha</s>
    <s id="23:6">May we [not reject the form body of a buddha,] yet attain freedom from all attachment.</s>
    <s id="23:7">May we be free from attachment to all phenomena, yet seek the wisdom that knows everything.</s>
    <s id="23:8">May we completely purify all phenomena as buddha realms without depending on others,</s>
    <s id="23:9">May we [completely purify all phenomena as buddha realms without depending on others,] yet understand the space-like characteristic of buddha realms.</s>
    <s id="23:10">May we never weary of bringing beings to maturity,</s>
    <s id="23:11">May we [never weary of bringing beings to maturity,] yet never abandon the characteristics of lacking self-identity.</s>
    <s id="23:12">May we magically display supernatural powers,</s>
    <s id="23:13">May we [magically display supernatural powers], yet never waver from the sphere of reality.</s>
    <s id="23:14">May we not stop setting our mind on enlightenment,</s>
    <s id="23:15">May we [not stop setting our mind on enlightenment,] yet may omniscient wisdom arise in us.</s>
    <s id="23:16">May we satisfy all beings by turning the wheel of the Dharma,</s>
    <s id="23:17">May we [satisfy all beings by turning the wheel of the Dharma,] yet not pass beyond the inexpressible nature of reality.</s>
    <s id="23:18">May we [3.a] demonstrate the magical emanations and blessings of a tathāgata,</s>
    <s id="23:19">May we [3.a] [demonstrate the magical emanations and blessings of a tathāgata], without nevertheless discarding the body of a bodhisattva, and</s>
    <s id="23:20">yet in all the perceptions of beings may we appear and</s>
    <s id="23:21">[yet in all the perceptions of beings] may we [appear and] then display the great parinirvāṇa.</s>
    <s id="23:22">Children of the Victors, uphold these aspects of the teachings and practice these obverse and direct ways of engaging in practice.#11 These ten teachings are the most excellent activity of a buddha.</s>
    <s id="23:23">Children of the Victor, these are the awakened activity of a bodhisattva.</s>
    <s id="23:24">The spontaneous activity of the bodhisattvas is independent of others and is the perfect attainment of unsurpassed awakening.#12</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">$23 King of the gods, great sovereign, boon-granting lord, Fearless hero famous throughout the world Whose face is radiant with insight like the full moon— The aspiration and activity of a great being is your sole companion.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">$24 Brahmā, Śakra, and the other world protectors Used the vajra-like samādhi, Mt.</s>
    <s id="25:2">Sumeru, as the churning stick And, along with compassion and effort, the nāga rope, Churned forth an elixir, the holy Dharma, From the ocean of great insight that spread everywhere like a feast of amṛta.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">$25 With this jewel of merit, the renowned Dharma, as the crown jewel, You were victorious in battle over the armies of rākṣasas and the asuras.</s>
    <s id="26:2">I dedicate this to the mighty helmet of the kingdom of the gods.#13</s>
    <s id="26:3">I dedicate this so that our radiance, retinues, and wealth may increase And in particular so that we may attain powerful and strong standings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">$26 I dedicate this so that we may perfect all the means of liberation Such as the magical powers, supernatural cognitions, and perfections And accomplish all our virtuous actions and intentions.</s>
    <s id="27:2">I dedicate this so that our bodies may be pervaded by the bliss of the Dharma nectar, Liberating us from minds that are plagued by suffering.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">$27 Spiritual teachers, kind and loving friends, We are wounded by the blade of the afflictions.</s>
    <s id="28:2">Please sustain us with your compassionate blessing And ensure that whomever is granted the crown is powerful And protects the teachings of the Tathāgata.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">$28 We are faulted beings who are confused and act inappropriately—please forgive us!</s>
    <s id="29:2">Those who know the time, vidyāmantra, and ritual, please be patient with us. [3.b]</s>
    <s id="29:3">We pray that the good fortune of this Dharma offering to the hosts of gods Shall ensure prosperity and cause the supreme Dharma to flourish.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">This concludes “The Threefold [Invocation] Ritual.”#14</s>
  </p>
</text>
