<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">The Question of Maitreya (3)</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">$1 [330.b] Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Thus did I hear at one time.</s>
    <s id="4:2">The Blessed One was dwelling in Rājagṛha, on Vulture Peak Mountain, together with a great saṅgha of monks and a great saṅgha of bodhisattvas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$2 On that occasion the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya#10 rose from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</s>
    <s id="5:2">Joining his palms and bowing to the Blessed One, he spoke these words:</s>
    <s id="5:3">“Blessed One, what are the karmic results of bestowing the Dharma?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">$3 The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya,</s>
    <s id="6:2">“Maitreya, suppose one person filled as many great trichiliocosms as there are grains of sand in the river Ganges with the seven precious substances and</s>
    <s id="6:3">offered them to the tathāgata, arhat, truly perfect buddhas, and another person, out of compassion, established a single verse of the Dharma in the mindstream of another.</s>
    <s id="6:4">Maitreya, the former mass of merit would not even come close to a hundredth of this latter mass of merit.</s>
    <s id="6:5">Nor could it be compared to even a thousandth, a hundred-thousandth, a ten-millionth, a hundred-sextillionth,#11 or any other portion, fraction, enumeration, or example.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">$4 After the Sugata had said this, the Teacher furthermore declared:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">“Consider one who has caused as many world realms as there are sand grains in the Ganges</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">To be filled to the brim with an abundance of riches#12</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">And offered these to the victors with a joyful mind,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">And another who has bestowed a single verse to a sentient being—</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">$5 “If that exceedingly vast gift of riches</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">Does not equal any fraction or portion#13</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">Of cultivating compassion and then bestowing a single verse, [331.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">How could one fathom the ripening of giving a verse twice, or three times?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">$6 When the Blessed One had spoken, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, the other bodhisattvas and the monks,#14 and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">$7 This completes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra “The Question of Maitreya.”</s>
  </p>
</text>
