<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Unraveling the Intent</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">Prologue</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">[1.b] Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$1Thus have I heard at one time.</s>
    <s id="5:2">The Blessed One was dwelling in an unfathomable palace, built with the blazing seven precious substances,#34 that emitted#35 great light rays suffusing countless universes.#36 Each of its rooms was well arranged and its design was infinite.</s>
    <s id="5:3">It was the indivisible maṇḍala, the domain transcending the three worlds.</s>
    <s id="5:4">Arising from the supreme roots of virtue of the one who transcends the world,#37 it was characterized by the perfectly pure cognition of the one who has achieved complete mastery.#38</s>
    <s id="5:5">Abode of the Tathāgata where the assembly of innumerable bodhisattvas gathered, it was attended by countless gods, nāgas, [2.a] yakṣas, gandharvas, demigods, garuḍas, kiṃnaras, mahoragas, humans, and nonhumans.</s>
    <s id="5:6">Supported by the great joy and bliss of savoring the Dharma and designed to accomplish the complete welfare of all beings, it was free of any harm caused by the stains of afflictions and clear of any demon.</s>
    <s id="5:7">Surpassing all manifestations, this unfathomable palace was displayed by the sovereign power of the Tathāgata.</s>
    <s id="5:8">Mindfulness, intelligence, and realization were its pathway;#39 mental stillness and insight were the vehicle leading to it;</s>
    <s id="5:9">the great gates of liberation—emptiness, appearancelessness, and wishlessness—were its entrance.</s>
    <s id="5:10">It was set on foundations adorned with an infinite accumulation of excellent qualities, which were like great kings of jeweled lotuses.#40</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">$2The Blessed One had a perfectly realized mind and was free from dualistic behavior.</s>
    <s id="6:2">Absorbed in the Dharma of the nonexistence of defining characteristics, he was residing in the domain of the buddhas.</s>
    <s id="6:3">He had attained equality with all buddhas.</s>
    <s id="6:4">His realization was unobstructed and his qualities#41 were irreversible.</s>
    <s id="6:5">He could not be overcome by objects of experience.#42 His abode was inconceivable.#43 Perfectly skilled in the sameness of the three times,#44 his five bodies were present in all worlds.</s>
    <s id="6:6">His knowledge of all phenomena was free from doubt.</s>
    <s id="6:7">He understood all practices.</s>
    <s id="6:8">His knowledge of phenomena was without uncertainty. [2.b] His body was unimaginable.</s>
    <s id="6:9">He possessed the gnosis bodhisattvas vow to accomplish.#45 He had attained the nondual abode of the buddhas, the sublime perfection, the supreme indivisible gnosis of the Tathāgata’s liberation.#46</s>
    <s id="6:10">He had realized the sameness [of all phenomena], the state of a buddha in which there is neither a center nor a periphery,#47 and reached the ultimate within the domain of truth, the point where the sphere of space ends.#48</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">$3The Blessed One [was accompanied by ]the entire immeasurable assembly of hearers.</s>
    <s id="7:2">Children of noble family, they were the heirs of the Buddha.</s>
    <s id="7:3">Their minds were liberated, their wisdom was emancipated, and their discipline was completely pure.</s>
    <s id="7:4">They happily gathered with those who longed for the Dharma.</s>
    <s id="7:5">They had heard much, kept in mind what they had heard, and accumulated [merit from] what they had heard.</s>
    <s id="7:6">They excelled in thought, speech, and deeds.</s>
    <s id="7:7">Their wisdom was swift, quick, sharp, emancipating,#49discerning,#50 vast, extensive, profound, and unequaled.</s>
    <s id="7:8">They possessed the jewel of wisdom and the three forms of knowledge.</s>
    <s id="7:9">They had attained the supreme state of happiness in this life.</s>
    <s id="7:10">The purity of their merit,#51 the excellence of their peaceful conduct, their patience, and their gentleness were vast.#52 They were fully engaged in the teaching of the Tathāgata.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">$4The Blessed One was also accompanied by all the innumerable bodhisattvas assembled from various buddha realms.</s>
    <s id="8:2">Firmly settled and engaged in a vast state, they had gone forth through the Dharma of the Great Vehicle.</s>
    <s id="8:3">Impartial toward all beings, they were free from all conceptions, conceptualizations, and fabrications.</s>
    <s id="8:4">Victorious over all demons and opposition, they were not involved with the considerations of the hearers and solitary realizers. [3.a] Steadfast through the great joy and happiness of savoring the Dharma, they were free from the five great fears.</s>
    <s id="8:5">Solely progressing toward the stages from which there is no regression, they had perfectly actualized the stage in which one pacifies the torment of beings.</s>
    <s id="8:6">Among them were thus the bodhisattva mahāsattvas Gam­bhīrārtha­saṃdhi­nirmo­cana, Vidhi­vatpari­pṛcchaka, Dharmodgata, Su­viśuddha­mati, Viśālamati, Guṇākara, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, Āryāva­loki­teśvara, Maitreya, and Mañjuśrī.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">Chapter 1</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">$5At that time, the bodhisattva Vidhi­vatpari­pṛcchaka questioned the bodhisattva Gam­bhīrārtha­saṃdhi­nirmo­cana on the ultimate whose defining characteristic is inexpressible and nondual:#53</s>
    <s id="10:2">“O son of the Victorious One, when it is said that all phenomena are nondual,</s>
    <s id="10:3">what are these phenomena?</s>
    <s id="10:4">In what way are they nondual?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">Gam­bhīrārtha­saṃdhi­nirmo­cana replied,</s>
    <s id="11:2">“Noble son, all phenomena, what we refer to as all phenomena, are of just two kinds: conditioned and unconditioned.</s>
    <s id="11:3">With respect to these, the conditioned is neither conditioned nor unconditioned.</s>
    <s id="11:4">The unconditioned is neither unconditioned nor conditioned.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">$6Vidhi­vatpari­pṛcchaka inquired,</s>
    <s id="12:2">“O son of the Victorious One, why is the conditioned neither conditioned nor unconditioned and the unconditioned neither unconditioned nor conditioned?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">Gam­bhīrārtha­saṃdhi­nirmo­cana answered,</s>
    <s id="13:2">“Noble son, the term conditioned is a word, a label used by the Teacher.</s>
    <s id="13:3">Words that are labels used by the Teacher are conventional expressions arising from imagination.</s>
    <s id="13:4">These conventional expressions arising from imagination are always unreal#54 conventional expressions arising from imagination in its diversity.</s>
    <s id="13:5">Therefore, the term conditioned is not the conditioned. [3.b]</s>
    <s id="13:6">Noble son, the term unconditioned is also included within conventions, just as expressions other than conditioned and unconditioned are and will [always] be.</s>
    <s id="13:7">One might object that there is, however, no expression in the absence of the object [to which it refers].</s>
    <s id="13:8">What is then this object?</s>
    <s id="13:9">It is the complete and perfect awakening to inexpressible [reality] through the sublime gnosis and vision#55 of the noble ones.#56 But</s>
    <s id="13:10">in order#57 to lead [others] to the perfect realization of this very inexpressible nature of phenomena, the Teacher labels this object with the term conditioned.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">$7“Noble son, the term unconditioned is also a word, a label used by the Teacher.</s>
    <s id="14:2">Words that are labels used by the Teacher are conventional expressions arising from imagination.#58</s>
    <s id="14:3">These conventional expressions arising from imagination are always conventional expressions deprived of any actuality that arise from imagination in its diversity.</s>
    <s id="14:4">Therefore, the term unconditioned is not the unconditioned.</s>
    <s id="14:5">Noble son, the term conditioned is also included within conventions, just as expressions other than conditioned and unconditioned are and will [always] be.</s>
    <s id="14:6">One might object that there is, however, no expression in the absence of the object [to which it refers].</s>
    <s id="14:7">What is then this object?</s>
    <s id="14:8">It is the complete and perfect awakening to inexpressible [reality] through the sublime gnosis and vision of the noble ones.</s>
    <s id="14:9">But</s>
    <s id="14:10">in order to lead [others] to the perfect realization of this very inexpressible nature of phenomena, the Teacher labels this object with the term unconditioned.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">$8Vidhi­vatpari­pṛcchaka asked,</s>
    <s id="15:2">“O son of the Victorious One, as the noble ones completely and perfectly awaken to inexpressible [reality] through their sublime gnosis and perception, why do they [4.a] label this object with the terms conditioned and unconditioned in order to lead [others] to the perfect realization of this very inexpressible nature of phenomena?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">Gam­bhīrārtha­saṃdhi­nirmo­cana replied,</s>
    <s id="16:2">“Noble son, it is like the following example:</s>
    <s id="16:3">A magician or his skillful apprentice, finding himself at the juncture of four great roads, assembles grass, leaves, twigs, pebbles, or stones and produces all kinds of magic illusions, such as regiments of elephants, horses, chariots, and soldiers or collections of jewels, pearls, beryl, seashells, crystal, and coral, as well as an abundance of wealth and grain in treasuries and granaries.</s>
    <s id="16:4">At that time,</s>
    <s id="16:5">in the presence of these illusions, those who are naive, slow-witted, or confused, not perceiving the grass, leaves, twigs, pebbles, or stones, see and hear those magical tricks and think that whatever appears exists—that these regiments of elephants, horses, chariots, and soldiers or collections of jewels, pearls, beryl, seashells, crystal, and coral, as well as this abundance of wealth and grain, treasuries and granaries, exist.</s>
    <s id="16:6">Clinging to these magical illusions according to the way they see and hear things and strongly believing in them, they express themselves through conventions, such as ‘This one is true but the other is false.’</s>
    <s id="16:7">They still need to examine these illusions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">“Those who are not naive or confused but have wisdom perceive the grass, leaves, twigs, pebbles, or stones.</s>
    <s id="17:2">They see and hear those magical tricks and understand that whatever appears does not exist—that these regiments of elephants, horses, chariots, and soldiers or collections of jewels, pearls, beryl, seashells, crystal, and coral, as well as this abundance of wealth and grain, treasuries and granaries, do not exist. [4.b] Yet,</s>
    <s id="17:3">they understand that the conception of an elephant regiment exists since its manifestation as a conception through an expedient#59 exists, as do the manifestations as conceptions of regiments of horses, chariots, and soldiers or collections of jewels, pearls, beryl, seashells, crystal, and coral, as well as this abundance of wealth and grain, treasuries and granaries, together with other similar manifestations.</s>
    <s id="17:4">So they understand that all those magical illusions, these magic illusions deceiving the eye, exist [in the way magical illusions do].#60 Thinking in this way,</s>
    <s id="17:5">[these wise beings] do not express themselves through conventions, such as ‘This one is true but the other is false,’ on account of clinging to these magical illusions in the way they see and hear things and thus strongly believing in them.#61 However,</s>
    <s id="17:6">they do express themselves through conventions in order to convey the true nature#62 [of these illusions to others], although they do not need to further examine these illusions.#63</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">$9Likewise, some childish or ordinary beings have not attained the transcendent sublime wisdom.</s>
    <s id="18:2">They have not understood that the nature of all phenomena is inexpressible.</s>
    <s id="18:3">When those beings perceive conditioned and unconditioned phenomena, they believe that whatever appears as a conditioned or unconditioned phenomenon exists, and</s>
    <s id="18:4">they express themselves through conventions, such as ‘This one is true but the other is false,’ on account of clinging to these appearances according to the way they see and hear things and thus strongly believing in them.</s>
    <s id="18:5">They still need to examine these appearances.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">“With regard to this, some beings who are not childish and have seen the truth have attained the transcendent sublime wisdom.</s>
    <s id="19:2">They have understood that the nature of all phenomena is inexpressible.</s>
    <s id="19:3">When they perceive conditioned and unconditioned phenomena, they believe that whatever appears as a conditioned or unconditioned phenomenon does not exist.</s>
    <s id="19:4">However,</s>
    <s id="19:5">with respect to these appearances, they think that the conceptions in terms of conditioned and unconditioned, [5.a] the manifestation of conceptions through an expedient in terms of conditioned and unconditioned, the occurrence of conceptualization, and the phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena exist in the way magical illusions do.</s>
    <s id="19:6">That which deludes the mind exists [in the way magical illusions do].#64 Thinking in that way,</s>
    <s id="19:7">they do not express themselves through conventions, such as ‘This one is true but the other is false,’ on account of clinging to these appearances according to the way they see and hear things and thus strongly believing in them.</s>
    <s id="19:8">However,</s>
    <s id="19:9">they do express themselves through conventions in order to convey the true nature [of these appearances to others], although</s>
    <s id="19:10">they do not need to further examine these appearances.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">“Noble son, the noble ones are thus completely and perfectly awakened to inexpressible [reality] through their sublime gnosis and vision of this object, but in order to lead [others] to the perfect realization of this very inexpressible nature of phenomena, they label this object with the terms conditioned and unconditioned.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">$10At that time, the bodhisattva Gam­bhīrārtha­saṃdhi­nirmo­cana recited these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">“The profound, which is inaccessible to foolish beings,Inexpressible and nondual, has been taught by the Victorious One.Yet,</s>
    <s id="22:2">fools deluded by ignoranceTake delight in mental elaborations and dwell on duality.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">“Deprived of understanding, afflicted by misunderstanding,They will be reborn as sheep or oxen.</s>
    <s id="23:2">Casting aside the words of the wise,They will wander in saṃsāra for a great length of time.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">This was the chapter of the bodhisattva Gam­bhīrārtha­saṃdhi­nirmo­cana—the first chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">Chapter 2</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">$11Then the bodhisattva Dharmodgata spoke these words:</s>
    <s id="26:2">“Blessed One, very long ago in ancient times, beyond as many universes as there are grains of sand in seventy-seven Ganges rivers,</s>
    <s id="26:3">I was residing in the world Kīrtimat of the tathāgata Viśālakīrti.</s>
    <s id="26:4">There I [saw ]7,700,000 non-Buddhists, together with their teachers, who had gathered in one place to consider the ultimate defining characteristic of phenomena.#65[5.b]</s>
    <s id="26:5">Although they had examined, analyzed, investigated, and considered in detail the ultimate defining characteristic of phenomena, they did not understand it.</s>
    <s id="26:6">They had changing opinions, lacked certainty, and were slow-witted as well as argumentative.</s>
    <s id="26:7">Insulting one another with harsh words, they became abusive, agitated, unprincipled, and violent.</s>
    <s id="26:8">Then,</s>
    <s id="26:9">Blessed One, I thought to myself,</s>
    <s id="26:10">‘This is so sad, and yet, how marvelous, how wonderful are the manifestations of the tathāgatas in the world and, through their manifestations, the realization and actualization of the ultimate whose defining characteristic is beyond all speculation!’ ”#66</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">$12The Blessed One answered to the bodhisattva Dharmodgata:</s>
    <s id="27:2">“So it is, Dharmodgata.</s>
    <s id="27:3">So it is.</s>
    <s id="27:4">I have completely and perfectly awakened to the ultimate characterized as being beyond all speculation.</s>
    <s id="27:5">Yet,#67</s>
    <s id="27:6">after I attained complete and perfect awakening, I communicated through words, gave explanations, established distinctions, expressed myself through conventions, and imparted teachings.</s>
    <s id="27:7">One might ask why I did this.</s>
    <s id="27:8">I have explained that the ultimate is what is cognized by noble beings in a personal and intuitive way,#68 whereas</s>
    <s id="27:9">ordinary beings’ knowledge [resulting from interacting] with one another belongs to the domain of speculation.#69</s>
    <s id="27:10">Therefore, Dharmodgata, you should know in this way through this approach that the ultimate is what is characterized as transcending all speculation.</s>
    <s id="27:11">Moreover, Dharmodgata, I have explained that the ultimate represents the domain in which there is no phenomenal appearance,#70 whereas speculation is the domain of phenomenal appearance.</s>
    <s id="27:12">Therefore, Dharmodgata, you should know in this way through this approach that the [6.a] ultimate is what is characterized as transcending all speculation.</s>
    <s id="27:13">Moreover, Dharmodgata, I have explained that the ultimate is inexpressible, whereas speculation is the domain of verbalization.</s>
    <s id="27:14">Therefore, Dharmodgata, you should know in this way through this approach that the ultimate is what is characterized as transcending all speculation.</s>
    <s id="27:15">Moreover, Dharmodgata, I have explained that the ultimate is free from all conventions, whereas speculation is the domain of conventions.</s>
    <s id="27:16">Therefore, Dharmodgata, you should know in this way through this approach that the ultimate is what is characterized as transcending all speculation.</s>
    <s id="27:17">Moreover, Dharmodgata, I have explained that the ultimate is devoid of argumentative disputation, whereas speculation is the domain of argumentative disputation.</s>
    <s id="27:18">Therefore, Dharmodgata, you should know in this way through this approach that the ultimate is what is characterized as transcending all speculation.#71</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">$13“Dharmodgata, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="28:2">beings who have only tasted pungent or bitter flavors their entire lives cannot imagine, infer, or appreciate the taste of honey and sugar.</s>
    <s id="28:3">Those who have indulged in desire and have been burnt by the torment of desire for a long time cannot imagine, infer, or appreciate the inner happiness of the recluse, which is independent from all phenomenal appearances related to form, sound, smell, taste, and contact.</s>
    <s id="28:4">Those who have indulged and taken delight in conversations for a long time cannot imagine, infer, or appreciate the inner happiness of the noble beings who remain silent.</s>
    <s id="28:5">Those who have indulged and taken delight in conventions for a long time through seeing, hearing, discriminating, and cognizing cannot imagine, infer, or appreciate the cessation of all conventions, the nirvāṇa that is the [6.b] extinction of transitory aggregates.</s>
    <s id="28:6">Dharmodgata, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="28:7">Those who have indulged and taken delight in argumentative disputations for a long time on account of their attachment to the self cannot imagine, infer, or appreciate that there is no attachment to the self and no argumentative disputations in Uttarakuru.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">“Dharmodgata, likewise, those who [have indulged for a long time in] speculation cannot imagine, infer, or appreciate the ultimate whose defining characteristic transcends all speculation.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">$14Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="31">
    <s id="31:1">“It is the domain whose characteristic must be intuitively cognized,Beyond all expressions, apart from all conventions, And free from argumentative disputations—#72Such is the ultimate whose characteristic transcends all speculation.”#73</s>
  </p>
  <p id="32">
    <s id="32:1">This was the chapter of the bodhisattva Dharmodgata—the second chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="33">
    <s id="33:1">Chapter 3</s>
  </p>
  <p id="34">
    <s id="34:1">$15Then the bodhisattva Su­viśuddha­mati addressed the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="34:2">“Blessed One, at an earlier time, you spoke these words:</s>
    <s id="34:3">‘The ultimate is subtle and profound.</s>
    <s id="34:4">Characterized as transcending what is distinct or indistinct#74 [from conditioned phenomena], it is difficult to understand.’</s>
    <s id="34:5">How wonderful indeed are these words of yours!</s>
    <s id="34:6">Blessed One, regarding this point, I once [saw ]many bodhisattvas who, having attained the stage of engagement through aspiration,#75 assembled in one place to discuss in the following way whether conditioned phenomena and the ultimate are distinct or indistinct.</s>
    <s id="34:7">Among them, some declared, ‘The defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are indistinct.’#76</s>
    <s id="34:8">Others replied, ‘It is not the case that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are indistinct, for they are distinct indeed.’ [7.a]</s>
    <s id="34:9">Some others, who were perplexed and lacked certainty, said, ‘Some pretend that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are distinct.</s>
    <s id="34:10">Some pretend that they are indistinct.</s>
    <s id="34:11">Which bodhisattvas speak the truth?</s>
    <s id="34:12">Which speak falsity?</s>
    <s id="34:13">Which are mistaken?</s>
    <s id="34:14">Which are not?’</s>
    <s id="34:15">Blessed One, I thought to myself,</s>
    <s id="34:16">‘So, none of these noble sons understands the ultimate whose subtle defining characteristic transcends whether it is distinct or indistinct from conditioned phenomena.</s>
    <s id="34:17">These bodhisattvas are truly#77 naive, confused, dull, unskilled, and mistaken.’ ”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="35">
    <s id="35:1">$16The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva Su­viśuddha­mati,</s>
    <s id="35:2">“So it is, Su­viśuddha­mati.</s>
    <s id="35:3">So it is.</s>
    <s id="35:4">Indeed, none of these noble sons understands the ultimate whose subtle defining characteristic transcends whether it is distinct or indistinct from conditioned phenomena.</s>
    <s id="35:5">These [bodhisattvas] are truly naive, confused, dull, unskilled, and mistaken.</s>
    <s id="35:6">Why is this so?</s>
    <s id="35:7">Su­viśuddha­mati, it is because those who analyze conditioned phenomena in this way neither realize nor actualize the ultimate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="36">
    <s id="36:1">$17“Why?</s>
    <s id="36:2">Su­viśuddha­mati, if the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate were indistinct, [even] spiritually immature people—all ordinary beings—would, as a consequence, realize the truth.</s>
    <s id="36:3">As mere ordinary beings,#78[7.b] not only would they attain nirvāṇa, the unsurpassable good,#79 but they would also fully and completely awaken to unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="37">
    <s id="37:1">“If the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate were distinct, even those who realize the truth would, as a consequence, not be detached from the phenomenal appearances of conditioned phenomena.</s>
    <s id="37:2">Since they would not be detached from the phenomenal appearances of conditioned phenomena, they would also not be liberated from the bondage of phenomenal appearances.</s>
    <s id="37:3">If they were not liberated from the bondage of phenomenal appearances, they would not be liberated from the bondage of corruption.</s>
    <s id="37:4">If they were not liberated from these two kinds of bondage, those who realize the truth would neither attain nirvāṇa, the unsurpassable good, nor fully and completely awaken to the unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="38">
    <s id="38:1">“Su­viśuddha­mati, ordinary beings do not realize the truth and,#80 as mere ordinary beings, neither do they attain nirvāṇa, the unsurpassable good, nor do they fully and completely awaken to the unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening.</s>
    <s id="38:2">For these reasons,</s>
    <s id="38:3">it is not correct to say that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are indistinct.</s>
    <s id="38:4">Regarding this point, you should know through this approach that those who consider the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate to be indistinct are not right but wrong.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="39">
    <s id="39:1">“Su­viśuddha­mati, it is not the case that those who realize the truth are not detached from the phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, for they are indeed detached from it.#81 Neither are they not liberated from the bondage of phenomenal appearance, for they are indeed liberated from it.</s>
    <s id="39:2">Nor are they not liberated from the bondage of corruption, for they are indeed liberated from it.</s>
    <s id="39:3">Since they are liberated from these two kinds of bondage, [8.a] not only do they attain nirvāṇa, the unsurpassable good, but they will also fully and completely awaken to the unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening.#82 For all these reasons,</s>
    <s id="39:4">it is not correct to say that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are distinct.</s>
    <s id="39:5">Regarding this point, you should know through this approach that those who consider the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate to be distinct are not right but wrong.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="40">
    <s id="40:1">$18“Moreover, Su­viśuddha­mati, if the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate were indistinct, then, just as the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena is encompassed by the defining characteristic of affliction, so too would the defining characteristic of the ultimate be included in the defining characteristic of affliction.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="41">
    <s id="41:1">“However, Su­viśuddha­mati, if the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate were distinct,</s>
    <s id="41:2">then the defining characteristic of the ultimate could not be the universal defining characteristic within all the defining characteristics of conditioned phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="42">
    <s id="42:1">“Su­viśuddha­mati, the defining characteristic of the ultimate is not encompassed by the defining characteristic of affliction, and the defining characteristic of the ultimate is the universal defining characteristic within all the defining characteristics of conditioned phenomena.</s>
    <s id="42:2">For these reasons,</s>
    <s id="42:3">it is not correct to say that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are either indistinct or distinct.</s>
    <s id="42:4">Regarding this point, you should know through this approach that those pretending that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are indistinct or distinct are not right but wrong.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="43">
    <s id="43:1">$19“Moreover, Su­viśuddha­mati, if the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate were not distinct, [8.b]</s>
    <s id="43:2">then, just as the defining characteristic of the ultimate is not specific to any defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena, so too would all defining characteristics of conditioned phenomena not be specific to any conditioned phenomenon, and yogis would also not look for the ultimate beyond whatever they see, hear, distinguish, or know with regard to conditioned phenomena.#83</s>
  </p>
  <p id="44">
    <s id="44:1">“However, Su­viśuddha­mati, if the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate were distinct, then, the mere selflessness and essencelessness of conditioned phenomena would not be the defining characteristic of the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="44:2">The defining characteristic of affliction and the defining characteristic of purity themselves would be simultaneously established as distinct defining characteristics of conditioned phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="45">
    <s id="45:1">“Su­viśuddha­mati, the defining characteristics of conditioned phenomena are specific and not unspecific to conditioned phenomena;</s>
    <s id="45:2">yogis do look for the ultimate beyond whatever they see, hear, distinguish, or know with regard to conditioned phenomena;</s>
    <s id="45:3">the ultimate is indeed characterized by the mere selflessness and essencelessness of conditioned phenomena;</s>
    <s id="45:4">and the defining characteristic of affliction and the defining characteristic of purity also are not simultaneously established as distinct defining characteristics of conditioned phenomena.</s>
    <s id="45:5">For all these reasons,</s>
    <s id="45:6">it is not correct to say that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are neither indistinct nor distinct.</s>
    <s id="45:7">Regarding this point, you should know through these approaches that those pretending that the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are indistinct or distinct are not right but wrong.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="46">
    <s id="46:1">$20“Su­viśuddha­mati, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="46:2">It is not easy to decide#84 whether the whiteness of the conch is distinct or indistinct from the defining characteristic of the conch, likewise with the yellowness of gold.</s>
    <s id="46:3">It is not easy to decide whether the quality of the sound produced by a vīṇā is [9.a] distinct or indistinct from the defining characteristic of sound, likewise with aloe and its fragrance, pepper and its heat, myrobalan and its astringency, cotton and its softness, and clarified butter and butter.</s>
    <s id="46:4">Thus it is not easy to decide whether the impermanence of all conditioned phenomena is distinct or indistinct from the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena, likewise with the suffering of all beings with outflows and the defining characteristic of beings with outflows, as well as the selflessness of all phenomena and the defining characteristic of phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="47">
    <s id="47:1">“Su­viśuddha­mati, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="47:2">It is not easy to decide whether the defining characteristic of restless desire and the defining characteristic of afflictions are distinct or indistinct from the defining characteristic of desire.</s>
    <s id="47:3">You should know it is just like this with anger and delusion too.</s>
    <s id="47:4">Likewise, Su­viśuddha­mati, you should not see anything good#85 in deciding whether the defining characteristic of conditioned phenomena and the defining characteristic of the ultimate are distinct or indistinct.</s>
    <s id="47:5">In this way, Su­viśuddha­mati, I have completely and fully awakened to the ultimate that is subtle, extremely subtle, [profound], extremely profound, difficult to understand, extremely difficult to understand, and characterized as transcending being distinct or indistinct from conditioned phenomena.#86 Yet,</s>
    <s id="47:6">after I attained complete and perfect awakening, I communicated through words, gave explanations, established distinctions, expressed myself through conventions, and [9.b] imparted teachings.”#87</s>
  </p>
  <p id="48">
    <s id="48:1">$21Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="49">
    <s id="49:1">“The defining characteristics of the domains of conditioned phenomena and of the ultimateAre free from being distinct or indistinct.#88</s>
    <s id="49:2">Those who imagine them to be distinct or indistinct are mistaken.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="50">
    <s id="50:1">“As beings practice mental stillness and insight,They will be liberated from the bonds of corruptionAnd the bonds of phenomenal appearance.”#89</s>
  </p>
  <p id="51">
    <s id="51:1">This was the chapter of the bodhisattva Su­viśuddha­mati—the third chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="52">
    <s id="52:1">Chapter 4</s>
  </p>
  <p id="53">
    <s id="53:1">$22Then the Blessed One spoke these words to Subhūti:</s>
    <s id="53:2">“Subhūti, do you know how many beings in the world#90 display their knowledge#91 under the influence of conceit?</s>
    <s id="53:3">Do you know how many beings in the world display their knowledge without conceit?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="54">
    <s id="54:1">Subhūti answered,</s>
    <s id="54:2">“Blessed One, according to my knowledge, there are only a few in the world of beings who present their knowledge without conceit, but</s>
    <s id="54:3">countless, innumerable, and inexpressible in number are those who do so under its influence.</s>
    <s id="54:4">Blessed One, at one time I was staying in a hermitage set in a great forest.</s>
    <s id="54:5">There were many monks living in the vicinity who had also established themselves there.</s>
    <s id="54:6">At sunrise, I saw them gather together.</s>
    <s id="54:7">They showed their knowledge and revealed their understanding by taking various aspects of phenomena as referential objects.#92</s>
  </p>
  <p id="55">
    <s id="55:1">$23“Some showed their knowledge by taking the five aggregates as referential objects: their phenomenal appearance, their arising, their disintegration, [10.a] their cessation, and the acknowledgment of their cessation.</s>
    <s id="55:2">In the same way, some showed their knowledge by taking the twelve sense domains as referential objects, some by taking dependent arising as a referential object.</s>
    <s id="55:3">Some showed their knowledge by taking the four kinds of sustenance as referential objects: their phenomenal appearance, their arising, their disintegration, their cessation, and the acknowledgment of their cessation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="56">
    <s id="56:1">$24“Some showed their knowledge by taking the four noble truths as referential objects: their defining characteristic, the comprehension of suffering, the abandoning of the cause of suffering, the actualization of the cessation of suffering, and the practice of the path.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="57">
    <s id="57:1">$25“Some showed their knowledge by taking the eighteen constituents as referential objects: their phenomenal appearance, their varieties, their manifoldness, their cessation, and the actualization of their cessation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="58">
    <s id="58:1">$26“Some showed their knowledge by taking the four applications of mindfulness as referential objects: their phenomenal appearance, their adverse factors, their antidotes, their practice, their arising from having been non-arisen, their remaining after they arose, and their maintaining, resuming, or increasing.</s>
    <s id="58:2">In the same way, some showed their knowledge by taking as referential objects the four correct self-restraints, as well as the four bases of supernatural powers, the five faculties, the five forces, and the seven branches of awakening.</s>
    <s id="58:3">Some showed their knowledge by taking as referential objects the eight branches of the noble path: [10.b] their phenomenal appearance, the antidotes to their adverse factors, their practice, their arising from having been non-arisen, their remaining after they arose, and their maintaining, resuming, or increasing.#93</s>
  </p>
  <p id="59">
    <s id="59:1">$27“Then I thought to myself,</s>
    <s id="59:2">‘These venerable monks displayed their knowledge by revealing their understanding by taking various aspects of phenomena as referential objects, but</s>
    <s id="59:3">they have not perceived the ultimate, whose defining characteristic is of a single nature#94 everywhere.’</s>
    <s id="59:4">These venerable persons have conceit and, without doubt, display their knowledge under the influence of conceit.</s>
    <s id="59:5">Blessed One, at an earlier time, you spoke these words:</s>
    <s id="59:6">‘The ultimate is subtle, profound, difficult to understand, extremely difficult to understand, and characterized as being of a single nature everywhere.’</s>
    <s id="59:7">How wonderful indeed are these very words of yours!</s>
    <s id="59:8">Blessed One, if even those who practice your teaching, such as these beings who became monks, find it difficult to understand in this way the ultimate whose defining characteristic is of a single nature everywhere, what need is there to mention how difficult it is for those outsiders who do not follow your teaching?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="60">
    <s id="60:1">$28The Blessed One replied,</s>
    <s id="60:2">“So it is, Subhūti.</s>
    <s id="60:3">So it is.</s>
    <s id="60:4">I have completely and fully awakened to the ultimate that, being characterized as being of a single nature everywhere, is subtle, extremely subtle, profound, extremely profound, difficult to understand, and extremely difficult to understand.</s>
    <s id="60:5">Yet,</s>
    <s id="60:6">after I attained complete and perfect awakening, [11.a] I communicated through words, gave explanations, established distinctions, expressed myself through conventions, and imparted teachings.</s>
    <s id="60:7">One might ask why I did this.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="61">
    <s id="61:1">$29“Subhūti, it is because I teach that the ultimate is the referential object conducive to purification#95 within the aggregates, as well as within the sense domains, dependent arising, the sustenances, the truths, the constituents, the applications of mindfulness, the self-restraints, the bases of supernatural powers, the faculties, the forces, the branches of awakening, and, Subhūti, the eightfold path.</s>
    <s id="61:2">This referential object conducive to purification within the aggregates is of a single nature everywhere and its defining characteristic is not different from theirs.</s>
    <s id="61:3">It is just the same from the sense domains up to the eightfold path: the referential object conducive to purification within these various referential objects is of a single nature everywhere and its defining characteristic is not different from theirs.</s>
    <s id="61:4">Subhūti, through this approach, you should thus know that what is characterized as being of a single nature everywhere is the ultimate.#96</s>
  </p>
  <p id="62">
    <s id="62:1">$30“Moreover, Subhūti, once renunciants who practice yoga have realized in reference to a single aggregate the selflessness of phenomena, which is the ultimate reality,#97</s>
    <s id="62:2">they do not look for this ultimate reality, this selflessness, individually within the other aggregates or in the sense domains, dependent arising, the sustenances, the truths, the constituents, the applications of mindfulness, the self-restraints, the bases of supernatural powers, the faculties, the forces, the branches of awakening, and the eightfold path.</s>
    <s id="62:3">Instead,</s>
    <s id="62:4">they rely upon the nondual gnosis#98 that is in accordance with true reality.</s>
    <s id="62:5">Through this alone,#99[11.b] they infallibly ascertain and realize the ultimate, characterized as being of a single nature everywhere.</s>
    <s id="62:6">Subhūti, through this approach, you should thus know that what is characterized as being of a single nature everywhere is the ultimate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="63">
    <s id="63:1">$31“Moreover, Subhūti, if ultimate reality itself, the selflessness of phenomena, had a defining characteristic distinct [from the defining characteristics of phenomena] in the way the aggregates, the sense domains, dependent arising, the sustenances, the truths, the constituents, the applications of mindfulness, the self-restraints, the bases of supernatural powers, the faculties, the forces, the branches of awakening, and the eightfold path have defining characteristics distinct from one another, then, on account of this, ultimate reality itself, the selflessness of phenomena, would have causes and arise from causes.</s>
    <s id="63:2">If it arose from causes, it would be conditioned.</s>
    <s id="63:3">If it were the conditioned, it would not be the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="63:4">If it were not the ultimate, one would need to look for some other ultimate.</s>
    <s id="63:5">Subhūti, this ultimate, the selflessness of phenomena, does not arise from causes.</s>
    <s id="63:6">It is not conditioned.</s>
    <s id="63:7">Neither is it the case that it is not the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="63:8">One must [therefore] not look for an ultimate other than that ultimate.</s>
    <s id="63:9">Thus, whether tathāgatas manifest or not, because it is the case that it permanently and immutably abides within phenomena, only this nature of phenomena, this constituent abiding in phenomena, is constant.#100 Subhūti, for all these reasons, you should know through this approach that the ultimate is characterized as being of a single nature everywhere.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="64">
    <s id="64:1">$32“Subhūti, it is like this: although there are many varieties of forms with distinct defining characteristics within space, since space itself is free from phenomenal appearances, [12.a] devoid of conceptions, and without change, its defining characteristic is of a single nature everywhere.</s>
    <s id="64:2">Likewise, Subhūti, you should know that the ultimate is characterized as being of a single nature everywhere, within all phenomena whose defining characteristics are distinct from one another.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="65">
    <s id="65:1">$33Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="66">
    <s id="66:1">“As proclaimed by the buddhas,This ultimate is not distinct from phenomena,And its defining characteristic is everywhere of a single nature.</s>
    <s id="66:2">Those who imagine it to be distinct from phenomenaAre conceited and deluded.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="67">
    <s id="67:1">This was the chapter of Subhūti—the fourth chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="68">
    <s id="68:1">Chapter 5</s>
  </p>
  <p id="69">
    <s id="69:1">$34Then, the bodhisattva Viśālamati asked the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="69:2">“Blessed One, when bodhisattvas who are skilled in the secrets of mind, thought, and cognition are called ‘skilled in the secrets of mind, thought, and cognition,’ what does it mean?#101</s>
    <s id="69:3">When they are designated in this way, what does it refer to?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="70">
    <s id="70:1">The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="70:2">“Viśālamati, you are asking this for the benefit and happiness of many beings, out of compassion for the world, and for the welfare, benefit, and happiness of all beings, including gods and humans.</s>
    <s id="70:3">Your intention is excellent when questioning the Tathāgata on this specific point.</s>
    <s id="70:4">Therefore, listen, Viśālamati.</s>
    <s id="70:5">I will explain to you in which way bodhisattvas are skilled in the secrets of mind, thought, and cognition.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="71">
    <s id="71:1">$35“Viśālamati, when such and such beings are reborn and manifest#102 in this saṃsāra comprised of six destinies, in any class of beings or state of birth, be it egg-born, womb-born, moisture-born, [12.b] or spontaneously generated,#103 there is first a twofold appropriation: the appropriation of the physical sense faculties together with their supports, and the appropriation of mental imprints producing the elaboration of conventional expressions with regard to phenomenal appearances, names, and conceptualizations.</s>
    <s id="71:2">In dependence upon this twofold appropriation,</s>
    <s id="71:3">the mind containing all the seeds matures, merges [with the embryo], grows, increases, and expands.#104</s>
    <s id="71:4">This twofold appropriation occurs in the realm of form but it does not appear in the realm of the formless.#105</s>
  </p>
  <p id="72">
    <s id="72:1">$36“Viśālamati, this cognition is also called ‘appropriating cognition’ because it grasps and appropriates the body.</s>
    <s id="72:2">It is also called ‘subliminal cognition,’ because it dwells and lies hidden in this body, sharing a common destiny.</s>
    <s id="72:3">It is also called ‘mind,’ because it is accumulated#106 and developed by visual forms, sounds, smells, flavors, tangible objects, and phenomena.#107</s>
  </p>
  <p id="73">
    <s id="73:1">$37“Viśālamati, taking this appropriating cognition as support and basis, the six kinds of cognition,#108 that is, visual, auditive, olfactory, gustatory, tactile, and mental cognitions, arise.</s>
    <s id="73:2">Among these, a visual cognition arises on the basis of the eye, which is connected with a visual cognition and a visual form.</s>
    <s id="73:3">Simultaneously and in conformity with this visual cognition, a mental cognition that conceptualizes the object arises at the same time, having the same object.</s>
    <s id="73:4">[Likewise,] Viśālamati, an auditive, olfactory, gustatory, or tactile cognition arises on the basis of a sense faculty connected to a cognition, such as the ear, nose, tongue, or body, and a sound, smell, flavor, or tangible object.</s>
    <s id="73:5">Simultaneously and in conformity with this auditive, olfactory, gustatory, or tactile cognition, a mental cognition that conceptualizes the object arises at the same time, having the same object.</s>
    <s id="73:6">If only one visual cognition arises at one time, [13.a] then only one mental cognition that conceptualizes the object arises simultaneously, having the same object.</s>
    <s id="73:7">If two, three, four, or five cognitions arise simultaneously, then also in that case, having the same object as the group of five cognitions, only one mental cognition that conceptualizes this object arises simultaneously.#109</s>
  </p>
  <p id="74">
    <s id="74:1">$38“Viśālamati, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="74:2">If the conditions for the arising of a single wave in a large stream of water are present, then only one wave arises.#110</s>
    <s id="74:3">If the conditions for the arising of two or many waves are present, then two or many waves arise.#111 However, the river [itself] neither stops as a stream of water nor becomes exhausted.</s>
    <s id="74:4">If the conditions for the arising of a single reflection in a perfectly polished mirror are present, then only one reflection arises.#112</s>
    <s id="74:5">If the conditions for the arising of two or many reflections are present, then two or many reflections arise.#113 However,</s>
    <s id="74:6">the mirror neither transforms itself into the object corresponding to the reflection nor manifests reflections by being in close contact [with the reflected objects].#114</s>
    <s id="74:7">Viśālamati, similarly, taking this appropriating cognition as support and basis, as in the examples of the river and the mirror,</s>
    <s id="74:8">if the conditions for the arising of one visual cognition are present, then only one visual cognition arises.</s>
    <s id="74:9">If the conditions for the simultaneous arising of up to five cognitions are present, then up to five cognitions simultaneously arise.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="75">
    <s id="75:1">$39“Viśālamati, taking in this way the knowledge#115 of this doctrine as a support and basis, bodhisattvas are skilled in the secrets of mind, thought, and cognition.</s>
    <s id="75:2">Yet, when the Tathāgata designates [13.b] the bodhisattvas as skilled in the secrets of mind, thought, and cognition, they are not designated as completely skilled merely on account of this.</s>
    <s id="75:3">Viśālamati, [I call bodhisattvas ‘skilled in the ultimate’ ]as soon as#116 they, by themselves and in their own experience,#117 neither perceive the appropriation nor the appropriating cognition but [instead perceive] in accordance with the truth;</s>
    <s id="75:4">as soon as they neither perceive the subliminal nor the subliminal cognition;</s>
    <s id="75:5">neither the accumulated nor the mind;#118 neither the eye, nor the form, nor the visual cognition;</s>
    <s id="75:6">neither the ear, nor the sound, nor the auditive cognition;</s>
    <s id="75:7">neither the nose, nor the smell, nor the olfactory cognition;</s>
    <s id="75:8">neither the tongue, nor the flavor, nor the gustatory cognition;</s>
    <s id="75:9">and neither the body, nor the tangible object, nor the tactile cognition.</s>
    <s id="75:10">Viśālamati, I call bodhisattvas ‘skilled in the ultimate’ as soon as they, by themselves and in their own experience, neither perceive thought, nor phenomena, nor mental cognition but instead perceive in accordance with the truth.</s>
    <s id="75:11">Viśālamati, the Tathāgata designates as skilled in the secrets of mind, thought, and cognition the bodhisattvas who are skilled in the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="75:12">Viśālamati, for this reason, bodhisattvas are skilled in the secrets of mind, thought, and cognition.</s>
    <s id="75:13">Also, when the Tathāgata designates them as such, it is for this reason.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="76">
    <s id="76:1">$40Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="77">
    <s id="77:1">“Profound and subtle is the appropriating cognition.</s>
    <s id="77:2">Containing all the seeds, it flows like a stream of water.</s>
    <s id="77:3">I did not teach it to the immature,Lest they would imagine it to be a self.”#119</s>
  </p>
  <p id="78">
    <s id="78:1">This was the chapter of Viśālamati—[14.a] the fifth chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="79">
    <s id="79:1">Chapter 6</s>
  </p>
  <p id="80">
    <s id="80:1">$41Then, the bodhisattva Guṇākara asked the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="80:2">“Blessed One, when bodhisattvas who are skilled in the defining characteristics of phenomena are called ‘skilled in the defining characteristics of phenomena,’ what does it mean?</s>
    <s id="80:3">Moreover, when the Tathāgata designates them as such, what does it refer to?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="81">
    <s id="81:1">$42The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva Guṇākara,</s>
    <s id="81:2">“Guṇākara, for the benefit and happiness of many beings, out of compassion for the world, for the welfare, benefit, and happiness of all beings, including gods and humans, you are asking this.</s>
    <s id="81:3">Your intention is excellent when questioning the Tathāgata on this specific point.</s>
    <s id="81:4">Therefore, listen, Guṇākara,</s>
    <s id="81:5">I will explain to you in which way bodhisattvas are skilled in the defining characteristics of phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="82">
    <s id="82:1">$43“Guṇākara, the defining characteristics of phenomena are three.</s>
    <s id="82:2">What are these three?</s>
    <s id="82:3">They are the imaginary defining characteristic, the other-dependent defining characteristic, and the actual defining characteristic.#120</s>
  </p>
  <p id="83">
    <s id="83:1">$44“Guṇākara, what is the imaginary defining characteristic [of phenomena]?</s>
    <s id="83:2">It is what is nominally and conventionally posited#121 as the essence or the distinctive [characteristic] of phenomena, even just#122 in order to designate#123 [them].#124</s>
  </p>
  <p id="84">
    <s id="84:1">$45“Guṇākara, what is the other-dependent defining characteristic [of phenomena]?</s>
    <s id="84:2">It is the dependent arising of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="84:3">It is like this:</s>
    <s id="84:4">‘When this is, that arises;</s>
    <s id="84:5">because this arises, that arises.’</s>
    <s id="84:6">It is also from ‘[in dependence upon ignorance as a condition,] conditioning mental factors [arise]’ up to ‘thus, the whole great mass of suffering comes to be.’ [14.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="85">
    <s id="85:1">$46“Guṇākara, what is the actual#125 defining characteristic [of phenomena]?</s>
    <s id="85:2">It is their true reality, namely, the unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening that is finally attained by bodhisattvas as they realize this [true reality] through their diligence and correct application of mind and then become perfectly familiar with the realization of this [true reality].#126</s>
  </p>
  <p id="86">
    <s id="86:1">$47“Guṇākara, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="86:2">you should consider the imaginary defining characteristic to be just like#127 the falsity of the visual aberrations [perceived] by someone suffering from the timira visual disorder.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="87">
    <s id="87:1">“Guṇākara, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="87:2">you should consider the other-dependent defining characteristic to be just like the phenomenal appearances manifesting to this very person suffering from the timira disease, such as [actually nonexistent] hairs, flies, sesame seeds, [or patches of] blue, yellow, red, or white [in their visual field].</s>
  </p>
  <p id="88">
    <s id="88:1">“Guṇākara, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="88:2">you should consider the actual defining characteristic to be just like the original and unerring visual object seen by the same person when their vision is healthy and free from the visual aberrations resulting from the timira disease.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="89">
    <s id="89:1">$48“Guṇākara, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="89:2">when a pure crystal is in contact with something blue, it appears to be a sapphire.</s>
    <s id="89:3">Because people perceive it by mistake as a sapphire, they are deceived by it.</s>
    <s id="89:4">When this pure crystal is in contact with something red, [green, or yellow, ]it appears to be a ruby[, an emerald, [15.a] or gold].</s>
    <s id="89:5">Because people perceive it by mistake as a ruby, [an emerald, or gold, ]they are deceived by it.</s>
    <s id="89:6">When this pure crystal is in contact with something [red, ]green, [or yellow, ]it appears to be [a ruby, ]an emerald[, [15.a] or gold].</s>
    <s id="89:7">Because people perceive it by mistake as [a ruby, ]an emerald, [or gold, ]they are deceived by it.</s>
    <s id="89:8">When this pure crystal is in contact with something [red, green, or ]yellow, it appears to be [a ruby, an emerald, [15.a] or ]gold.</s>
    <s id="89:9">Because people perceive it by mistake as [a ruby, an emerald, or ]gold, they are deceived by it.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="90">
    <s id="90:1">$49“Guṇākara, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="90:2">You should consider the mental imprint of conventions in terms of an imaginary defining characteristic#128 upon the other-dependent defining characteristic to be just like the contact of colors with a pure crystal.</s>
    <s id="90:3">Thus, you should consider the perception of an imaginary defining characteristic [superimposed] on the other-dependent defining characteristic to be just like the mistaken perception of a sapphire, ruby, emerald, or gold [superimposed] on the pure crystal.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="91">
    <s id="91:1">Guṇākara, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="91:2">You should consider the other-dependent defining characteristic to be just like this pure crystal itself.</s>
    <s id="91:3">Thus, you should consider the actual defining characteristic as the permanent and immutable lack of any actuality or essence in the imaginary defining characteristic [superimposed] on the other-dependent defining characteristic,#129 just as there is permanently and immutably no actuality or essence in the defining characteristic of a sapphire, ruby, emerald, or gold [superimposed] on a pure crystal.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="92">
    <s id="92:1">$50Thus, Guṇākara, bodhisattvas distinctly perceive#130 the imaginary defining characteristic on the basis of names denoting phenomenal appearances.#131</s>
    <s id="92:2">They distinctly perceive the other-dependent defining characteristic on the basis of the erroneous conception#132 [that superimposes] an imaginary defining characteristic#133 on the other-dependent defining characteristic.#134</s>
    <s id="92:3">They distinctly perceive the actual defining characteristic on the basis of the nonexistence of any erroneous conception [that superimposes] an imaginary defining characteristic on the other-dependent defining characteristic.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="93">
    <s id="93:1">$51“Guṇākara, when bodhisattvas distinctly perceive the imaginary defining characteristic [superimposed] on the other-dependent defining characteristic of phenomena exactly as it is, they distinctly perceive the phenomena devoid of any defining characteristic exactly as they are. [15.b]</s>
    <s id="93:2">Guṇākara, when bodhisattvas distinctly perceive the other-dependent defining characteristic exactly as it is,</s>
    <s id="93:3">they distinctly perceive the phenomena characterized by affliction exactly as they are.</s>
    <s id="93:4">Guṇākara, when bodhisattvas distinctly perceive the actual defining characteristic exactly as it is,</s>
    <s id="93:5">they distinctly perceive the phenomena characterized by purification exactly as they are.</s>
    <s id="93:6">Guṇākara, when bodhisattvas distinctly perceive the phenomena devoid of a defining characteristic [superimposed] on the other-dependent defining characteristic exactly as they are,</s>
    <s id="93:7">they abandon the phenomena characterized by affliction.</s>
    <s id="93:8">Once they have abandoned the phenomena characterized by affliction, they will obtain the phenomena characterized by purification.</s>
    <s id="93:9">Guṇākara, since bodhisattvas distinctly perceive in this way the imaginary, other-dependent, and actual defining characteristics of phenomena exactly as they are, they distinctly perceive the phenomena devoid of a defining characteristic, those characterized by affliction, and those characterized by purification exactly as they are.#135</s>
    <s id="93:10">Having distinctly perceived the phenomena devoid of a defining characteristic exactly as they are,</s>
    <s id="93:11">they abandon the phenomena characterized by affliction.</s>
    <s id="93:12">Once they have abandoned the phenomena characterized by affliction,</s>
    <s id="93:13">they will obtain the phenomena characterized by purification.</s>
    <s id="93:14">For all these reasons,</s>
    <s id="93:15">bodhisattvas are skilled in the defining characteristics of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="93:16">Moreover, when the Tathāgata designates the bodhisattvas as ‘skilled in the defining characteristics of phenomena,’ it is for these reasons.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="94">
    <s id="94:1">$52Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="95">
    <s id="95:1">“Once the phenomena devoid of defining characteristics have been distinctly perceived,The phenomena characterized by affliction will be abandoned. [16.a]</s>
    <s id="95:2">Once the phenomena characterized by affliction have been abandoned,</s>
    <s id="95:3">The phenomena characterized by purification will be obtained.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="96">
    <s id="96:1">“Careless beings, overcome by wrongdoing and indulging in laziness,Do not realize the imperfection of conditioned phenomena.Falling apart in the midst of fleeting phenomena, They deserve#136 compassion.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="97">
    <s id="97:1">This was the chapter of Guṇākara —the sixth chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="98">
    <s id="98:1">Chapter 7</s>
  </p>
  <p id="99">
    <s id="99:1">$53At that time, the bodhisattva Para­mārtha­samud­gata asked the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="99:2">“Blessed One, when I was alone in a secluded place, I had the following thought:</s>
    <s id="99:3">‘The Blessed One also spoke in many ways of the defining characteristic specific to the five aggregates, mentioning the defining characteristic of their arising, disintegration, abandonment, and comprehension.#137</s>
    <s id="99:4">In the same way, he spoke of the twelve sense domains, dependent arising, and the four kinds of sustenance.</s>
    <s id="99:5">The Blessed One also spoke in many ways of the defining characteristic of the four noble truths, mentioning the comprehension of suffering, the abandoning of the cause of suffering, the actualization of the cessation of suffering, and the practice of the path.</s>
    <s id="99:6">The Blessed One also spoke in many ways of the defining characteristic specific to the eighteen constituents, mentioning their varieties, manifoldness, abandonment, and comprehension.</s>
    <s id="99:7">The Blessed One also spoke in many ways of the defining characteristic specific to the four applications of mindfulness, mentioning their adverse factors, antidotes, practice, their arising from being non-arisen, their remaining after they arose, and their maintaining, resuming, or increasing.</s>
    <s id="99:8">Similarly, he also spoke in many ways of the defining characteristic specific to the four correct self-restraints, the four bases of supernatural powers, the five faculties, the five forces, and the seven branches of awakening. [16.b]</s>
    <s id="99:9">The Blessed One also spoke in many ways of the defining characteristic specific to the eight branches of the path, mentioning their adverse factors, antidotes, and practices, their arising from being non-arisen and remaining after they arose, and their maintaining, resuming, or increasing.’</s>
  </p>
  <p id="100">
    <s id="100:1">“When the Blessed One further said, ‘All phenomena are without an essence,#138 unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa,’ what was the underlying intent of the Blessed One?</s>
    <s id="100:2">I would like to ask the Blessed One about this point: what was the Blessed One thinking when he said, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa’?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="101">
    <s id="101:1">$54The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva Para­mārtha­samud­gata,</s>
    <s id="101:2">“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, this reflection of yours arose virtuously and appropriately.</s>
    <s id="101:3">It is excellent indeed.</s>
    <s id="101:4">You are asking this for the benefit and happiness of many beings, out of compassion for the world, and for the welfare, benefit, and happiness of all beings, including gods and humans.</s>
    <s id="101:5">Your intention is excellent when questioning the Tathāgata on this specific point.</s>
    <s id="101:6">Therefore, listen, Para­mārtha­samud­gata.</s>
    <s id="101:7">I will explain to you what my underlying intent was when I declared, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, [17.a] primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’#139</s>
  </p>
  <p id="102">
    <s id="102:1">$55“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, the essencelessness of all phenomena has three aspects.</s>
    <s id="102:2">Having in mind essencelessness regarding defining characteristics, essencelessness regarding arising, and essencelessness regarding the ultimate, I thus taught what is called the essencelessness of all phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="103">
    <s id="103:1">$56“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, what is the essencelessness of all phenomena with regard to defining characteristics?</s>
    <s id="103:2">It is the imaginary defining characteristic [of phenomena].</s>
    <s id="103:3">Why?</s>
    <s id="103:4">Because as much as this defining characteristic is nominally and conventionally posited, it is not posited#140 on the basis of an essence or a distinctive [characteristic].#141 Therefore, it is called the essencelessness of all phenomena with regard to defining characteristics.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="104">
    <s id="104:1">$57“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, what is the essencelessness of all phenomena with regard to arising?</s>
    <s id="104:2">It is the other-dependent defining characteristic of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="104:3">Why?</s>
    <s id="104:4">Because this is [the defining characteristic] arising on account of causes other [than itself] and not by itself.</s>
    <s id="104:5">Therefore, it is called essencelessness with regard to arising.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="105">
    <s id="105:1">$58“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, what is the essencelessness of all phenomena with regard to the ultimate?</s>
    <s id="105:2">Phenomena arising in dependence upon causes, which lack an essence on account of lacking an essence in terms of arising and also lack an essence on account of lacking an ultimate essence.</s>
    <s id="105:3">Why?</s>
    <s id="105:4">Because, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, I showed that the referential object conducive to purification within phenomena is the ultimate, but</s>
    <s id="105:5">the other-dependent defining characteristic is not the referential object conducive to purification.</s>
    <s id="105:6">Therefore, this essencelessness is called essencelessness with regard to the ultimate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="106">
    <s id="106:1">“Moreover, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, the actual defining characteristic of phenomena should also be referred to as essencelessness with regard to the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="106:2">Why?</s>
    <s id="106:3">Because, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, the selflessness of phenomena is called the essencelessness of phenomena, which is the [17.b] ultimate, but</s>
    <s id="106:4">the ultimate is characterized by#142 the essencelessness of all phenomena.</s>
    <s id="106:5">Therefore, it is called essencelessness with regard to the ultimate.#143</s>
  </p>
  <p id="107">
    <s id="107:1">$59“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="107:2">consider essencelessness with regard to defining characteristics to be exactly like a [nonexistent] sky flower;</s>
    <s id="107:3">consider essencelessness with regard to arising, as well as essencelessness with regard to the ultimate in one of its aspects, to be exactly like a magic illusion;#144</s>
    <s id="107:4">consider essencelessness with regard to the ultimate in its other aspect, which consists in the selflessness of phenomena and pervades everything, to be exactly like space, which consists in the essencelessness of form and pervades everything.#145</s>
  </p>
  <p id="108">
    <s id="108:1">$60“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, with this threefold essencelessness in mind, I taught what is called the essencelessness of all phenomena.</s>
    <s id="108:2">Para­mārtha­samud­gata, having in mind essencelessness with regard to defining characteristics,</s>
    <s id="108:3">I taught, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’</s>
    <s id="108:4">Why?</s>
    <s id="108:5">Because, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, what lacks a specific defining characteristic is unborn.</s>
    <s id="108:6">What is unborn is unceasing.</s>
    <s id="108:7">What is unborn and unceasing is primordially in the state of peace.</s>
    <s id="108:8">What is primordially in the state of peace is naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.</s>
    <s id="108:9">For what is naturally in the state of nirvāṇa, there is nothing in the slightest that passes into the state of nirvāṇa.</s>
    <s id="108:10">Therefore, having in mind essencelessness with regard to defining characteristics,</s>
    <s id="108:11">I taught, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’</s>
  </p>
  <p id="109">
    <s id="109:1">$61“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, having in mind essencelessness with regard to the ultimate, [18.a] which is characterized by selflessness,</s>
    <s id="109:2">I taught, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’</s>
    <s id="109:3">Why?</s>
    <s id="109:4">Because essencelessness with regard to the ultimate, which is characterized by selflessness, indeed abides permanently and immutably.</s>
    <s id="109:5">As the nature of phenomena, it is unconditioned and free from all afflictions.</s>
    <s id="109:6">What permanently and immutably abides as the very nature of phenomena, being unconditioned, is unborn and unceasing due to being unconditioned.</s>
    <s id="109:7">Because it is free from all afflictions, it is primordially in the state of peace and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.#146</s>
    <s id="109:8">Therefore, having in mind essencelessness with regard to the ultimate, which is characterized by selflessness,</s>
    <s id="109:9">I taught, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’</s>
  </p>
  <p id="110">
    <s id="110:1">$62“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, I did not designate three kinds of essencelessness because those in the world of beings consider that the imaginary essence and the other-dependent essence, as well as the actual essence, are different by nature.#147 Rather,</s>
    <s id="110:2">I did so because they superimpose an imaginary essence on the other-dependent essence and the actual essence and because they designate the other-dependent essence and the actual essence as the defining characteristics of an imaginary essence.</s>
    <s id="110:3">While they designate them in this way, their minds,#148 which are saturated with designations, become confined to such designations and predisposed#149 toward them.</s>
    <s id="110:4">On this basis, they wrongly conceive the other-dependent essence and the actual essence as the defining characteristics of an imaginary essence.</s>
    <s id="110:5">[18.b]</s>
    <s id="110:6">Wrongly conceiving them in this way, with their wrong conception of the other-dependent essence as the defining characteristic of an imaginary essence acting as a cause and condition, they will give rise in the future to an other-dependent essence.#150</s>
    <s id="110:7">As a result of this, they will be afflicted by the afflictions of defilements, karma, and birth.</s>
    <s id="110:8">Because they will not pass beyond saṃsāra, they will transmigrate and wander among hell beings, animals, hungry ghosts, gods, demigods, and humans for a very long time.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="111">
    <s id="111:1">$63“Among these beings, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, some do not produce roots of virtue from the very beginning.</s>
    <s id="111:2">They do not clear obstructions or bring their mental continuums to maturity.</s>
    <s id="111:3">Their confidence in my teaching is limited and they have not accomplished the accumulations of merit and gnosis.</s>
    <s id="111:4">I impart to those beings the teaching on essencelessness with regard to arising.</s>
    <s id="111:5">Once they have heard this teaching, they understand that conditioned phenomena arising in dependence on causes are of an impermanent, unstable, and unreliable nature.</s>
    <s id="111:6">They develop aversion and repulsion towards conditioned phenomena.</s>
    <s id="111:7">Once they have done this, they turn away from wrongdoing.</s>
    <s id="111:8">Not committing any wrongdoing, they establish themselves in virtue.</s>
    <s id="111:9">With this as a cause, they produce the roots of virtue that were yet to be produced.</s>
    <s id="111:10">They clear obstructions that were yet to be cleared.</s>
    <s id="111:11">They bring their mental continuums, which were not yet mature, to maturity.</s>
    <s id="111:12">As a result, their confidence in my teaching becomes vast, and they will accomplish the accumulations of merit and gnosis.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="112">
    <s id="112:1">$64“Although such beings have produced in this way roots of virtue up to the accomplishment of the accumulation of merit and gnosis,</s>
    <s id="112:2">they [19.a] do not understand essencelessness with regard to arising just as it is, as the essencelessness with regard to defining characteristics and the essencelessness with regard to the ultimate in its two aspects.</s>
    <s id="112:3">For this reason,</s>
    <s id="112:4">they will not be completely repulsed by all conditioned phenomena, completely free from desire, or completely liberated.</s>
    <s id="112:5">They will not be completely liberated from all the afflictions of defilements, karma, and birth.</s>
    <s id="112:6">It is therefore for them that the Tathāgata imparts the teaching on the essencelessness with regard to defining characteristics and the essencelessness with regard to the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="112:7">He does so in order to make them feel repulsion towards all conditioned phenomena, as well as to free them from desire, to completely liberate them, and to take them perfectly#151 beyond the afflictions of defilements, karma, and birth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="113">
    <s id="113:1">$65“Once they have heard this teaching, they do not wrongly conceive the other-dependent essence as the defining characteristic of an imaginary essence.</s>
    <s id="113:2">As a result,</s>
    <s id="113:3">they accept the essencelessness with regard to arising as the essencelessness with regard to defining characteristics and the essencelessness with regard to the ultimate in its two aspects.</s>
    <s id="113:4">They discern and understand it exactly as it is.</s>
    <s id="113:5">It is like this:</s>
    <s id="113:6">Their minds,#152 which are no longer saturated with designations, are not confined to these designations or predisposed toward them.</s>
    <s id="113:7">As a result,</s>
    <s id="113:8">by attaining the powers of wisdom in this life and perfectly cutting off the continuity [of the aggregates] into a future existence, they will put an end to the other-dependent defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="113:9">On this basis, they will be completely repulsed by all conditioned phenomena, completely free from desire, and completely liberated.</s>
    <s id="113:10">[19.b]</s>
    <s id="113:11">They will be completely liberated from all the afflictions of defilements, karma, and birth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="114">
    <s id="114:1">$66“Moreover, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, even those belonging to the lineage of the hearers’ vehicle attain nirvāṇa, the unsurpassable happiness, through this very path and journey,#153</s>
    <s id="114:2">as do those belonging to the lineage of the solitary realizers’ vehicle and the lineage of the tathāgatas.</s>
    <s id="114:3">This is why</s>
    <s id="114:4">it is the single path of purification for hearers, solitary realizers, and bodhisattvas.</s>
    <s id="114:5">Since there is only a single purification, there is no other.</s>
    <s id="114:6">Therefore, with this in mind, I taught the Single Vehicle.</s>
    <s id="114:7">Yet,</s>
    <s id="114:8">it is not the case that those in the world of beings are not of various types corresponding to their capacities, be they weak, average, or sharp in accordance with their nature.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="115">
    <s id="115:1">$67“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, even if they were to exert themselves as all buddhas did,#154 individuals belonging to the hearers’ lineage with the state of peace as their sole journey could not reach the heart of awakening and attain the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening.</s>
    <s id="115:2">Why?</s>
    <s id="115:3">Because, having limited compassion and a great fear of suffering, they belong to a lineage that is by nature inferior.</s>
    <s id="115:4">Thus, having limited compassion, they avoid striving for beings’ welfare.</s>
    <s id="115:5">Being afraid of suffering, they stay clear from the conditioning process of the mental factors.#155</s>
    <s id="115:6">However, I did not teach that avoiding striving for beings’ welfare and staying clear from the conditioning process of the mental factors was the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening.</s>
    <s id="115:7">Therefore, these individuals are called those who have the state of peace as their sole journey.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="116">
    <s id="116:1">$68“I taught that hearers who evolve toward awakening belong to the [20.a] category of bodhisattvas</s>
    <s id="116:2">because, liberated from the obscuration of defilements and inspired by the tathāgatas, they liberate their minds from the obscuration of cognitive objects.</s>
    <s id="116:3">It is [only] because they first liberated themselves from the obscuration of defilements for their own sake that the Tathāgata designated them as the lineage of hearers.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="117">
    <s id="117:1">$69“Thus, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, there are beings with various degrees of confidence in my Dharma and my Vinaya, which are well proclaimed, well imparted, pure in their intention, and well communicated.</s>
    <s id="117:2">In this teaching, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, the Tathāgata, having in mind the three kinds of essencelessness, teaches through a discourse of provisional meaning:</s>
    <s id="117:3">‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’</s>
  </p>
  <p id="118">
    <s id="118:1">$70“Among such beings, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, some have produced roots of virtue, purified their obscurations, and brought their mental continuum to maturity.</s>
    <s id="118:2">They have much confidence in my teaching and have accomplished the accumulations of merit and gnosis.</s>
    <s id="118:3">Once they have heard my teaching,</s>
    <s id="118:4">they understand my explanations in accordance with my underlying intent exactly as it is.</s>
    <s id="118:5">Moreover, they recognize that this teaching is the truth.#156</s>
    <s id="118:6">Through their wisdom, they realize its meaning exactly as it is.</s>
    <s id="118:7">By also engaging in the practice of this realization, they will very quickly attain the ultimate state.</s>
    <s id="118:8">They will develop faith in these teachings, and think, ‘Amazing!</s>
    <s id="118:9">The Blessed One is completely and perfectly awakened.</s>
    <s id="118:10">Through him, one becomes perfectly awakened with respect to all phenomena.’</s>
  </p>
  <p id="119">
    <s id="119:1">$71“Among such beings, some have not produced roots of virtue, purified their obscurations, and brought their mental continuums to maturity.</s>
    <s id="119:2">Their confidence in my teaching is limited and [20.b] they have not accomplished the accumulations of merit and gnosis.</s>
    <s id="119:3">They are honest and sincere.</s>
    <s id="119:4">Unable to evaluate and refute#157 [others’ views], they do not consider their own as supreme.</s>
    <s id="119:5">Once they have heard my teaching,</s>
    <s id="119:6">although they do not understand my explanations in accordance with my underlying intent exactly as it is,</s>
    <s id="119:7">they still develop confidence and faith in these teachings:</s>
    <s id="119:8">‘The Tathāgata’s discourse is profound and has the appearance of profundity.</s>
    <s id="119:9">[Because] emptiness is the topic of this discourse, it is difficult to perceive and difficult to understand.</s>
    <s id="119:10">Being beyond judgment, it does not belong to the domain of speculation.</s>
    <s id="119:11">It can [only] be known by intelligent scholars well versed in the subtle.’#158</s>
    <s id="119:12">They think, ‘We do not understand the meaning of this sūtra and these teachings that were taught by the Blessed One.</s>
    <s id="119:13">Profound is the awakening of the Buddha and the nature of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="119:14">Only the Tathāgata understands them.</s>
    <s id="119:15">We, however, do not.</s>
    <s id="119:16">The Dharma taught by the tathāgatas arises according to the various inclinations of beings.</s>
    <s id="119:17">Their gnosis#159 and perception are infinite, whereas ours are merely like the [shallow] hoofprints left by a cow.’</s>
    <s id="119:18">Filled with devotion for these discourses, they also write them down.</s>
    <s id="119:19">Having written them down, they also keep them in mind, read them, propagate them, venerate them, expound them, recite them, and chant them aloud.</s>
    <s id="119:20">However,</s>
    <s id="119:21">because they do not understand these profound teachings in accordance with my underlying intent, they are unable to engage themselves in the various aspects of practice.</s>
    <s id="119:22">As a consequence of this, they will further develop their accumulation of merit and gnosis, and</s>
    <s id="119:23">those whose mental continuums are still immature will bring them to maturity.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="120">
    <s id="120:1">$72“Other beings have not perfectly completed these stages up to the great accumulation of merit and gnosis. [21.a] They are dishonest and insincere.</s>
    <s id="120:2">Capable of evaluating and refuting [others’ views], they consider their own as supreme.</s>
    <s id="120:3">Once they have heard my teaching,</s>
    <s id="120:4">they do not understand my profound explanations in accordance with my underlying intent exactly as it is.</s>
    <s id="120:5">Although they have confidence in this teaching, they wrongly conceive it according to its literal meaning:</s>
    <s id="120:6">‘All phenomena are only without an essence, only unborn, only unceasing, only primordially in the state of peace, and only naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’</s>
    <s id="120:7">As a consequence of this, they acquire the view that all phenomena are inexistent and the view that they are without defining characteristics.</s>
    <s id="120:8">Then, once they have acquired these views, they negate all phenomena by [negating] all defining characteristics, thereby negating the imaginary defining characteristic as well as the other-dependent and actual defining characteristics.</s>
    <s id="120:9">Why is it said that they negate all three defining characteristics?</s>
    <s id="120:10">Because, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, if the other-dependent and actual defining characteristics are accepted, then the imaginary defining characteristic also will be distinctly perceived.</s>
    <s id="120:11">Now, those who consider the other-dependent and actual defining characteristics as inexistent have already negated the imaginary defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="120:12">This is why they are called those who negate all three defining characteristics.</s>
    <s id="120:13">They consider my teaching to be the truth while considering some nonsense to be its meaning.</s>
    <s id="120:14">Those who consider my teaching to be the truth while considering some nonsense to be its meaning cling to my teaching as the truth while at the same time clinging to some nonsense as its meaning.</s>
    <s id="120:15">Since they have confidence in my teaching, they will progress by developing virtuous qualities.</s>
    <s id="120:16">However,</s>
    <s id="120:17">because they wrongly conceive some nonsense to be the meaning of my teaching, they will stray from wisdom.</s>
    <s id="120:18">Straying from wisdom, [21.b] they will stray from the vast and immeasurable virtuous qualities.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="121">
    <s id="121:1">$73“Others hear from those beings that my teaching is the truth while some nonsense is its meaning.</s>
    <s id="121:2">Then,</s>
    <s id="121:3">delighted by this view, they accept that my teaching is the truth and some nonsense is its meaning.</s>
    <s id="121:4">Thus, they wrongly conceive my teaching as the truth with some nonsense as its meaning.</s>
    <s id="121:5">As a consequence of this, you should know that they will likewise stray from virtuous qualities.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="122">
    <s id="122:1">$74“Others who take no delight in this view are overcome by fear and anxiety when they hear that all phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.</s>
    <s id="122:2">They then say, ‘These are not the words of the Buddha but the words of Māra!’</s>
    <s id="122:3">Thinking in this way, they reject this discourse, disparage it, denigrate it, and criticize it.</s>
    <s id="122:4">As a consequence of this, they will obtain the great misfortune as well as the great karmic obscuration [of rejecting the truth].#160</s>
    <s id="122:5">This is precisely why I said, ‘Those who mislead the multitude of beings into obtaining the great karmic obscuration, who consider all defining characteristics as inexistent and teach some nonsense as the meaning of my teaching, are burdened with great karmic obscuration [of rejecting the truth].</s>
  </p>
  <p id="123">
    <s id="123:1">$75“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, among such beings, some have not produced roots of virtue, purified their obscurations, and brought their mental continuum to maturity.</s>
    <s id="123:2">Their confidence in my teaching is limited, and they have not accomplished the accumulations of merit and gnosis.</s>
    <s id="123:3">They are dishonest and insincere.</s>
    <s id="123:4">Although they are unable to evaluate and refute [others’ views], they consider their own as supreme.</s>
    <s id="123:5">When they hear my teaching,</s>
    <s id="123:6">they neither understand my explanations in accordance with my underlying intent exactly as it is, nor do they develop confidence in this teaching.</s>
    <s id="123:7">They accept that my teaching is not the truth and its meaning is some nonsense.</s>
    <s id="123:8">They say, ‘These are not the words of the Buddha [22.a] but the words of Māra!’</s>
    <s id="123:9">Thinking in this way, they reject this discourse, disparage it, denigrate it, criticize it, and distort [its meaning].</s>
    <s id="123:10">In many ways, they apply themselves to discarding, undermining, and subverting this discourse, considering as enemies those who are devoted to it.</s>
    <s id="123:11">From the very beginning, they are affected by the karmic obscuration [of rejecting the truth].</s>
    <s id="123:12">As a consequence of this, they also cause [others] to be obscured by this karmic obscuration.</s>
    <s id="123:13">Although it is easy to determine the beginning of this karmic obscuration, it is difficult to know how many myriad eons it will last.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="124">
    <s id="124:1">“Thus, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, those are the various degrees of confidence in my Dharma and my Vinaya,#161 which are well proclaimed, well imparted, pure in their intention, and well communicated.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="125">
    <s id="125:1">$76Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="126">
    <s id="126:1">“All phenomena are without an essence, unborn,Unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, And naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.What wise person would say this without an underlying intent?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="127">
    <s id="127:1">“I have spoken of essencelessness With regard to defining characteristics, arising, and the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="127:2">No wise person who understands my underlying intentWill travel the path leading to corruption.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="128">
    <s id="128:1">“There is only one path of purification for all beings,As there is only one purification, not two.</s>
    <s id="128:2">This is why, even if there are various lineages of beings, I proclaimed the Single Vehicle.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="129">
    <s id="129:1">“In the world of beings, innumerable areThe solitary beings who attain nirvāṇa,While rare are those who have attained nirvāṇaAnd possess the energy and compassion to not turn away from beings. [22.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="130">
    <s id="130:1">“Subtle, inconceivable, and undifferentiatedIs the uncontaminated domain of those who are liberated.Nondual and inexpressible, blissful and immutable,It is the accomplishment of all [intentions], the release from all suffering and defilements.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="131">
    <s id="131:1">$77Then, the bodhisattva Para­mārtha­samud­gata said to the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="131:2">“Blessed One, the speech expounding the underlying intent of the buddhas is subtle, extremely subtle, profound, extremely profound, difficult to understand, and extremely difficult to understand.</s>
    <s id="131:3">How marvelous, how wonderful it is!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="132">
    <s id="132:1">“This is how I understand the meaning of the words spoken by the Blessed One:</s>
    <s id="132:2">The phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization,#162 is nominally and conventionally posited as an essential characteristic or a distinctive characteristic,#163 for example as the aggregate of form, its arising, its cessation, its abandonment, or the comprehension of this aggregate.</s>
    <s id="132:3">What is posited in this way is the imaginary defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="132:4">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to essencelessness with regard to the defining characteristics of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="132:5">The phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is the other-dependent defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="132:6">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to essencelessness with regard to both the arising of phenomena and the ultimate in one of its aspects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="133">
    <s id="133:1">“This is how I understand the meaning of the words spoken by the Blessed One:</s>
    <s id="133:2">this very phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is devoid of any actuality or essence as that which has an imaginary defining characteristic.#164</s>
    <s id="133:3">[23.a] On account of this, this essencelessness or selflessness of phenomena, true reality, the referential object conducive to purification, is the actual defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="133:4">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to the essencelessness of phenomena with regard to the ultimate in its other aspect.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="134">
    <s id="134:1">“One should proceed in exactly the same way with the remaining aggregates as well as with each of the twelve sense domains, the twelve factors of conditioned existence, the four kinds of sustenance, and the six and eighteen constituents.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="135">
    <s id="135:1">$78“This is how I understand the meaning of the words spoken by the Blessed One:</s>
    <s id="135:2">The phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is nominally and conventionally posited as an essential characteristic or a distinctive characteristic, for example as the noble truth of suffering or the comprehension of suffering.</s>
    <s id="135:3">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to essencelessness with regard to the defining characteristics of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="135:4">The phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is the other-dependent defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="135:5">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to essencelessness with regard to both the arising of phenomena and the ultimate in one of its aspects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="136">
    <s id="136:1">“This is how I understand the meaning of the words spoken by the Blessed One:</s>
    <s id="136:2">This very phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is devoid of any actuality or essence as that which has an imaginary defining characteristic.#165</s>
    <s id="136:3">[23.b] On account of this, this essencelessness or selflessness of phenomena, true reality, the referential object conducive to purification, is the actual defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="136:4">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to the essencelessness of phenomena with regard to the ultimate in its other aspect.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="137">
    <s id="137:1">“As with the noble truth of suffering, one should proceed in exactly the same way with the other truths.</s>
    <s id="137:2">As with the truths, so one should proceed in exactly the same way with each of the applications of mindfulness, the self-restraints, the bases of supernatural powers, the faculties, the forces, the branches of awakening, and the branches of the path.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="138">
    <s id="138:1">$79“This is how I understand the meaning of the words spoken by the Blessed One:</s>
    <s id="138:2">The phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is nominally and conventionally posited as an essential characteristic or a distinctive characteristic, for example as correct concentration,#166 its adverse factors and antidotes, its practice, its arising from being non-arisen, its remaining after it arose, and its maintaining, resuming, increasing, or expanding.</s>
    <s id="138:3">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to essencelessness with regard to the defining characteristics of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="138:4">The phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is the other-dependent defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="138:5">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to essencelessness with regard to both the arising of phenomena and the ultimate in one of its aspects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="139">
    <s id="139:1">“This is how I [24.a] understand the meaning of the words spoken by the Blessed One:</s>
    <s id="139:2">This very phenomenal appearance of conditioned phenomena, namely, the basis of the imaginary defining characteristic, the object of conceptualization, is devoid of any actuality or essence as that which has an imaginary defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="139:3">On account of this, this essencelessness or selflessness of phenomena, true reality, the referential object conducive to purification, is the actual defining characteristic.</s>
    <s id="139:4">For this reason, Blessed One, you referred to the essencelessness of phenomena with regard to the ultimate in its other aspect.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="140">
    <s id="140:1">$80“Blessed One, thus it is said, for example, that dried ginger should be added to all medicinal powders and elixirs.</s>
    <s id="140:2">Likewise, this teaching of definitive meaning expounded by#167 the Blessed One in reference to the statement, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa,’#168 should also be added to all the discourses of provisional meaning.#169</s>
  </p>
  <p id="141">
    <s id="141:1">“Blessed One, it is like this: for example, the canvas for a painting, whether blue, yellow, red, or white, is identical for all painted figures and thus perfectly clarifies their contours.</s>
    <s id="141:2">Likewise, this teaching of definitive meaning expounded by the Blessed One in reference to the statement, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa,’ is identical in all discourses of provisional meaning and thus perfectly clarifies their interpretable intent.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="142">
    <s id="142:1">“Blessed One, it is like this: for example, adding clarified butter to all sorts of stews, meat dishes, and porridge is delicious.</s>
    <s id="142:2">Likewise, it is delightful to add to all discourses of provisional meaning this teaching of definitive meaning expounded by the Blessed One in reference to the statement, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’ [24.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="143">
    <s id="143:1">“Blessed One, it is like this: for example, space is identical everywhere and, [being empty and free from all obstruction,] does not hinder any endeavor.</s>
    <s id="143:2">Likewise, this teaching of definitive meaning expounded by the Blessed One in reference to the statement, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa,’ is identical in all discourses of provisional meaning and does not hinder any endeavor in the course of the hearers’, solitary realizers’, or bodhisattvas’ vehicle.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="144">
    <s id="144:1">$81Following these words, the Blessed One complimented the bodhisattva Para­mārtha­samud­gata:</s>
    <s id="144:2">“Excellent, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, this is excellent!</s>
    <s id="144:3">You have understood my explanation in accordance with the Tathāgata’s underlying intent.</s>
    <s id="144:4">Your examples of the dried ginger, painting, clarified butter, and space perfectly illustrated its point.</s>
    <s id="144:5">Para­mārtha­samud­gata, so it is, and not otherwise.</s>
    <s id="144:6">Therefore, keep in mind this teaching in this way.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="145">
    <s id="145:1">$82Then, the bodhisattva Para­mārtha­samud­gata spoke again to the Blessed One:</s>
    <s id="145:2">“In the deer park of Ṛṣivadana in Vārāṇasī, the Blessed One first set in motion the wonderful wheel of Dharma by teaching the four noble truths to those who were engaged in the hearers’ vehicle.</s>
    <s id="145:3">Not a single god or human in the world had previously ever turned such a wheel of Dharma.</s>
    <s id="145:4">However,</s>
    <s id="145:5">this turning of the Dharma wheel by the Blessed One was surpassable and adapted to the circumstances.</s>
    <s id="145:6">Being of provisional meaning,#170 it became a topic of dispute.</s>
    <s id="145:7">Then,</s>
    <s id="145:8">for those who were engaged in the Great Vehicle, [25.a] you turned the second, even more wonderful, wheel of Dharma in the form of a teaching on emptiness:</s>
    <s id="145:9">‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa.’</s>
    <s id="145:10">However,</s>
    <s id="145:11">this turning of the Dharma wheel by the Blessed One was surpassable and adapted to the circumstances.</s>
    <s id="145:12">Being of provisional meaning, it became a topic of dispute.</s>
    <s id="145:13">Then,</s>
    <s id="145:14">for those who were engaged in all vehicles,#171 you turned the third wonderful Dharma wheel of excellent discernment in reference to the statement, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and by nature in the state of nirvāṇa.’#172</s>
    <s id="145:15">This turning of the Dharma wheel by the Blessed One was unsurpassable and not limited to the circumstances.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="146">
    <s id="146:1">$83“Blessed One, when sons or daughters of noble family have heard the teaching of definitive meaning taught by the Blessed One in reference to the statement, ‘All phenomena are without an essence, unborn, unceasing, primordially in the state of peace, and naturally in the state of nirvāṇa,’</s>
    <s id="146:2">they develop devotion for this teaching and commission its transcription into writing.</s>
    <s id="146:3">Once it has been put into writing, they keep it in mind, read it, venerate it, propagate it, expound it, chant it aloud, contemplate it, and apply it in their practice.</s>
    <s id="146:4">As they do so, how much merit will they produce?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="147">
    <s id="147:1">$84The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="147:2">“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, these sons and daughters of noble family will produce immeasurable and [25.b] incalculable merit.</s>
    <s id="147:3">Although it is difficult to illustrate this with examples, I will briefly explain it to you.</s>
    <s id="147:4">Para­mārtha­samud­gata, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="147:5">Compared to the amount of earth, the amount of dirt at the tip of a fingernail does not come close to a hundredth, a thousandth, a one hundred thousandth of it, or anything implying calculation, partition, numeration, analogy, or comparison.</s>
    <s id="147:6">Compared to the amount of water contained in the four great oceans, the amount of water contained in the hoofprint of an ox does not come close to a hundredth, a thousandth, a one hundred thousandth of it, or anything implying calculation, partition, numeration, analogy, or comparison.</s>
    <s id="147:7">Likewise, Para­mārtha­samud­gata, compared to the amount of merit accumulated by developing confidence in my teaching of definitive meaning up to applying it in one’s practice, the amount of merit accumulated by developing confidence in my teaching of provisional meaning . . . up to applying it in one’s practice does not come close to a hundredth, a thousandth, a one hundred thousandth of it, or anything implying calculation, partition, numeration, analogy, or comparison.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="148">
    <s id="148:1">$85The bodhisattva Para­mārtha­samud­gata inquired,</s>
    <s id="148:2">“Blessed One, what is the name of this teaching as a Dharma discourse that unravels the Tathāgata’s intent?#173 How should I keep it in mind?”#174</s>
  </p>
  <p id="149">
    <s id="149:1">The Blessed One answered:</s>
    <s id="149:2">“Para­mārtha­samud­gata, this is a teaching of definitive meaning on the ultimate.</s>
    <s id="149:3">Therefore, keep it in mind as The Teaching of Definitive Meaning on the Ultimate.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="150">
    <s id="150:1">As the Blessed One expounded this teaching of definitive meaning on the ultimate, six hundred thousand beings produced the mind directed at the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening;#175</s>
    <s id="150:2">three hundred thousand hearers purified the Dharma eye from impurities and contaminations;</s>
    <s id="150:3">one hundred and fifty hearers who were without attachment liberated their minds from all outflows;</s>
    <s id="150:4">and</s>
    <s id="150:5">seventy-five thousand bodhisattvas attained the acceptance that phenomena are non-arisen. [26.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="151">
    <s id="151:1">This was the chapter of the bodhisattva Para­mārtha­samud­gata—the seventh chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="152">
    <s id="152:1">Chapter 8</s>
  </p>
  <p id="153">
    <s id="153:1">$86Then, the bodhisattva Maitreya asked a question to the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="153:2">“Blessed One, when bodhisattvas practice mental stillness and insight in the Great Vehicle, what is their support and basis?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="154">
    <s id="154:1">The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="154:2">“Maitreya, their support and basis are the discourses teaching Dharma and the constant aspiration to attain the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="155">
    <s id="155:1">$87“The Blessed One taught that four things are the referential objects of mental stillness and insight: the image with conceptualization;</s>
    <s id="155:2">the image without conceptualization;</s>
    <s id="155:3">the point where phenomena end;</s>
    <s id="155:4">and the accomplishment of the goal.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="156">
    <s id="156:1">“Blessed One, how many referential objects of mental stillness are there?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="157">
    <s id="157:1">“There is [only] one, namely, the image without conceptualization.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="158">
    <s id="158:1">“How many are the referential objects of insight?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="159">
    <s id="159:1">“There is only one, namely, the image with conceptualization.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="160">
    <s id="160:1">“How many are the referential objects of both combined?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="161">
    <s id="161:1">“There are two, namely, the point where phenomena end and the accomplishment of the goal.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="162">
    <s id="162:1">$88“Blessed One, once bodhisattvas have taken as a support and basis these four things that are the referential objects of mental stillness and insight,</s>
    <s id="162:2">how do they dedicate themselves to mental stillness?</s>
    <s id="162:3">How do they become skilled in the practice of insight?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="163">
    <s id="163:1">“Maitreya, I have given to the bodhisattvas discourses teaching Dharma in the following twelve collections of teachings: sūtras, discourses in prose and verse, prophecies, poetic discourses, aphorisms, discourses for specific beings, narratives, parables, discourses on previous lives, extensive discourses, teachings on miracles, and instructions. [26.b] Once bodhisattvas have properly heard these explanations, once they have memorized them well, recited them, examined them, and understood them by means of discernment,</s>
    <s id="163:2">they remain alone in seclusion and settle themselves in a state of inner absorption.</s>
    <s id="163:3">Then, they direct their attention in that (1) they direct their attention toward the teachings they have properly contemplated#176 and (2) continuously direct their attention inwardly toward the mind that is directing attention.</s>
    <s id="163:4">As they repeatedly engage themselves in this way, their bodies and minds become flexible.</s>
    <s id="163:5">The occurrence of this physical and mental flexibility is what is called mental stillness.</s>
    <s id="163:6">This is how bodhisattvas dedicate themselves to mental stillness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="164">
    <s id="164:1">$89“Once they have obtained#177 this physical and mental flexibility, they settle in this very state and abandon some aspects of mind [corresponding to mental stillness].#178 Then,</s>
    <s id="164:2">they apply themselves to analyzing the image that is the object of their concentration according to the teachings they have properly contemplated.</s>
    <s id="164:3">Differentiating, discerning, considering, and examining in this way the cognitive aspects of the image that is the object of their concentration, accepting and wishing to do so, and distinguishing, scrutinizing, and investigating [this discerning mind in the same way] is what is called [the practice of] insight.</s>
    <s id="164:4">This is how bodhisattvas are skilled in insight.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="165">
    <s id="165:1">$90“Blessed One, when bodhisattvas direct their attention inwardly toward the mind that takes the mind as its referential object but have not yet attained physical and mental flexibility, what do you call their practice of directing attention?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="166">
    <s id="166:1">“Maitreya, this is not yet mental stillness.</s>
    <s id="166:2">So you should refer to it as a practice aspiring to mental stillness.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="167">
    <s id="167:1">“Blessed One, when bodhisattvas direct their attention toward the image that is the object of their concentration according to the teachings they have properly contemplated, but they have not yet attained physical and mental flexibility, what do you call their practice of [27.a] directing attention?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="168">
    <s id="168:1">“Maitreya, this is not yet insight.</s>
    <s id="168:2">So you should refer to it as a practice aspiring to insight.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="169">
    <s id="169:1">$91“Blessed One, should we refer to the path of mental stillness and the path of insight as being distinct or indistinct from one another?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="170">
    <s id="170:1">“Maitreya, we should refer to them as neither distinct nor indistinct.</s>
    <s id="170:2">Why are they not distinct?</s>
    <s id="170:3">Because mental stillness takes mind, which is the referential object of insight, as its object.</s>
    <s id="170:4">Why are they not indistinct?</s>
    <s id="170:5">Because insight takes a conceptual image as its referential object.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="171">
    <s id="171:1">$92“Blessed One, what image do bodhisattvas focus on as their object of concentration?</s>
    <s id="171:2">Should we consider it as distinct from mind or not?”#179</s>
  </p>
  <p id="172">
    <s id="172:1">“Maitreya, we must consider that it is not distinct from mind.</s>
    <s id="172:2">Why?</s>
    <s id="172:3">Because this image is merely a representation.</s>
    <s id="172:4">Maitreya, I have explained that cognition is constituted#180 by the mere representation that is the referential object [of this cognition].”#181</s>
  </p>
  <p id="173">
    <s id="173:1">“Blessed One, if this image that is the object of concentration is not distinct from the mind,</s>
    <s id="173:2">how does this very mind investigate itself?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="174">
    <s id="174:1">“Maitreya, [ultimately] no phenomenon whatsoever investigates any phenomenon at all.</s>
    <s id="174:2">However,</s>
    <s id="174:3">the mind that arises as [if it were conscious of an object] appears as [if it were investigating itself].</s>
    <s id="174:4">Maitreya, it is like this:</s>
    <s id="174:5">based on a form [in front of a mirror], you see that same form on the clear surface of this mirror and realize that you are seeing a reflection, an image</s>
    <s id="174:6">in which this reflection and the form [it is based on] appear to be distinct objects.</s>
    <s id="174:7">Likewise, the mind arising as [if it were conscious of an object] and what is called its image, the object of concentration, appear as if they were distinct objects.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="175">
    <s id="175:1">$93“Blessed One, should we say that mental images naturally present to beings, such as the appearance of material form and so forth, [27.b] are also not distinct from mind?”#182</s>
  </p>
  <p id="176">
    <s id="176:1">“Maitreya, we should say that they are not distinct.</s>
    <s id="176:2">However,</s>
    <s id="176:3">foolish beings with erroneous ideas do not understand just as it is that [mental] images are mere representations.</s>
    <s id="176:4">As a consequence, their minds are mistaken.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="177">
    <s id="177:1">$94“Blessed One, when do the bodhisattvas practice only insight?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="178">
    <s id="178:1">“Whenever they direct their attention#183 toward mental appearances#184 without interruption.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="179">
    <s id="179:1">“When do the bodhisattvas practice only mental stillness?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="180">
    <s id="180:1">“Whenever they direct their attention toward the unimpeded mind without interruption.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="181">
    <s id="181:1">“When do they combine both insight and mental stillness and unite them evenly?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="182">
    <s id="182:1">“Whenever they direct their attention toward the one-pointedness of mind.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="183">
    <s id="183:1">“Blessed One, what is a mental appearance?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="184">
    <s id="184:1">“Maitreya, this is the referential object of insight, the conceptual image that is the object of concentration.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="185">
    <s id="185:1">“What is the unimpeded mind?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="186">
    <s id="186:1">“Maitreya, it is the referential object of mental stillness, the mind that takes the image as an object.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="187">
    <s id="187:1">“What is one-pointedness of mind?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="188">
    <s id="188:1">“[One-pointedness of mind is] realizing in regard to the image that is the object of concentration, ‘This is merely a representation,’ and, on realizing that, directing one’s attention toward true reality.”#185</s>
  </p>
  <p id="189">
    <s id="189:1">$95“Blessed One, how many kinds of insight are there?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="190">
    <s id="190:1">“Maitreya, there are three: insight arising from phenomenal appearance, insight arising from inquiry, and insight arising from awakening.”#186</s>
  </p>
  <p id="191">
    <s id="191:1">“What is insight arising from phenomenal appearance?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="192">
    <s id="192:1">“It is the insight in which attention is directed exclusively toward a conceptual image, the object of concentration.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="193">
    <s id="193:1">“What is insight arising from inquiry?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="194">
    <s id="194:1">“It is the insight in which attention is directed in order to perfectly understand whatever phenomena were not yet understood by means of wisdom.”#187[28.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="195">
    <s id="195:1">“What is insight arising from awakening?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="196">
    <s id="196:1">“It is the insight in which attention is directed on whatever phenomena one perfectly understood by means of wisdom in order to attain the happiness of liberation.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="197">
    <s id="197:1">$96“How many kinds of mental stillness are there?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="198">
    <s id="198:1">“There are three kinds of mental stillness corresponding to the unimpeded mind.</s>
    <s id="198:2">Maitreya, it is also said to be of eight kinds: the first, second, third, and fourth meditative absorptions, the domain of the infinity of space, the domain of infinite cognition, the domain of nothingness, and the domain of neither conception nor lack of conception.</s>
    <s id="198:3">It is also of four kinds: immeasurable loving-kindness, immeasurable compassion, immeasurable joy, and immeasurable equanimity.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="199">
    <s id="199:1">$97“Blessed One, you have mentioned ‘mental stillness and insight that are established in Dharma’ and ‘mental stillness and insight that are not established in Dharma.’</s>
    <s id="199:2">What do these terms mean?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="200">
    <s id="200:1">“Maitreya, the mental stillness and insight that are established in Dharma are the mental stillness and insight whose object is in agreement with phenomenal appearance as presented in the teachings that bodhisattvas have understood and contemplated.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="201">
    <s id="201:1">“You should know that the mental stillness and insight that are not established in Dharma are the mental stillness and insight whose object, being unrelated to the teachings that bodhisattvas have understood and contemplated, is based on other instructions or precepts, such as taking as referential objects putrefying or festering corpses as well as any other similar objects, the impermanence of all conditioned phenomena, the suffering [inherent to all conditioned phenomena], the selflessness of all phenomena, and nirvāṇa as the state of peace.#188</s>
  </p>
  <p id="202">
    <s id="202:1">“Maitreya, regarding this, I consider those bodhisattvas who follow the teaching based on the mental stillness and insight established in Dharma to possess sharp faculties.</s>
    <s id="202:2">As for those faithfully following the teaching based on the mental stillness and insight that are not established in Dharma, I consider them to possess inferior faculties.” [28.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="203">
    <s id="203:1">$98“Blessed One, you also mentioned ‘the mental stillness and insight with a specific#189 teaching as a referential object’ and ‘the mental stillness and insight with a universal teaching as a referential object.’</s>
    <s id="203:2">What do these terms mean?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="204">
    <s id="204:1">“Maitreya, suppose that bodhisattvas practice the mental stillness and insight that take as a referential object an individual teaching, such as a specific discourse, among all the teachings they have understood and contemplated.</s>
    <s id="204:2">This is called mental stillness and insight with a specific teaching as a referential object.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="205">
    <s id="205:1">Now, suppose that bodhisattvas unify, condense, subsume, or gather teachings from various discourses into a single one,</s>
    <s id="205:2">thinking that all these teachings converge toward true reality, lean toward true reality, and tend toward true reality;</s>
    <s id="205:3">converge toward awakening, lean toward awakening, and tend toward awakening;</s>
    <s id="205:4">converge toward nirvāṇa, lean toward nirvāṇa, and tend toward nirvāṇa;</s>
    <s id="205:5">and converge toward a shift in one’s basis of existence,#190 lean toward a shift in one’s basis of existence, and tend toward a shift in one’s basis of existence.</s>
    <s id="205:6">Thinking that all these teachings actually refer to the immeasurable and infinite virtuous truth,#191 they direct their attention [toward their referential object].</s>
    <s id="205:7">This is [called] mental stillness and insight with a universal teaching as a referential object.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="206">
    <s id="206:1">$99“Blessed One, you also mentioned mental stillness and insight ‘with a fairly universal teaching as a referential object,’ ‘with a highly universal teaching as a referential object,’ and ‘with an infinitely universal teaching as a referential object.’</s>
    <s id="206:2">What do these terms mean?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="207">
    <s id="207:1">“Maitreya, suppose the bodhisattvas gather together [the meaning of] each of the twelve collections of my teaching, from the sūtras up to the extensive discourses, the teachings on miracles, and the instructions. [29.a] Having done so, they direct their attention toward this referential object.</s>
    <s id="207:2">This should be known as the mental stillness and insight with a fairly universal teaching as a referential object.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="208">
    <s id="208:1">When the bodhisattvas gather together#192 all the teachings or discourses they have understood and contemplated and then direct their attention onto this referential object, this should be known as the mental stillness and insight with a highly universal teaching as a referential object.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="209">
    <s id="209:1">“When the bodhisattvas gather together the teachings imparted by the tathāgatas that refer to the infinite truth,#193 the infinite words and letters expressing it, and the ever-increasing infinite wisdom and eloquence of the tathāgatas and then direct their attention toward this referential object, this should be known as the mental stillness and insight with an infinitely universal teaching as a referential object.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="210">
    <s id="210:1">$100“Blessed One, how do bodhisattvas obtain mental stillness and insight with a universal teaching as a referential object?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="211">
    <s id="211:1">“Maitreya, you should know that they obtain them through five causes:</s>
    <s id="211:2">(1) At the time of directing their attention, they destroy all supports of corruption in every moment.</s>
    <s id="211:3">(2) After giving up the variety of conditioned phenomena, they rejoice in the joy of Dharma.</s>
    <s id="211:4">(3) They perfectly know the immeasurable and unceasing brilliance of Dharma in the ten directions.</s>
    <s id="211:5">(4) They bring together, without conceptualizing them, the phenomenal appearances that are imbued with the accomplishment of the goal and in harmony with the element conducive to purification.</s>
    <s id="211:6">(5) In order to attain, perfect, and accomplish the truth body, they seize the most supreme and auspicious cause.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="212">
    <s id="212:1">$101“Blessed One, how should we know at which point[the bodhisattvas cognize and obtain the mental stillness and the insight that have a universal teaching as a referential object?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="213">
    <s id="213:1">“Maitreya, you should know that they cognize them on the first bodhisattva stage, Utmost Joy, and obtain them on the third stage, Illuminating.</s>
    <s id="213:2">Maitreya, in spite of this, even beginners among bodhisattvas should not abstain from training in them and directing their attention toward their referential object.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="214">
    <s id="214:1">$102“Blessed One, in what way do mental stillness and insight become a concentration associated with mental engagement#194 and investigation?</s>
    <s id="214:2">[29.b] In what way do they become a concentration not with mental engagement but with investigation only?</s>
    <s id="214:3">In what way do they become a concentration without either mental engagement or investigation?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="215">
    <s id="215:1">“Maitreya, when mental stillness and insight attend to experiences of the manifest and coarse#195 phenomenal appearances mentioned in the teachings the bodhisattvas have understood, investigated, and examined, this is the concentration associated with mental engagement and investigation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="216">
    <s id="216:1">“When mental stillness and insight do not consist in attending the experiences corresponding to the manifest and coarse phenomenal appearances mentioned in their teachings but consist in being merely mindful of appearances, namely, in attending the experience of subtle phenomenal appearances,#196 this is a concentration not with mental engagement but with investigation only.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="217">
    <s id="217:1">“When mental stillness and insight consist in practicing by directing one’s attention toward the experience of the effortless Dharma with regard to each and every phenomenal appearance mentioned in these teachings, this is a concentration without either mental engagement or investigation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="218">
    <s id="218:1">“Moreover, Maitreya, mental stillness and insight arising from inquiry consist in a concentration associated with mental engagement and investigation.</s>
    <s id="218:2">The mental stillness and insight arising from awakening is a concentration not with mental engagement but with investigation only.#197</s>
    <s id="218:3">The mental stillness and insight taking a universal teaching as its referential object consist in a concentration without either mental engagement or investigation.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="219">
    <s id="219:1">$103“Blessed One, what is the cause of mental stillness?</s>
    <s id="219:2">What is the cause of setting the mind?</s>
    <s id="219:3">What is the cause of equanimity?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="220">
    <s id="220:1">“Maitreya, when one feels excited or feels one might become excited, one directs one’s attention toward phenomena that induce sorrow and the unimpeded mind.#198</s>
    <s id="220:2">This is what is called the cause of mental stillness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="221">
    <s id="221:1">“Maitreya, when one feels drowsy or feels one might become drowsy, one directs one’s attention toward phenomena that induce joy and mental appearance.#199 This is what is called the cause of setting the mind.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="222">
    <s id="222:1">“Maitreya, whether one is devoted to mental stillness or insight only, [30.a] or practices them in union, when one applies one’s mind without being affected by these two secondary defilements,#200 [namely agitation and drowsiness,] one directs one’s attention spontaneously.</s>
    <s id="222:2">This is what is called the cause of equanimity.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="223">
    <s id="223:1">$104“Blessed One, the bodhisattvas who practice mental stillness and insight possess the analytical knowledge of designations as well as the analytical knowledge of the objects of designation.#201 In what way do they possess these analytical knowledges?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="224">
    <s id="224:1">“Maitreya, the analytical knowledge of designations comprises five points: names, phrases, letters, their individual apprehension, and their collective apprehension.</s>
    <s id="224:2">What is a name?</s>
    <s id="224:3">It is that which superimposes a so-called essential or distinctive characteristic on the phenomena conducive to affliction and purification for the sake of communication.</s>
    <s id="224:4">What is a phrase?</s>
    <s id="224:5">It is that which is based on a collection of those very names taken as its support and basis in order to designate objects of affliction and purification.</s>
    <s id="224:6">What are letters?</s>
    <s id="224:7">They are phonemes acting as the basis for both names and phrases.</s>
    <s id="224:8">What is the analytical knowledge that apprehends them individually?</s>
    <s id="224:9">It is the analytical knowledge resulting from directing one’s attention toward a specific referential object.</s>
    <s id="224:10">What is the analytical knowledge that apprehends them collectively?</s>
    <s id="224:11">It is the analytical knowledge resulting from directing one’s attention toward a general referential object.</s>
    <s id="224:12">When all these five points are put together, this should be known as the analytical knowledge of designations.</s>
    <s id="224:13">This is how bodhisattvas possess the analytical knowledge of designations.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="225">
    <s id="225:1">$105“Maitreya, the analytical knowledge of the objects of designation comprises ten points:</s>
    <s id="225:2">the diversity of things and the nature of things;#202 the apprehending subject and the apprehended object;</s>
    <s id="225:3">the abodes and objects of enjoyment;</s>
    <s id="225:4">wrong view and correct view;</s>
    <s id="225:5">and the object conducive to affliction and the object conducive to purification. [30.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="226">
    <s id="226:1">1.</s>
    <s id="226:2">“Maitreya, all#203 the various divisions of phenomena conducive to affliction and purification according to their aspects represent the diversity of things, namely, the fivefold enumeration of the aggregates, the sixfold enumeration of the internal sense domains, the sixfold enumeration of the external sense domains, and so on.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="227">
    <s id="227:1">2.</s>
    <s id="227:2">“Maitreya, the true reality of all these very phenomena conducive to affliction and purification is the nature of things itself.</s>
    <s id="227:3">It has seven aspects:#204</s>
    <s id="227:4">(i) the true reality of arising in the sense that all conditioned phenomena are without beginning and end;</s>
    <s id="227:5">(ii) the true reality of defining characteristics in the sense that everything, person or phenomenon, is without a self;</s>
    <s id="227:6">(iii) the true reality of representations in the sense that all conditioned phenomena are mere representations;#205</s>
    <s id="227:7">(iv) the true reality of existence in the sense of the truth of suffering that I have taught;</s>
    <s id="227:8">(v) the true reality of mistaken action#206 in the sense of the truth of the origin of suffering that I have taught;</s>
    <s id="227:9">(vi) the true reality of purification in the sense of the truth of cessation [of suffering] that I have taught;</s>
    <s id="227:10">(vii) the true reality of correct action in the sense of the truth of the path that I have taught.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="228">
    <s id="228:1">“Maitreya, on account of the true reality of arising, defining characteristics, and existence, all beings are similar and equal.</s>
    <s id="228:2">Maitreya, on account of the true reality of defining characteristics and representations, all phenomena are similar and equal.</s>
    <s id="228:3">Maitreya, on account of the true reality of purification, the awakening of the hearers, the awakening of the solitary realizers, and the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening are similar and equal.</s>
    <s id="228:4">Maitreya, on account of the true reality of correct action, similar and equal too are the wisdoms encompassed by the mental stillness and insight that take as a referential object a universal teaching that has been heard, contemplated, and practiced.#207[31.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="229">
    <s id="229:1">3.</s>
    <s id="229:2">“Maitreya, the apprehending subject consists in the phenomena of the five physical sense domains, mind, thought, cognition, and mental states.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="230">
    <s id="230:1">4.</s>
    <s id="230:2">“Maitreya, the apprehended object consists in the six external sense domains.</s>
    <s id="230:3">In addition, Maitreya, apprehending subjects are also apprehended objects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="231">
    <s id="231:1">5.</s>
    <s id="231:2">“Maitreya, the objects corresponding to abodes are the worlds of beings, which manifest wherever there are beings:</s>
    <s id="231:3">as one, one hundred, one thousand, or one hundred thousand villages;</s>
    <s id="231:4">as one, one hundred, one thousand, or one hundred thousand continents;</s>
    <s id="231:5">as one, one hundred, one thousand, or one hundred thousand great continents of Jambudvīpa;</s>
    <s id="231:6">as one, one hundred, one thousand, or one hundred thousand times the four great continents;</s>
    <s id="231:7">as one, one hundred, one thousand, or one hundred thousand universes of a thousand worlds;</s>
    <s id="231:8">as one, one hundred, one thousand, or one hundred thousand bichiliocosms;</s>
    <s id="231:9">as one, one hundred, one thousand, one hundred thousand, ten million, one billion, ten billion, one hundred billion, or ten trillion trichiliocosms;</s>
    <s id="231:10">as one, one hundred, one thousand, one hundred thousand times an incalculable number of them;</s>
    <s id="231:11">or as many as the number of atoms present in one hundred thousand times an incalculable number of trichiliocosms.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="232">
    <s id="232:1">6.</s>
    <s id="232:2">“Maitreya, I have taught that objects of enjoyment are the assets and belongings owned by beings for the sake of their enjoyment.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="233">
    <s id="233:1">7.</s>
    <s id="233:2">“Maitreya, a wrong view is a mistaken conception, thought, or view conceiving the impermanent as permanent, suffering as happiness, impurity as purity, or selflessness as self with regard to notions such as an apprehending subject.</s>
    <s id="233:3">[31.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="234">
    <s id="234:1">8.</s>
    <s id="234:2">“Maitreya, a correct view, being the opposite of a wrong view, is its antidote.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="235">
    <s id="235:1">9.</s>
    <s id="235:2">“Maitreya, the object conducive to affliction is of three kinds: the object conducive to the affliction comprising the defilements of the three worlds, to the affliction of karma, and to the affliction of arising.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="236">
    <s id="236:1">10.</s>
    <s id="236:2">“Maitreya, the object conducive to purification consists of all that is in harmony with awakening on account of being free indeed from the three sorts of affliction.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="237">
    <s id="237:1">“Maitreya, you should know that all objects of designation are included in these ten points.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="238">
    <s id="238:1">$106“Moreover, Maitreya, the analytical knowledge of these objects of designation comprises five items.</s>
    <s id="238:2">What are they?</s>
    <s id="238:3">They are the topics to be comprehended, the objects of designation to be comprehended, comprehension, the result of comprehension, and the communication of this result.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="239">
    <s id="239:1">1.</s>
    <s id="239:2">“Maitreya, the topics to be comprehended consist of anything that is knowable or perceptible, such as what is referred to as the aggregates, the internal and external sense domains, and so forth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="240">
    <s id="240:1">2.</s>
    <s id="240:2">“Maitreya, the objects of designation to be comprehended consist of [all] cognitive objects, however diverse they appear and as they really are:</s>
    <s id="240:3">the conventional and the ultimate;</s>
    <s id="240:4">shortcomings and qualities;</s>
    <s id="240:5">conditions and time;</s>
    <s id="240:6">the defining characteristics of arising, abiding, and disintegrating;</s>
    <s id="240:7">sickness, old age, and death;</s>
    <s id="240:8">suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the path leading to the cessation of suffering;</s>
    <s id="240:9">true reality, the ultimate limit of existence, and the domain of truth;</s>
    <s id="240:10">condensed and detailed teachings;</s>
    <s id="240:11">categorical, analytical, interrogative, and dismissive answers;</s>
    <s id="240:12">and secret instructions and proclamations.</s>
    <s id="240:13">You should know that these are the objects of designation to be comprehended.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="241">
    <s id="241:1">3.</s>
    <s id="241:2">“Maitreya, comprehension is grasping both [32.a] the topics and the objects of designation to be comprehended, any factor that is in harmony with awakening, such as the applications of mindfulness, the correct self-restraints, and so forth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="242">
    <s id="242:1">4.</s>
    <s id="242:2">“Maitreya, the result of comprehension consists of disciplining and completely eliminating desire, anger, and delusion, as well as in actualizing the results of the path of the recluse together with the virtuous qualities of the hearers and tathāgatas I have described as mundane and supramundane, ordinary and extraordinary.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="243">
    <s id="243:1">5.</s>
    <s id="243:2">“Maitreya, communicating this result consists in revealing what brings about liberation#208 on the basis of#209 the very teachings one has actualized, as well as in propagating these teaching for the sake of others.#210</s>
  </p>
  <p id="244">
    <s id="244:1">“Maitreya, you should know that all objects are subsumed within these five points.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="245">
    <s id="245:1">$107“Maitreya, the bodhisattvas’ analytical knowledge of the objects of designation includes four topics.</s>
    <s id="245:2">What are they?</s>
    <s id="245:3">They are mental appropriation, experience, affliction, and purification.</s>
    <s id="245:4">Maitreya, you should know that all the objects of designation are also included within these four topics.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="246">
    <s id="246:1">$108“Maitreya, the bodhisattvas’ analytical knowledge of the objects of designation is also presented according to three topics.</s>
    <s id="246:2">What are they?</s>
    <s id="246:3">They are letters, meanings, and contexts.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="247">
    <s id="247:1">1.</s>
    <s id="247:2">“Maitreya, you should understand the letters as forming collections of names.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="248">
    <s id="248:1">2.</s>
    <s id="248:2">“Maitreya, meanings comprise ten aspects:</s>
    <s id="248:3">the defining characteristic of true reality, the defining characteristic of comprehension, the defining characteristic of abandonment, the defining characteristic of realization, the defining characteristic of practice, the defining characteristic consisting of these very five defining characteristics, the defining characteristic of the relation between the support and the supported, [32.b] the defining characteristic of the phenomena undermining comprehension and so forth, the defining characteristic of the phenomena in harmony with comprehension, and the defining characteristic of the benefits and shortcomings resulting respectively from having comprehension or not.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="249">
    <s id="249:1">3.</s>
    <s id="249:2">“Maitreya, there are five contexts: the context of the surrounding universe, the context of beings, the context of Dharma, the context of discipline, and the context of methods of discipline.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="250">
    <s id="250:1">“Maitreya, you should know that all objects of designation are also included within these three topics.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="251">
    <s id="251:1">$109“Blessed One, what differences are made between the comprehension of the objects of designation that is produced by the wisdom arising from hearing the Dharma, the comprehension of the objects of designation that is produced by the wisdom arising from contemplating the Dharma, and the comprehension of the objects of designation that is produced by the wisdom arising from practicing mental stillness and insight?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="252">
    <s id="252:1">“Maitreya, through the wisdom arising from hearing the Dharma, the bodhisattvas rely on the literal meaning of words but not on their underlying intent, which they do not understand;</s>
    <s id="252:2">although they are in harmony with liberation, their comprehension is [limited to] the objects of designation that do not liberate them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="253">
    <s id="253:1">“Maitreya, through the wisdom arising from contemplating the Dharma, the bodhisattvas do not rely exclusively on the literal meaning of words but also on the underlying intent, which they understand;</s>
    <s id="253:2">although they are in great harmony with liberation, their comprehension is [still limited to] the objects of designation that do not liberate them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="254">
    <s id="254:1">“Maitreya, through the wisdom arising from practicing mental stillness and insight, the bodhisattvas, relying on the literal meaning of words or not, rely on the underlying intent, which they understand by means of an image, an object of concentration corresponding to a cognitive object;</s>
    <s id="254:2">they are in great harmony with liberation, and their comprehension includes the objects of designation that liberate them.</s>
    <s id="254:3">Maitreya, such is the difference between them.” [33.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="255">
    <s id="255:1">$110“Blessed One, what is the gnosis#211 of the bodhisattvas who practice mental stillness and insight and who comprehend designations as well as objects of designation?</s>
    <s id="255:2">What is their perception?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="256">
    <s id="256:1">“Maitreya, I have explained their gnosis#212 and perception in many ways, but I will give you a concise explanation.</s>
    <s id="256:2">Gnosis consists in the mental stillness and insight that take a universal teaching as a referential object.</s>
    <s id="256:3">Perception consists in the mental stillness and insight that take a specific teaching as a referential object.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="257">
    <s id="257:1">$111“Blessed One, as bodhisattvas practice mental stillness and insight, which kinds of phenomenal appearance do they discard?</s>
    <s id="257:2">How do they direct their attention to achieve this?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="258">
    <s id="258:1">“Maitreya, they discard the phenomenal appearance of designations and objects of designation by directing their attention on true reality.</s>
    <s id="258:2">They discard names by not taking the essence of names as a referential object and by not paying attention to the phenomenal appearance that constitutes their basis.</s>
    <s id="258:3">You should know that just as it is with names, so it is also with words, letters, and all objects of designation.</s>
    <s id="258:4">Maitreya, they discard letters, meanings, and contexts by not taking their essence as a referential object and by not paying attention to the phenomenal appearance that constitutes their basis.”#213</s>
  </p>
  <p id="259">
    <s id="259:1">$112“Blessed One, is phenomenal appearance also discarded with regard to the analytical knowledge of the object of designation corresponding to true reality?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="260">
    <s id="260:1">“Maitreya, if the analytical knowledge of the object of designation corresponding to true reality does not have a phenomenal appearance and does not take a phenomenal appearance as its referential object, then what would be discarded in that case?</s>
    <s id="260:2">Maitreya, the analytical knowledge of the object of designation corresponding to true reality disposes of all the phenomenal appearances of designations and objects of designation.</s>
    <s id="260:3">But I did not teach that anything at all could dispose of this analytical knowledge.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="261">
    <s id="261:1">$113“Blessed One, you have explained by way of analogy that it is impossible to discern one’s own appearance#214 in a container filled with muddy water, a dirty mirror, or an agitated pond surface, [33.b] but that it is possible in a container filled with clear water, a well-polished mirror, or a quiet pond.</s>
    <s id="261:2">You have explained that, likewise, the mind of those who do not practice cannot know true reality exactly as it is, whereas the mind of those who do practice can indeed.</s>
    <s id="261:3">In reference to this statement, what is this mental inspection?#215 What true reality do you have in mind here, and what is the meaning of this statement?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="262">
    <s id="262:1">“Maitreya, I spoke those words in reference to the three kinds of mental inspection: the mental inspection arising from hearing the Dharma, the mental inspection arising from contemplating the Dharma, and the mental inspection arising from practicing the Dharma.</s>
    <s id="262:2">I taught this having in mind the true reality of representations.”#216</s>
  </p>
  <p id="263">
    <s id="263:1">$114“Blessed One, how many kinds of phenomenal appearances did you teach to the bodhisattvas who possess the analytical knowledge of designations and objects of designation and who engage in eliminating phenomenal appearances?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="264">
    <s id="264:1">“Maitreya, there are ten kinds of phenomenal appearances, and these bodhisattvas eliminate them by means of emptiness.</s>
    <s id="264:2">What are these ten?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="265">
    <s id="265:1">1.</s>
    <s id="265:2">“The diverse phenomenal appearances in the way of words and letters through which designations and objects of designation are analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of all phenomena.#217</s>
  </p>
  <p id="266">
    <s id="266:1">2.</s>
    <s id="266:2">“The phenomenal appearances corresponding to a continuum of arisings and cessations or abidings and transformations through which the object designated as the true reality of existence is analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of defining characteristic and by the emptiness of what is without beginning and end.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="267">
    <s id="267:1">3.</s>
    <s id="267:2">“The phenomenal appearances resulting from the belief in a perduring self or the thought, ‘I am,’ through which the object designated as the apprehending subject is analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of the inner subject and the emptiness of what is not taken as a referential object.#218</s>
  </p>
  <p id="268">
    <s id="268:1">4.</s>
    <s id="268:2">“The phenomenal appearances resulting from the belief in objects of enjoyment through which the object designated as the apprehended object is analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of the outer object.#219</s>
  </p>
  <p id="269">
    <s id="269:1">5.</s>
    <s id="269:2">“The phenomenal appearances of pleasure within the inner subject and of beauty regarding the outer object through which courtesans#220 and possessions are analytically known as objects of enjoyment—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of the outer object and the emptiness of essence. [34.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="270">
    <s id="270:1">6.</s>
    <s id="270:2">“The innumerable phenomenal appearances through which objects of designation corresponding to states of existence are analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the great emptiness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="271">
    <s id="271:1">7.</s>
    <s id="271:2">“With formlessness as a support, the phenomenal appearances of the liberation brought about by inner peace are analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of conditioned phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="272">
    <s id="272:1">8.</s>
    <s id="272:2">“The phenomenal appearance of the selflessness of persons and phenomena, the phenomenal appearance of what is merely a representation, and the phenomenal appearance of the ultimate through which the object of designation corresponding to the true reality of defining characteristics is analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of the limitless, the emptiness of the substanceless, the emptiness of essence of the substanceless, and the emptiness of the ultimate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="273">
    <s id="273:1">9.</s>
    <s id="273:2">“The phenomenal appearances of what is unconditioned and changeless through which the object of designation corresponding to the true reality leading to purification#221 is analytically known—these phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of the unconditioned and the emptiness devoid of rejection.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="274">
    <s id="274:1">10.</s>
    <s id="274:2">“The phenomenal appearances of emptiness resulting from directing one’s attention toward this very emptiness as an antidote to phenomenal appearances are eliminated by means of the emptiness of emptiness.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="275">
    <s id="275:1">$115“Blessed One, when bodhisattvas eliminate these ten kinds of phenomenal appearances,</s>
    <s id="275:2">which phenomenal appearances do they eliminate and from which binding phenomenal appearances will they be free?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="276">
    <s id="276:1">“Maitreya, by eliminating the object of concentration, the phenomenal appearance corresponding to an image,#222 bodhisattvas will be free from phenomenal appearances consisting in the phenomenal appearances of affliction, which they will also eliminate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="277">
    <s id="277:1">“Maitreya, you should know that these various kinds of emptiness are the direct antidotes to these various kinds of phenomenal appearance.</s>
    <s id="277:2">But it is not the case that each of them is not an antidote to all phenomenal appearances.</s>
    <s id="277:3">Maitreya, it is like this: ignorance does not [directly] bring about all afflictions up to old age and death [with regard to the twelve factors of conditioned existence].</s>
    <s id="277:4">Yet,</s>
    <s id="277:5">because it is indeed the closely or very closely related condition [for their arising, it does bring them about indirectly].</s>
    <s id="277:6">This is why it is taught that ignorance directly brings about conditioning mental factors.</s>
    <s id="277:7">You should consider the present topic in the same way. [34.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="278">
    <s id="278:1">$116“Blessed One, what is it that bodhisattvas realize in the context of the Great Vehicle?</s>
    <s id="278:2">What is then inherent to the defining characteristic of emptiness that causes bodhisattvas to not deviate from it because of pride?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="279">
    <s id="279:1">Then, the Blessed One said, “Excellent, Maitreya.</s>
    <s id="279:2">You question the Tathāgata on this point so that bodhisattvas will not deviate from emptiness.</s>
    <s id="279:3">This is excellent indeed.</s>
    <s id="279:4">Why?</s>
    <s id="279:5">Because, Maitreya, bodhisattvas who deviate from emptiness will also deviate from the entire Great Vehicle.</s>
    <s id="279:6">Therefore, listen well, Maitreya, and I will explain to you what is inherent to the defining characteristic of emptiness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="280">
    <s id="280:1">“Maitreya, emptiness as taught in the Great Vehicle means that the other-dependent and actual defining characteristics are completely devoid of the imaginary defining characteristic of affliction and purification and that bodhisattvas do not take this imaginary defining characteristic as a referential object.”#223</s>
  </p>
  <p id="281">
    <s id="281:1">$117“Blessed One, how many types of concentration are included within mental stillness and insight?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="282">
    <s id="282:1">“Maitreya, you should know that they include all the types of concentration of the hearers, bodhisattvas, and tathāgatas that I have taught.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="283">
    <s id="283:1">“Blessed One, from which causes do mental stillness and insight arise?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="284">
    <s id="284:1">“Maitreya, they arise from a pure discipline and a pure view resulting from hearing and contemplating [the Dharma] as their causes.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="285">
    <s id="285:1">“Blessed One, please explain what their results are.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="286">
    <s id="286:1">“Maitreya, a pure mind and a pure wisdom are their results.</s>
    <s id="286:2">You should know that all mundane and supramundane virtuous qualities of the hearers, the bodhisattvas, and the tathāgatas are also their results.” [35.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="287">
    <s id="287:1">“Blessed One, what is the activity of mental stillness and insight?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="288">
    <s id="288:1">“Maitreya, they liberate one from the two kinds of bonds: the bonds of phenomenal appearance and the bonds of corruption.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="289">
    <s id="289:1">$118“Blessed One, among the five obstacles mentioned by the Blessed One, which are obstacles to mental stillness, which are obstacles to insight, and which are obstacles to both?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="290">
    <s id="290:1">“Maitreya, caring#224 about the body and objects of enjoyment is an obstacle to mental stillness.</s>
    <s id="290:2">Not obtaining instructions from noble beings as desired is an obstacle to insight.</s>
    <s id="290:3">Living in a state of confusion and being content with bare necessities are obstacles to both.#225</s>
    <s id="290:4">On account of the first of these, one will not exert oneself.</s>
    <s id="290:5">On account of the second, one will not exert oneself through to the completion of practice.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="291">
    <s id="291:1">“Blessed One, among the five obstructions mentioned by the Blessed One, which are obstructions to mental stillness, which are obstructions to insight, and which are obstructions to both?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="292">
    <s id="292:1">“Maitreya, agitation and remorse are obstructions to mental stillness.</s>
    <s id="292:2">Laziness, lethargy, and doubts are obstructions to insight.</s>
    <s id="292:3">Craving for desired objects and malicious thoughts are obstructions to both.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="293">
    <s id="293:1">“Blessed One, when is the path of mental stillness purified?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="294">
    <s id="294:1">“At the time when agitation and remorse have been conquered.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="295">
    <s id="295:1">“Blessed One, when is the path of insight purified?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="296">
    <s id="296:1">“At the time when laziness, lethargy, and doubts have been conquered.”#226</s>
  </p>
  <p id="297">
    <s id="297:1">$119“Blessed One, how many kinds of mental distractions will bodhisattvas engaged in mental stillness and insight experience?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="298">
    <s id="298:1">“Maitreya, they will experience five kinds of mental distractions: the mental distraction with regard to the way one directs one’s attention, the mental distraction with regard to outer objects, the mental distraction with regard to the inner subject, the mental distraction produced by phenomenal appearances, [35.b] and the mental distraction resulting from corruption.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="299">
    <s id="299:1">1.</s>
    <s id="299:2">“Maitreya, if bodhisattvas forsake the way attention is directed in the Great Vehicle#227 and fall into the way hearers and solitary realizers direct their attention, then</s>
    <s id="299:3">this is mental distraction regarding the way one directs one’s attention.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="300">
    <s id="300:1">2.</s>
    <s id="300:2">“If bodhisattvas let their minds wander among the five external objects of desire, entertainments, phenomenal appearances, conceptualizations, defilements, secondary defilements, and external referential objects, then</s>
    <s id="300:3">this is mental distraction with regard to outer objects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="301">
    <s id="301:1">3.</s>
    <s id="301:2">“If bodhisattvas sink into laziness and lethargy, experience the taste of absorption, or become stained by any secondary defilement related to absorption, then</s>
    <s id="301:3">this is mental distraction with regard to the inner subject.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="302">
    <s id="302:1">4.</s>
    <s id="302:2">“If bodhisattvas direct their attention toward the phenomenal appearance that is the inner subject’s object of concentration by relying upon the phenomenal appearances of outer objects, then</s>
    <s id="302:3">this is mental distraction produced by phenomenal appearances.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="303">
    <s id="303:1">5.</s>
    <s id="303:2">“If bodhisattvas become conceited by identifying themselves with the body afflicted by corruption with regard to sensations arising in the course of directing the inner subject’s attention,</s>
    <s id="303:3">this is mental distraction ensuing from corruption.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="304">
    <s id="304:1">$120“Blessed One, for which obstacles do mental stillness and insight serve as antidotes from the first stage of the bodhisattva path up to the stage of a tathāgata?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="305">
    <s id="305:1">1.</s>
    <s id="305:2">“Maitreya, on the first stage, mental stillness and insight are antidotes to the defilement of bad destinies as well as to the affliction of karma and birth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="306">
    <s id="306:1">2.</s>
    <s id="306:2">“On the second stage, they are antidotes to the arising of confusion resulting from subtle transgressions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="307">
    <s id="307:1">3.</s>
    <s id="307:2">“On the third stage, they are antidotes to attachment for desirous objects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="308">
    <s id="308:1">4.</s>
    <s id="308:2">“On the fourth stage, they are antidotes to craving for absorption and Dharma.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="309">
    <s id="309:1">5.</s>
    <s id="309:2">“On the fifth stage, they are antidotes to the exclusive rejection of saṃsāra and exclusive inclination toward nirvāṇa.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="310">
    <s id="310:1">6.</s>
    <s id="310:2">‘On the sixth stage, they are antidotes to the abundant arising of phenomenal appearances.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="311">
    <s id="311:1">7.</s>
    <s id="311:2">“On the seventh stage, they are antidotes to the subtle arising of phenomenal appearances.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="312">
    <s id="312:1">8.</s>
    <s id="312:2">“On the eighth, they are antidotes to exerting oneself toward what is without phenomenal appearance as well as to not having mastery over phenomenal appearances.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="313">
    <s id="313:1">9.</s>
    <s id="313:2">On the ninth, they are antidotes to not having mastery in teaching the Dharma in every aspect. [36.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="314">
    <s id="314:1">10.</s>
    <s id="314:2">“On the tenth, they are antidotes to not having obtained the perfect analytical knowledge of the truth body.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="315">
    <s id="315:1">11.</s>
    <s id="315:2">“Maitreya, on the stage of a tathāgata, mental stillness and insight are antidotes to the extremely subtle defiling obstructions and the even more subtle cognitive obstructions.#228</s>
    <s id="315:3">By fully eliminating these obstructions, one abides within the truth body that has been completely purified.</s>
    <s id="315:4">As a consequence, one obtains the realization of the object corresponding to the accomplishment of the goal—the gnosis and vision that are utterly free from attachment and hindrance.”#229</s>
  </p>
  <p id="316">
    <s id="316:1">$121“Blessed One, in what way do bodhisattvas obtain mental stillness and insight, so that they will attain the unsurpassable complete and perfect awakening?”#230</s>
  </p>
  <p id="317">
    <s id="317:1">“Maitreya, once bodhisattvas have obtained mental stillness and insight, they consider the seven aspects of true reality.#231</s>
    <s id="317:2">With their minds concentrated on the doctrine that has been heard and contemplated, they direct their attention inwardly toward the true reality that has been well#232 understood, contemplated, and focused upon.</s>
    <s id="317:3">As they direct their attention in this way on true reality, their minds then remain in complete equanimity#233 toward each and every subtle phenomenal appearance that manifests, not to mention coarse ones.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="318">
    <s id="318:1">“Maitreya, these subtle phenomenal appearances include the phenomenal appearances appropriated by mind;</s>
    <s id="318:2">the phenomenal appearances of experiences, representations, affliction, and purification;</s>
    <s id="318:3">the internal or external phenomenal appearances and those that are both internal and external;</s>
    <s id="318:4">the phenomenal appearances related to the notion that one must act for the benefit of all beings;</s>
    <s id="318:5">the phenomenal appearances of knowledge and suchness;</s>
    <s id="318:6">the phenomenal appearances of the four noble truths of suffering, the origin of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the path;#234 the phenomenal appearances of the conditioned, the unconditioned, the permanent, the impermanent, and the nature inherent to what is subject to suffering and change [36.b] or what is not subject to change;</s>
    <s id="318:7">the phenomenal appearance distinct or indistinct from the defining characteristic specific to the conditioned;</s>
    <s id="318:8">the phenomenal appearance of everything as a result of having the notion of ‘everything’ in reference to anything;</s>
    <s id="318:9">and the phenomenal appearance of the selflessness of the person and of phenomena.</s>
    <s id="318:10">The bodhisattva’s mind remains in complete equanimity toward all these phenomenal appearances as they manifest.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="319">
    <s id="319:1">“Continually practicing in this way, they will in due time purify their minds from obstacles, obstructions, and distractions.</s>
    <s id="319:2">In the course of this practice, the seven aspects of the cognition that is personal and intuitive, the gnosis#235 that is the awakening#236 to the seven aspects of true reality, will arise.</s>
    <s id="319:3">Such is the bodhisattvas’ path of seeing.</s>
    <s id="319:4">By obtaining it, bodhisattvas have entered the faultless state of truth,#237 are born into the lineage of tathāgatas, and, upon obtaining the first stage, enjoy all the advantages of this stage.</s>
    <s id="319:5">Because they have already obtained mental stillness and insight, they have attained their two referential objects: the image with conceptualization and the image without conceptualization.</s>
    <s id="319:6">Thus, having obtained the path of seeing, they attain the point where phenomena end.#238</s>
  </p>
  <p id="320">
    <s id="320:1">“In the higher stages, they enter the path of practice and direct their attention toward their threefold referential object.#239</s>
    <s id="320:2">It is like this: in the way one uses a smaller wedge to pull out a larger one and thus drives out a wedge by means of a wedge, they eliminate all phenomenal appearances related to affliction by eliminating internal phenomenal appearances.</s>
    <s id="320:3">When they eliminate them, they also eliminate corruption.</s>
    <s id="320:4">By getting rid of phenomenal appearance and corruption, they gradually purify their minds in the higher stages in the way gold is refined.</s>
    <s id="320:5">They will attain the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening and also obtain the realization of the object corresponding to the accomplishment of the goal.#240 Thus,</s>
    <s id="320:6">Maitreya, [37.a] once bodhisattvas have achieved mental stillness and insight in this way, they will attain the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="321">
    <s id="321:1">$122“How do bodhisattvas practice so that they accomplish the great powers of a bodhisattva?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="322">
    <s id="322:1">“Maitreya, the bodhisattvas who are skillful with regard to these six topics accomplish the great powers of a bodhisattva: (1) the arising of the mind, (2) the underlying condition of the mind, (3) the emergence from the mind, (4) the increase of the mind, (5) the decrease of the mind, (6) and skillful means.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="323">
    <s id="323:1">1.</s>
    <s id="323:2">“How are they skillful with regard to the arising of the mind?</s>
    <s id="323:3">They are skillful with regard to the arising of the mind as it is if they know the sixteen ways in which mind arises:#241</s>
    <s id="323:4">(i) the representation that is a support and receptacle, for example, the appropriating cognition;#242</s>
    <s id="323:5">(ii) the representation that is a variegated image of a referential object, for example, the mental cognition of conceptualizations that simultaneously apprehends forms and so on, or that simultaneously apprehends outer and inner objects, or that in a single instant simultaneously settles in several states of concentration, perceives numerous buddha fields, or sees many tathāgatas—being nothing but the mental cognition of conceptualizations;</s>
    <s id="323:6">(iii) the representation taking limited phenomenal appearances as its object, for example, the mind related to the [realm of] desire;</s>
    <s id="323:7">(iv) the representation taking vast phenomenal appearances as its object, for example, the mind related to the [realm of] form;</s>
    <s id="323:8">(v) the representation taking immeasurable phenomenal appearances as its object, for example, the mind related to the domain of limitless space and limitless cognition;</s>
    <s id="323:9">(vi) the representation taking subtle phenomenal appearances as its object, for example, the mind related to the domain of nothingness;</s>
    <s id="323:10">(vii) the representation taking ultimate phenomenal appearances as its object, for example, the mind related to the domain of neither conception nor lack of conception;</s>
    <s id="323:11">(viii) the representation that does not have phenomenal appearance [as its object], for example, the supramundane mind and the mind having cessation as its object;</s>
    <s id="323:12">[37.b] (ix) the representation involving suffering, for example, the mind of hell beings;</s>
    <s id="323:13">(x) the representation involving mixed sensations, for example, the mind experienced in the [realm of] desire;</s>
    <s id="323:14">(xi) the representation involving joy, for example, the mind belonging to the first and second meditative absorptions;</s>
    <s id="323:15">(xii) the representation involving bliss, for example, the mind belonging to the third meditative absorption;</s>
    <s id="323:16">(xiii) the representation involving neither suffering nor bliss, for example, the mind belonging to the fourth meditative absorption up to the domain of neither conception nor lack of conception;</s>
    <s id="323:17">(xiv) the representation involving defilements, for example, the mind associated with defilements and secondary defilements;</s>
    <s id="323:18">(xv) the representation involving virtue, for example, the mind associated with faith and so on;</s>
    <s id="323:19">and</s>
    <s id="323:20">(xvi) the neutral representation, for example, the mind that is not associated with either defilement or virtue.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="324">
    <s id="324:1">2.</s>
    <s id="324:2">“How are they skillful with regard to the underlying condition of the mind?</s>
    <s id="324:3">They are skillful when they cognize the true reality of representations as it truly is.#243</s>
  </p>
  <p id="325">
    <s id="325:1">3.</s>
    <s id="325:2">“How are they skillful with regard to the emergence from the mind?</s>
    <s id="325:3">They are skillful when they cognize the as they truly are the two bonds, namely, the bonds of phenomenal appearance and corruption.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="326">
    <s id="326:1">4.</s>
    <s id="326:2">“How are they skillful with regard to the increase of the mind?</s>
    <s id="326:3">They are skillful when they cognize as such the arising and increase of the mind at the moment when the mind that is the antidote to phenomenal appearance and corruption arises and increases.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="327">
    <s id="327:1">5.</s>
    <s id="327:2">“How are they skillful with regard to the decrease of the mind?</s>
    <s id="327:3">They are skillful when they cognize as such the decrease and decline of the mind at the moment when the mind afflicted by the adverse factors of phenomenal appearance and corruption decreases and declines.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="328">
    <s id="328:1">6.</s>
    <s id="328:2">“How are they skilled in terms of means?</s>
    <s id="328:3">They are skillful when they practice the eight liberations, the eight domains of mastery, and the ten domains of totality.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="329">
    <s id="329:1">“Maitreya, in this way bodhisattvas have accomplished, do accomplish, and will accomplish the great powers of a bodhisattva. [38.a]”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="330">
    <s id="330:1">$123“The Blessed One said that all sensations have come to complete cessation in the domain of the nirvāṇa with no aggregates remaining.</s>
    <s id="330:2">What are then those sensations?”#244</s>
  </p>
  <p id="331">
    <s id="331:1">“Maitreya, in brief, two kinds of sensations cease: (1) the sensations#245 arising from corruption incumbent on being alive and (2) the sensations arising from their resulting objects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="332">
    <s id="332:1">1.</s>
    <s id="332:2">“Among those, the sensations arising from corruption related to one’s existence are of four kinds: (i) sensations arising from physical corruption, (ii) sensations arising from nonphysical corruption, (iii) sensations arising from corruption currently brought to fruition, and (iv) sensations arising from corruption not yet brought to fruition.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="333">
    <s id="333:1">“Sensations arising from corruption brought to fruition refer to present sensations, whereas</s>
    <s id="333:2">sensations arising from sensations not yet brought to fruition refer to sensations that are the causes for future sensations.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="334">
    <s id="334:1">2.</s>
    <s id="334:2">“The sensations of their resulting objects are also of four kinds: (i) sensations related to places, (ii) sensations related to necessities, (iii) sensations related to enjoyments, and (iv) sensations related to relations.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="335">
    <s id="335:1">“Moreover, there are sensations in the domain of the nirvāṇa with aggregates remaining.</s>
    <s id="335:2">Although these include sensations not yet brought to fruition,#246 their opposites, the experience of sensations arising from present sensations, have not completely ceased.</s>
    <s id="335:3">They are experienced as a mixture of pleasant and unpleasant sensations.</s>
    <s id="335:4">Both kinds of sensation already brought to fruition have completely ceased.</s>
    <s id="335:5">Only the category of sensations arising from present sensations are experienced.</s>
    <s id="335:6">In the domain of the nirvāṇa with no aggregates remaining, even this will cease when one passes into parinirvāṇa.</s>
    <s id="335:7">This is why I said that all sensations have come to a complete cessation in the domain of the nirvāṇa with no aggregates remaining.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="336">
    <s id="336:1">$124Thereupon, the Blessed One spoke these words to the bodhisattva Maitreya:</s>
    <s id="336:2">“Maitreya, you questioned the Tathāgata with determination and skill regarding the perfect and pure path of yoga.</s>
    <s id="336:3">This is excellent.</s>
    <s id="336:4">I taught that this path of yoga is perfect and pure, and exactly#247 so I have [38.b] taught and will teach all the perfect buddhas of the past and the future.</s>
    <s id="336:5">The sons and daughters of noble family should devote themselves to this path with great effort.”#248</s>
  </p>
  <p id="337">
    <s id="337:1">$125Then, at that moment,#249 the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="338">
    <s id="338:1">“This presentation of the teachings by means of designations Is thoughtful and of great significance for [the practice of this] yoga.#250</s>
    <s id="338:2">Those who, by relying on this Dharma, Correctly devote themselves to this yoga will attain awakening.#251</s>
  </p>
  <p id="339">
    <s id="339:1">“Those who, seeking liberation, study the entire Dharma By looking for faults and disputing itAre, Maitreya, as far from this yoga As is the sky from the earth.#252</s>
  </p>
  <p id="340">
    <s id="340:1">“Wise#253 and skilled in the real meaning#254 of benefiting beingsIs the one who does not strive to benefit beings thinking they will reward him.#255</s>
    <s id="340:2">The one expecting a reward will indeed#256 not obtainThe joy that is both#257 supreme and free from covetousness.#258</s>
  </p>
  <p id="341">
    <s id="341:1">“Those who grant Dharma instructions [to obtain] desirous objectsHave renounced desirous objects and yet#259 still accept them.</s>
    <s id="341:2">Although these fools have obtained the priceless and faultless#260 jewel of Dharma,They wander like beggars.#261</s>
  </p>
  <p id="342">
    <s id="342:1">“Therefore, with great effort Strive to abandon disputation, distractions, and mental elaborations.</s>
    <s id="342:2">In order to liberate the world of beings including the gods,Devote yourself to this yoga.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="343">
    <s id="343:1">$126Then, the bodhisattva Maitreya asked the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="343:2">“Blessed One, what is the name of the teaching imparted in this Dharma discourse that unravels the Tathāgata’s intent?</s>
    <s id="343:3">How should I keep it in mind?”#262</s>
  </p>
  <p id="344">
    <s id="344:1">The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="344:2">“Maitreya, this is a teaching of definitive meaning on yoga.</s>
    <s id="344:3">Keep it in mind as The Teaching of Definitive Meaning on Yoga.”</s>
    <s id="344:4">As the Blessed One expounded this teaching, six hundred thousand beings produced the mind directed at the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening,</s>
    <s id="344:5">three hundred thousand hearers [39.a] purified the Dharma eye from impurities and contaminations;</s>
    <s id="344:6">one hundred and fifty hearers who were without attachment liberated their minds from all outflows;</s>
    <s id="344:7">and</s>
    <s id="344:8">seventy-five thousand bodhisattvas attained the state wherein their attention was directed toward the great yoga.#263</s>
  </p>
  <p id="345">
    <s id="345:1">This was the chapter of the bodhisattva Maitreya—the eighth chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="346">
    <s id="346:1">Chapter 9</s>
  </p>
  <p id="347">
    <s id="347:1">$127Then the bodhisattva Avaloki­teśvara addressed the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="347:2">“Blessed One, the ten stages of the bodhisattva are called (1) Utmost Joy, (2) Stainless, (3) Illuminating, (4) Radiant, (5) Hard to Conquer, (6) Manifest, (7) Far Reaching, (8) Immovable, (9) Excellent Intelligence, and (10) Cloud of Dharma.</s>
    <s id="347:3">When taken together with the eleventh, [called] Buddha Stage, in how many kinds of purification and subdivisions are they included?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="348">
    <s id="348:1">$128The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="348:2">“Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that they are included in four kinds of purification and eleven subdivisions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="349">
    <s id="349:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that the first stage is included in the purification of intention;</s>
    <s id="349:2">the second, in the purification of superior discipline;</s>
    <s id="349:3">and</s>
    <s id="349:4">the third, in the purification of superior mind;</s>
    <s id="349:5">while stages four to eleven are included in the purification of superior wisdom, which gradually leads to perfection from stage to stage.</s>
    <s id="349:6">These stages are thus included in four kinds of purification.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="350">
    <s id="350:1">$129“What are the eleven levels—the subdivisions including the ten stages of the bodhisattva and the Buddha Stage?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="351">
    <s id="351:1">1.</s>
    <s id="351:2">“On the first level consisting of actions based on superior#264 devotion, bodhisattvas cultivate superior devotion and patience#265 by engaging in the ten practices related to Dharma.#266 Once they have passed beyond this stage, they will enter the faultless state of truth of the bodhisattvas.#267</s>
  </p>
  <p id="352">
    <s id="352:1">2.</s>
    <s id="352:2">“Although the first level is accomplished by these practices, [39.b] the second level is not, because the bodhisattvas are still unable to act while being aware of confusion resulting from subtle transgressions.</s>
    <s id="352:3">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="353">
    <s id="353:1">3.</s>
    <s id="353:2">“Although the second level is accomplished by this practice, the third level is not, because the bodhisattvas are still unable to settle into a perfect mundane concentration and recollect what they have heard.</s>
    <s id="353:3">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="354">
    <s id="354:1">4.</s>
    <s id="354:2">“However, the fourth level is not thereby accomplished, because the bodhisattvas, who frequently engage in practicing the awakening factors#268 in the way they obtained them, are still unable to settle their minds due to attachment to states of absorption and the teaching.#269</s>
    <s id="354:3">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="355">
    <s id="355:1">5.</s>
    <s id="355:2">“Although the fourth level is accomplished through this practice, the fifth level is not, because the bodhisattvas are still unable to fully examine the truths or settle in superior equanimity regarding saṃsāra and nirvāṇa, which they exclusively reject or focus upon, respectively.</s>
    <s id="355:3">They are still unable to practice the awakening factors in conjunction with skillful means.</s>
    <s id="355:4">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="356">
    <s id="356:1">6.</s>
    <s id="356:2">“Although the fifth level is accomplished by this practice, the sixth level is not, because, even once they have recognized the activities of conditioned states for what they are, the bodhisattvas are still unable to maintain for long an aversion toward them.</s>
    <s id="356:3">They are also still unable to remain for long directing their attention toward what lacks phenomenal appearances.</s>
    <s id="356:4">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="357">
    <s id="357:1">7.</s>
    <s id="357:2">“Although the sixth level is accomplished by this practice, the seventh level is not, because the bodhisattvas are still unable to remain without hindrance and interruption while directing their attention toward what lacks phenomenal appearance.</s>
    <s id="357:3">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed. [40.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="358">
    <s id="358:1">8.</s>
    <s id="358:2">“Although the seventh level is accomplished by this practice, the eighth level is not, because the bodhisattvas are still unable to rest in equanimity while striving to abide in what lacks phenomenal appearance.</s>
    <s id="358:3">They are also still unable to attain mastery over phenomenal appearance.</s>
    <s id="358:4">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="359">
    <s id="359:1">9.</s>
    <s id="359:2">“Although the eighth level is accomplished by this practice, the ninth level is not because the bodhisattvas are still unable to masterfully teach the Dharma in all its aspects by using synonyms, definitions, explanations, and categories.</s>
    <s id="359:3">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="360">
    <s id="360:1">10.</s>
    <s id="360:2">“Although the ninth level is accomplished by this practice, the tenth level is not because the bodhisattvas are still unable to obtain the analytical knowledge of the perfect truth body.</s>
    <s id="360:3">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="361">
    <s id="361:1">11.</s>
    <s id="361:2">“Although the ninth level is accomplished by this practice, the tenth level is not because the bodhisattvas are still unable to obtain the gnosis and vision that are utterly free from attachment and hindrance regarding all cognitive objects.#270</s>
    <s id="361:3">By striving to accomplish this level, they will succeed.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="362">
    <s id="362:1">“Since this level is accomplished by this practice, all levels are accomplished.</s>
    <s id="362:2">Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that all the stages are included in these eleven levels.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="363">
    <s id="363:1">$130“Blessed One, why is the first stage called Utmost Joy?</s>
    <s id="363:2">Why are the other stages up to the Buddha Stage called what they are?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="364">
    <s id="364:1">1.</s>
    <s id="364:2">“The first stage is called Utmost Joy because there is a supreme and immense joy in attaining the immaculate and sublime purpose, the supramundane mind.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="365">
    <s id="365:1">2.</s>
    <s id="365:2">The second stage is called Stainless because it is free from all stains consisting in [even] subtle transgressions or faulty discipline.#271</s>
  </p>
  <p id="366">
    <s id="366:1">3.</s>
    <s id="366:2">The third stage is called Illuminating because it is the very state of concentration and recollection imbued with the immeasurable light of gnosis.#272[40.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="367">
    <s id="367:1">4.</s>
    <s id="367:2">The fourth stage is called Radiant because the fire of gnosis produced by the practice of the awakening factors is set ablaze#273 in order to burn the fuel of afflictions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="368">
    <s id="368:1">5.</s>
    <s id="368:2">The fifth stage is called Hard to Conquer because it is difficult indeed to master the practice of these very awakening factors in conjunction with skillful means.#274</s>
  </p>
  <p id="369">
    <s id="369:1">6.</s>
    <s id="369:2">The sixth stage is called Manifest because the activity of conditioning mental factors becomes manifest, as does the bodhisattvas’ attention that is repeatedly directed toward what lacks phenomenal appearance.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="370">
    <s id="370:1">7.</s>
    <s id="370:2">The seventh stage is called Far Reaching because once the bodhisattvas engage for a long time without hindrance and interruption while directing their attention toward what lacks phenomenal appearance, this stage is connected with the subsequent stages of purification.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="371">
    <s id="371:1">8.</s>
    <s id="371:2">The eighth stage is called Immovable because what lacks phenomenal appearance is spontaneously accomplished and the bodhisattvas are unshaken by the manifestation of defilements resulting from phenomenal appearance.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="372">
    <s id="372:1">9.</s>
    <s id="372:2">The ninth stage is called Excellent Intelligence because the bodhisattvas obtain a vast intelligence that flawlessly masters all aspects related to teaching the Dharma.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="373">
    <s id="373:1">10.</s>
    <s id="373:2">The tenth stage is called Cloud of Dharma because the body afflicted by corruption, which is as empty as the sky, is pervaded and covered by the accumulation of Dharma#275 that is like a [great] cloud.#276</s>
  </p>
  <p id="374">
    <s id="374:1">11.</s>
    <s id="374:2">The eleventh stage is called Buddha Stage because once one has abandoned the most subtle defiling and cognitive obstructions, one completely and perfectly awakens and knows all aspects to be known,#277 without attachment and hindrance.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="375">
    <s id="375:1">$131“Blessed One, how many kinds of delusion and adverse factors of corruption are there on these stages?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="376">
    <s id="376:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, there are twenty-two kinds of delusion and eleven adverse factors of corruption:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="377">
    <s id="377:1">1.</s>
    <s id="377:2">“On the first stage, there is the delusion of wrongly conceiving the person and phenomena, the delusion of bad destinies, and the adverse factor of the corruption resulting from these.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="378">
    <s id="378:1">2.</s>
    <s id="378:2">“On the second stage, there is the delusion of confusion resulting from subtle transgressions, [41.a] the delusion related to the various aspects of the maturation of karma, and the adverse factor of the corruption resulting from these two.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="379">
    <s id="379:1">3.</s>
    <s id="379:2">“On the third stage, there is the delusion of desire, the delusion of perfectly remembering what was heard, and the adverse factor of the corruption resulting from these.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="380">
    <s id="380:1">4.</s>
    <s id="380:2">“On the fourth stage, there is the delusion of attachment to the states of absorption, the delusion of attachment to Dharma, and the adverse factor of the corruption resulting from these.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="381">
    <s id="381:1">5.</s>
    <s id="381:2">“On the fifth stage, there is the delusion of attending to saṃsāra as exclusively negative or positive, the delusion of attending to nirvāṇa as exclusively negative or positive, and the adverse factor of the corruption resulting from these.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="382">
    <s id="382:1">6.</s>
    <s id="382:2">“On the sixth stage, there is the delusion of making manifest the activity of conditioning mental factors, the delusion of the many manifesting phenomenal appearances, and the adverse factor of corruption resulting from these.#278</s>
  </p>
  <p id="383">
    <s id="383:1">7.</s>
    <s id="383:2">“On the seventh stage, there is the delusion of the manifestation of subtle phenomenal appearances, the delusion toward skillful means since one’s attention is exclusively directed toward what lacks phenomenal appearance, and the adverse factor of the corruption resulting from these.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="384">
    <s id="384:1">8.</s>
    <s id="384:2">“On the eighth stage, there is the delusion of exerting oneself toward what lacks phenomenal appearance, the delusion of not having mastery over phenomenal appearances, and the adverse factor of the corruption resulting from these.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="385">
    <s id="385:1">9.</s>
    <s id="385:2">“On the ninth stage, there is the delusion of having mastery in the boundless teaching and expression of Dharma, the delusion of having mastery in continuously keeping it in mind in terms of wisdom and eloquence,#279 the delusion of having command of eloquent speech, and the adverse factor consisting in the corruption resulting from these two types of delusion.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="386">
    <s id="386:1">10.</s>
    <s id="386:2">“On the tenth stage, there is the delusion with regard to the sublime superior knowledge, the delusion of engaging in what is secret and subtle, and the adverse factor consisting of the corruption resulting from these two.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="387">
    <s id="387:1">11.</s>
    <s id="387:2">“On the Buddha Stage, there is the delusion of the extremely subtle attachment to cognitive objects, the delusion of the extremely subtle hindrance related to defilements, and the adverse factor consisting of the corruption resulting from these two. [41.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="388">
    <s id="388:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, this is a presentation of the stages according to twenty-two kinds of delusion and eleven types of corruption.</s>
    <s id="388:2">The unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening does not have any of them.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="389">
    <s id="389:1">“In which case,#280 Blessed One, the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening, the most sublime blessing and result, is truly wondrous!</s>
    <s id="389:2">Once bodhisattvas have torn the great net of delusion in this fashion and gone beyond the vast jungle of corruption, they will awaken to the complete and perfect enlightenment.”#281</s>
  </p>
  <p id="390">
    <s id="390:1">$132“Blessed One, through how many kinds of purifications are these stages presented?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="391">
    <s id="391:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, they are presented through eight purifications:</s>
    <s id="391:2">(1) the purification of intention, (2) the purification of the mind, (3) the purification of compassion, (4) the purification of the perfections, (5) the purification of the vision of buddhas and of their veneration, (6) the purification of bringing beings to maturity, (7) the purification of birth, and (8) the purification of power.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="392">
    <s id="392:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that the purifications on the first stage, from the purification of superior intention up to the purification of power, as well as the purifications on the higher stages including the Buddha Stage, from the purification of superior intention up to the purification of power, become more and more intense.#282</s>
    <s id="392:2">Thus, if one excepts the purification of birth on the Buddha Stage, the qualities on the first stage seem similar to those of the higher stages.</s>
    <s id="392:3">However,</s>
    <s id="392:4">you should know that the qualities of each higher stage are superior to those on the former stage.</s>
    <s id="392:5">You should also understand that the qualities on the ten stages of a bodhisattva can be surpassed, whereas the qualities on the Buddha Stage are unsurpassable.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="393">
    <s id="393:1">$133“Blessed One, why did you declare that, among all kinds of birth, the birth of a bodhisattva is supreme?” [42.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="394">
    <s id="394:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, it is supreme for four reasons:</s>
    <s id="394:2">(1) it accomplishes the great purification of one’s roots of virtue, (2) it is appropriated as a result of mental inspection, (3) it is imbued with the compassion that protects all beings, and (4) it is not itself afflicted, but it repels the afflictions of others.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="395">
    <s id="395:1">$134“Blessed One, why did you declare that bodhisattvas practice with a vast aspiration, are sublime, have a sublime aspiration, and possess the force of aspiration?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="396">
    <s id="396:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, [I declared this] for four reasons:</s>
    <s id="396:2">(1) bodhisattvas are skilled with respect to the blissful state of nirvāṇa, (2) they are able to attain it swiftly, (3) they have both given up this swift attainment and this blissful state, and (4) without wavering or being compelled,#283 they mentally produce the aspiration to go for a long time through many kinds of suffering for the sake of beings.</s>
    <s id="396:3">Therefore, I said that bodhisattvas possess a vast aspiration, a sublime aspiration, and the force of aspiration.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="397">
    <s id="397:1">$135“Blessed One, how many foundations of training do the bodhisattvas have?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="398">
    <s id="398:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, they have six: generosity, discipline, patience, diligence, meditative absorption, and wisdom.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="399">
    <s id="399:1">“Blessed One, among those six, how many constitute the training in superior discipline, how many constitute the training in superior mind, and how many constitute the training in superior wisdom?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="400">
    <s id="400:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that the first three constitute the training in superior discipline,</s>
    <s id="400:2">meditative absorption constitutes the training in superior mind,</s>
    <s id="400:3">wisdom constitutes the training in superior wisdom, and</s>
    <s id="400:4">diligence is present in each of these trainings.” [42.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="401">
    <s id="401:1">“Blessed One, how many of these foundations of training constitute the accumulation of merit?</s>
    <s id="401:2">How many constitute the accumulation of gnosis?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="402">
    <s id="402:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, the training in superior discipline constitutes the accumulation of merit.</s>
    <s id="402:2">The training in superior wisdom constitutes the accumulation of gnosis.</s>
    <s id="402:3">Diligence and meditative absorption are present in both.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="403">
    <s id="403:1">“Blessed One, how do bodhisattvas train in these six foundations of training?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="404">
    <s id="404:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, they train in these six foundations of training according to five points: (1) by having devotion from the beginning for the teaching of the pure Dharma, for the teaching of the six perfections, and for the collection of teachings on the bodhisattva [path];</s>
    <s id="404:2">(2) by accomplishing next the wisdom arising from hearing, contemplating, and practicing [the truth] through the ten activities related to Dharma;</s>
    <s id="404:3">(3) by preserving the awakening mind;</s>
    <s id="404:4">(4) by relying upon a virtuous friend;</s>
    <s id="404:5">and (5) by continuously practicing virtue.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="405">
    <s id="405:1">“Blessed One, why are the foundations of training known in terms of a sixfold classification?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="406">
    <s id="406:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, there are two reasons: (1) they benefit beings and (2) they are antidotes to defilements.</s>
    <s id="406:2">You should know that, among them, three benefit beings while three are antidotes to defilements.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="407">
    <s id="407:1">1.</s>
    <s id="407:2">“Through their generosity, bodhisattvas benefit beings by providing them with what is necessary to life;</s>
    <s id="407:3">through their discipline, they benefit beings by not impoverishing them, harming them, or ridiculing them;</s>
    <s id="407:4">and</s>
    <s id="407:5">through their patience, they benefit beings by enduring impoverishment, harm, and ridicule.</s>
    <s id="407:6">Thus, they benefit beings through these three foundations of training.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="408">
    <s id="408:1">2.</s>
    <s id="408:2">“Through their diligence they apply themselves to the virtue that completely overcomes defilements and eliminates them, since defilements are unable to deflect them from this practice;</s>
    <s id="408:3">through their meditative absorption [43.a] they destroy defilements;</s>
    <s id="408:4">and</s>
    <s id="408:5">through their wisdom they put an end to their latent dispositions.</s>
    <s id="408:6">Thus, these three foundations of training are antidotes to defilements.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="409">
    <s id="409:1">$136“Blessed One, why are the other perfections known in terms of a fourfold classification?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="410">
    <s id="410:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, it is because they assist these six perfections:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="411">
    <s id="411:1">1.</s>
    <s id="411:2">“With the first three perfections, bodhisattvas benefit beings.</s>
    <s id="411:3">Then, they establish beings in virtue through the skillful means consisting of the four methods of conversion.</s>
    <s id="411:4">Therefore, I taught that the perfection of skillful means assists the first three perfections.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="412">
    <s id="412:1">2.</s>
    <s id="412:2">“Avaloki­teśvara, suppose the bodhisattvas are unable to practice at all times in this life as a result of their many defilements.</s>
    <s id="412:3">Suppose they are unable to focus their minds within due to the weakness of their superior intention as a result of their limited experience#284 and aspiration.</s>
    <s id="412:4">Suppose they are unable to accomplish the supramundane wisdom because they did not practice the meditative absorption based on the referential objects corresponding to the teachings on the bodhisattva path they have heard.</s>
    <s id="412:5">However,</s>
    <s id="412:6">since they have accumulated merit, even to a limited extent, they produce with their minds the aspiration that their defilements will decrease in the future.</s>
    <s id="412:7">This is the perfection of aspiration.</s>
    <s id="412:8">Because defilements decrease and bodhisattvas are able to exert their diligence through this perfection, the perfection of aspiration therefore assists the perfection of diligence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="413">
    <s id="413:1">3.</s>
    <s id="413:2">“Then, relying on a noble being and on hearing the Dharma, they attain the state in which they direct their attention on discipline.</s>
    <s id="413:3">Once they have turned away from having a superior intention whose power is limited, they obtain the power of intention of the heavenly realms.#285 This is the perfection of power.</s>
    <s id="413:4">Because bodhisattvas are able to focus on their minds within through this perfection, the perfection of power therefore assists the perfection of meditative absorption. [43.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="414">
    <s id="414:1">4.</s>
    <s id="414:2">“The bodhisattvas settle in meditative absorption as they practice the referential objects corresponding to the teachings on the bodhisattva path they have heard.</s>
    <s id="414:3">This is the perfection of wisdom.</s>
    <s id="414:4">Because bodhisattvas are able to accomplish supramundane wisdom through this perfection, the perfection of gnosis therefore assists the perfection of wisdom.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="415">
    <s id="415:1">$137“Blessed One, why should one know that the six perfections are taught in this order?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="416">
    <s id="416:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, it is because the former is the support on which the latter is established, and so on and so forth.</s>
    <s id="416:2">By not fixating on their bodies and possessions, bodhisattvas acquire discipline.</s>
    <s id="416:3">By maintaining their discipline, they take possession of patience.</s>
    <s id="416:4">Through patience, they engage in diligence.</s>
    <s id="416:5">By having engaged in diligence, they establish meditative absorption.</s>
    <s id="416:6">Once meditative absorption is established, they will obtain the supramundane wisdom.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="417">
    <s id="417:1">$138“Blessed One, of how many kinds are these perfections?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="418">
    <s id="418:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, each of these perfections is of three kinds:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="419">
    <s id="419:1">1.</s>
    <s id="419:2">“The three kinds of generosity are the gift of Dharma, the gift of material objects, and the gift of fearlessness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="420">
    <s id="420:1">2.</s>
    <s id="420:2">“The three kinds of discipline are the discipline that turns away from what is not virtuous, the discipline that engages in virtue, and the discipline that engages in benefiting beings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="421">
    <s id="421:1">3.</s>
    <s id="421:2">“The three kinds of patience are the patience of enduring harm, the patience of not considering [one’s own] suffering, and the patient acceptance of Dharma by means of reflection.#286</s>
  </p>
  <p id="422">
    <s id="422:1">4.</s>
    <s id="422:2">“The three kinds of diligence are the diligence that is like armor, the diligence to practice virtue, and the diligence to benefit beings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="423">
    <s id="423:1">5.</s>
    <s id="423:2">“The three kinds of meditative absorption are the meditative absorption of blissful abiding that, nonconceptual and peaceful, is an antidote to defilements and suffering, the meditative absorption that brings about good qualities, and the meditative absorption that accomplishes the welfare of beings. [44.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="424">
    <s id="424:1">6.</s>
    <s id="424:2">“The three kinds of wisdom are the wisdom that takes the conventional truth as its referential object, the wisdom that takes the ultimate truth as its referential object, and the wisdom that takes the welfare of beings as its referential object.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="425">
    <s id="425:1">$139“Blessed One, why are the perfections called ‘perfections’?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="426">
    <s id="426:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, this is for five reasons.</s>
    <s id="426:2">The perfections are without attachment, disinterested, free from faults, nonconceptual, and dedication of merit:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="427">
    <s id="427:1">1.</s>
    <s id="427:2">“Being without attachment, they are completely devoid of attachment to factors adverse to themselves.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="428">
    <s id="428:1">2.</s>
    <s id="428:2">“Being disinterested, they are free from thoughts fixating on results or on some reward obtained from their accomplishment.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="429">
    <s id="429:1">3.</s>
    <s id="429:2">“Being free from faults, they are not involved with afflicted phenomena and lack unskillful means.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="430">
    <s id="430:1">4.</s>
    <s id="430:2">“Being nonconceptual, they are free from any literal assumption of having a defining characteristic specific to them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="431">
    <s id="431:1">5.</s>
    <s id="431:2">“Being dedication of merit, they are the aspiration for the result of the bodhisattva path by having produced and accumulated#287 these perfections.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="432">
    <s id="432:1">$140“Blessed One, what are the factors adverse to the perfections?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="433">
    <s id="433:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that there are six factors:</s>
    <s id="433:2">(1) considering as beneficial the joy produced by desirous objects, (2) indulging into pleasurable activities through one’s body, speech, or mind, (3) not enduring contempt with patience, (4) invoking merit to justify one’s lack of diligence, (5) being distracted by occupations, entertainment, and people, and (6) considering as beneficial the conventional mental elaborations arising from what one sees, hears, thinks, or is conscious of.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="434">
    <s id="434:1">$141“Blessed One, what is the result of the maturation of these perfections?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="435">
    <s id="435:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, [44.b] you should know that there are six:</s>
    <s id="435:2">(1) great wealth, (2) rebirth in pleasant destinies, (3) happiness and satisfaction from peace and concord, (4) sovereignty over beings, (5) the absence of physical harm, and (6) the renown of having great powers.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="436">
    <s id="436:1">$142“Blessed One, how are these perfections involved with afflicted phenomena?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="437">
    <s id="437:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, they are involved through four practices:</s>
    <s id="437:2">(1) the practice of the perfections without compassion, (2) the improper practice of the perfections, (3) the irregular practice of the perfections, and (4) the negligent practice of the perfections.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="438">
    <s id="438:1">“The improper practice of the perfections occurs when the practice of one of these perfections impairs the practice of the other perfections.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="439">
    <s id="439:1">$143“Blessed One, what are unskillful means?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="440">
    <s id="440:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, the bodhisattvas assist beings by means of these perfections.</s>
    <s id="440:2">If they do not establish beings in virtue once they have pulled them from nonvirtuous states and instead are satisfied to merely provide material objects to them, this is unskillful means.</s>
    <s id="440:3">Why?</s>
    <s id="440:4">Avaloki­teśvara, one does not assist beings by merely doing this.</s>
    <s id="440:5">It is like this: excrements, whether in large or small quantity, cannot be made to smell good by any method#288 whatsoever.</s>
    <s id="440:6">Likewise, no method that merely supports beings with material objects can make happy those who are suffering because their nature is to experience the suffering arising from being conditioned.#289 In contrast,</s>
    <s id="440:7">establishing them in virtue is the best and only way to benefit them.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="441">
    <s id="441:1">$144“Blessed One, how many kinds of purification are [included] in these perfections?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="442">
    <s id="442:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, I did not state that there were other purifications apart from the five kinds [I have already mentioned].#290 However,</s>
    <s id="442:2">in relation to what I have already explained, [45.a] I will clarify for you the (1) general and (2) specific purifications included in the perfections.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="443">
    <s id="443:1">1.</s>
    <s id="443:2">“You should know that the general purifications that are common to all perfections include seven points:</s>
    <s id="443:3">(1) bodhisattvas do not seek to make a profit from others through the teachings on the bodhisattva path;</s>
    <s id="443:4">(2) they do not produce wrong conceptions with regard to these teachings;</s>
    <s id="443:5">(3) with respect to these teachings, they do not give rise to indecision or doubts as to whether they will attain awakening or not;</s>
    <s id="443:6">(4) they do not praise themselves, nor do they blame others or despise them;</s>
    <s id="443:7">(5) they do not generate arrogance or carelessness;</s>
    <s id="443:8">(6) they are not satisfied with only limited or inferior attainments;</s>
    <s id="443:9">and (7) they are not stingy or envious of others because of these teachings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="444">
    <s id="444:1">2.</s>
    <s id="444:2">“You should know that the purifications specific to each perfection also includes seven points:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="445">
    <s id="445:1">“The seven points of the purification included in the perfection of generosity are as follows: (1) bodhisattvas practice generosity that is the purification of generosity through the purification#291 of the object that is the gift, and (2–7) they practice generosity that is the purification of generosity through the purification of discipline, view, mind, speech, knowledge, and stains.</s>
    <s id="445:2">Thus, as I have just explained, the purifications included in the perfection of generosity that bodhisattvas obtain and practice constitute the seven aspects of the purification of generosity.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="446">
    <s id="446:1">“The seven points of the purification included in the perfection of discipline are as follows: (1) bodhisattvas are skilled in all aspects of the foundation of training related to vows, (2) they are skilled in removing transgressions, (3) their discipline is free from doubts, (4) they have a firm discipline, (5) they maintain discipline in all circumstances, (6) they engage in discipline at all times, and (7) they engage in the training by correctly practicing the foundations of training.</s>
    <s id="446:2">These are the seven aspects of the purification of discipline.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="447">
    <s id="447:1">“The seven points of the purification included in the perfection of patience are as follows: (1) when confronted with any kind of adversity, bodhisattvas do not waver because they are confident in the maturation of their karma;</s>
    <s id="447:2">[45.b] (2) they do not engage in harming others by abusing, insulting, striking, intimidating, or criticizing them in order to retaliate;</s>
    <s id="447:3">(3) they do not hold grudges;</s>
    <s id="447:4">(4) when accused,#292 they do not give rise to defilements;</s>
    <s id="447:5">(5) they themselves do not indulge in accusations;</s>
    <s id="447:6">(6) they do not practice patience with a mind that is fearful of consequences or interested;</s>
    <s id="447:7">and (7) they do not fail to accomplish others’ benefit.</s>
    <s id="447:8">These are the seven purifications of patience.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="448">
    <s id="448:1">“The seven points of the purification included in the perfection of diligence are as follows: (1) bodhisattvas understand the equanimity of diligence;</s>
    <s id="448:2">(2) with reference to diligence, they neither praise themselves nor deprecate others;</s>
    <s id="448:3">(3–6) they are powerful, diligent, enthusiastic, and resolute;</s>
    <s id="448:4">and (7) they never cease to be diligent with respect to virtuous qualities.</s>
    <s id="448:5">These are the seven purifications of diligence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="449">
    <s id="449:1">“The seven points of the purification included in the perfection of meditative absorption are (1) the meditative absorption in the concentration that understands phenomenal appearance, (2) the perfect meditative absorption in concentration, (3) the meditative absorption in the concentration that has these two aspects, (4) the meditative absorption in the spontaneously arising concentration, (5) the meditative absorption in the concentration without support, (6) the meditative absorption in the concentration that produces flexibility, and (7) the meditative absorption in the concentration in the boundless practice of the referential objects corresponding to the teachings on the bodhisattva path.</s>
    <s id="449:2">These are the seven purifications of meditative absorption.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="450">
    <s id="450:1">“The seven points of the purification included in the perfection of wisdom are as follows: (1) Once they have abandoned the extremes of superimposition and negation by means of wisdom, bodhisattvas emerge [from cyclic existence] through the middle path. (2) On account of this wisdom, they realize the very meaning of the gate to liberation exactly as it is, namely, the threefold gate to liberation: emptiness, wishlessness, and appearancelessness.</s>
    <s id="450:2">(3) They realize exactly as it is the very meaning of essence, namely, the threefold essence: the imaginary, the other-dependent, and the actual. (4) They realize exactly as it is the very meaning of essencelessness, namely, the threefold essencelessness regarding defining characteristics, arising, and the ultimate. [46.a]</s>
    <s id="450:3">(5) They realize exactly as it is the very meaning of the conventional truth in relation to the five sciences.#293 (6) They realize exactly as it is the very meaning of the ultimate truth with respect to the seven aspects of true reality. (7) They frequently abide in the unique approach of the nonconceptual state free of mental elaborations.</s>
    <s id="450:4">By means of the insight that takes countless universal teachings as its referential object, they correctly accomplish the attainment resulting from the practice of the teachings that are in harmony with Dharma.</s>
    <s id="450:5">You should know that these are the seven purifications of meditative absorption.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="451">
    <s id="451:1">$145“Blessed One, what is the function of each of these five purifications?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="452">
    <s id="452:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that the five functions are as follows:</s>
    <s id="452:2">(1) Having no attachment, the bodhisattvas continuously practice the perfections in this life.</s>
    <s id="452:3">Because they practice them with enthusiasm, they are conscientious.</s>
    <s id="452:4">(2) Being disinterested, they obtain the cause for the careful practice of these perfections in their future lives.</s>
    <s id="452:5">(3) Free of any wrongdoing, they practice the perfect, pure, and stainless perfections.</s>
    <s id="452:6">(4) Unburdened by conceptions, they swiftly perfect the perfections through their skillful means.</s>
    <s id="452:7">(5) Because they transfer their merit, they will attain in all their future lives the inexhaustible perfections together with the desirable results produced by the maturation of their karma, until they obtain the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="453">
    <s id="453:1">$146“Blessed One, what is the vastness of the bodhisattvas’ practice of these perfections?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="454">
    <s id="454:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, bodhisattvas are without attachment and disinterested, and they transfer their merit.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="455">
    <s id="455:1">“In what way are they without afflictions?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="456">
    <s id="456:1">“They are free of any wrongdoing and conceptions.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="457">
    <s id="457:1">“In what way are they stainless?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="458">
    <s id="458:1">“They act as they mentally inspect.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="459">
    <s id="459:1">“In what way are they immovable?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="460">
    <s id="460:1">“They are said to be immovable because this is the nature of those who have entered the stages of a bodhisattva.” [46.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="461">
    <s id="461:1">“In what way are the perfections utterly pure?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="462">
    <s id="462:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, they are included within the tenth stage and the Buddha Stage.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="463">
    <s id="463:1">$147“Blessed One, why is the desirable result of the maturation resulting from the practice of the perfections always inexhaustible#294 in the case of the bodhisattvas?</s>
    <s id="463:2">Why do they obtain this inexhaustibility through the perfections?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="464">
    <s id="464:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, it is because they practice each perfection#295 in dependence upon the others.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="465">
    <s id="465:1">$148“Blessed One, why is it that bodhisattvas do not have faith in the desirable result of the maturation resulting from the practice of the perfections in the way they have faith in the perfections?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="466">
    <s id="466:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, this is due to five reasons: (1) The perfections are the cause for the highest bliss and happiness, (2) they are the cause for the benefit of oneself and others, (3) they are the cause for the desirable result of their maturation in future lives, (4) they are the foundation of the freedom from afflictions, and (5) they have the nature of immutability.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="467">
    <s id="467:1">$149“Blessed One, what are their specific powers?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="468">
    <s id="468:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, you should know that their specific powers have the following four qualities:</s>
    <s id="468:2">(1) When the bodhisattvas practice the perfections, they eliminate adverse factors, such as greed, faulty discipline, mental agitation, laziness, distraction, and wrong views;</s>
    <s id="468:3">(2) they will attain the unsurpassable, complete and perfect awakening;</s>
    <s id="468:4">(3) in this life, they will benefit themselves as well as beings;</s>
    <s id="468:5">and (4) in future lives they will attain the desirable result of their maturation, which is vast and inexhaustible.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="469">
    <s id="469:1">$150“Blessed One, from what cause do these perfections arise?</s>
    <s id="469:2">What are their result and benefit?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="470">
    <s id="470:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, the perfections have compassion as their cause.</s>
    <s id="470:2">As result, they have the desirable result of their maturation and [47.a] the result accomplishing the benefit of beings.</s>
    <s id="470:3">As benefit, they have the great benefit of accomplishing the great awakening.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="471">
    <s id="471:1">$151“Blessed One, if the bodhisattvas have inexhaustible resources as well as compassion for beings, why are there poor people in the world?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="472">
    <s id="472:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, this is nothing but the fault resulting from beings’ own karma.</s>
    <s id="472:2">If it were not so, if no obstruction were brought about by beings’ own faults, bodhisattvas could at all times engage in compassionate activities toward them.</s>
    <s id="472:3">As bodhisattvas have inexhaustible resources, how could the vision of suffering manifest?</s>
    <s id="472:4">Avaloki­teśvara, it is like this: hungry ghosts whose bodies are tormented by thirst perceive the waters of the ocean as a dry and barren place.</s>
    <s id="472:5">This is not the fault of the ocean but the fault resulting from the maturation of nothing but these hungry ghosts’ own karma.</s>
    <s id="472:6">Likewise, the absence of result is not the fault of the bodhisattvas’ generosity, which is like the ocean, but the fault of beings themselves, the fault resulting from the karma of those who are like hungry ghosts.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="473">
    <s id="473:1">$152“Blessed One, through which perfection do bodhisattvas apprehend essencelessness?”#296</s>
  </p>
  <p id="474">
    <s id="474:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, they apprehend it through the perfection of wisdom.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="475">
    <s id="475:1">“Blessed One, when they apprehend essencelessness through the perfection of wisdom, why then do they not apprehend that essencelessness has an essence?”#297</s>
  </p>
  <p id="476">
    <s id="476:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, I did not declare that essencelessness is apprehended by means of an essence.#298 However,</s>
    <s id="476:2">if one does not use expressions to teach, it is impossible to explain that this essencelessness is inexpressible and cognized intuitively.</s>
    <s id="476:3">On this basis, I said that they perceive essencelessness.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="477">
    <s id="477:1">$153“Blessed One, what is called perfection, immediate perfection,#299 and great perfection?” [47.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="478">
    <s id="478:1">1.</s>
    <s id="478:2">“Avaloki­teśvara, bodhisattvas possess virtuous qualities, generosity and so on, that they have practiced over immeasurable periods of time.</s>
    <s id="478:3">But</s>
    <s id="478:4">when defilements arise in them, they are unable to overcome them and, instead, are overcome by them.</s>
    <s id="478:5">Thus,</s>
    <s id="478:6">this inferior and intermediate aspiration on the stage where one proceeds by means of aspiration is called perfection.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="479">
    <s id="479:1">2.</s>
    <s id="479:2">“Then, bodhisattvas possess virtuous qualities that they have practiced during further immeasurable periods of time.</s>
    <s id="479:3">When defilements arise in them, these bodhisattvas overcome them and cannot be overcome by them.</s>
    <s id="479:4">Thus,</s>
    <s id="479:5">taking hold of these qualities beginning with the first stage is called immediate perfection.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="480">
    <s id="480:1">3.</s>
    <s id="480:2">“Next, bodhisattvas possess virtuous qualities that they have practiced during even longer immeasurable periods of time.</s>
    <s id="480:3">In the bearer of such qualities, no defilement arises at all.</s>
    <s id="480:4">Thus,</s>
    <s id="480:5">taking hold of these qualities beginning with the eighth stage is called great perfection.”#300</s>
  </p>
  <p id="481">
    <s id="481:1">$154“Blessed One, how many kinds of latent dispositions toward defilements are there on the stages?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="482">
    <s id="482:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, there are three:#301</s>
  </p>
  <p id="483">
    <s id="483:1">1.</s>
    <s id="483:2">“The latent dispositions that destroy the factors conducive to the manifestation of defilements are as follows:</s>
    <s id="483:3">on the first five stages, the factors conducive to the manifestation of innate defilements are non-innate defilements.</s>
    <s id="483:4">At that point, these factors do not manifest.</s>
    <s id="483:5">As a consequence, these latent dispositions are called latent dispositions that destroy the factors conducive [to the manifestation of defilements].</s>
  </p>
  <p id="484">
    <s id="484:1">2.</s>
    <s id="484:2">“The latent dispositions of limited power are as follows:</s>
    <s id="484:3">on the sixth and seventh stages, subtle aspects of the latent dispositions manifest and through practice are suppressed.</s>
    <s id="484:4">Therefore, as a consequence of this subtle manifestation, these latent dispositions are called latent dispositions of limited power.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="485">
    <s id="485:1">3.</s>
    <s id="485:2">“The subtle latent dispositions are as follows: on the eighth stage and above, defilements do not manifest at all because there only remain cognitive obstructions to be cleared.</s>
    <s id="485:3">Therefore, these latent dispositions are called subtle latent dispositions.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="486">
    <s id="486:1">$155“Blessed One, how many kinds of elimination of corruption characterize these latent dispositions?”#302</s>
  </p>
  <p id="487">
    <s id="487:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, there are three kinds:#303</s>
    <s id="487:2">(1) the elimination of superficial corruption characterizes the first and the second type of latent dispositions]#304</s>
    <s id="487:3">(2) the elimination of deeper corruption characterizes [48.a] the third type of latent dispositions, and</s>
    <s id="487:4">(3) since the elimination of the innermost corruption is the state in which there are no latent dispositions at all, I have taught that it is the Buddha Stage.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="488">
    <s id="488:1">$156“Blessed One, after how many eons are these types of corruption eliminated?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="489">
    <s id="489:1">“Avaloki­teśvara, they are abandoned within three incalculable periods of time—within immeasurable eons, seasons, moons, half-moons, days and nights, days, half days, hours, minutes, seconds, or split seconds.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="490">
    <s id="490:1">$157“Blessed One, how should the defining characteristic, the fault, and the positive quality of defilements arising in bodhisattvas be known?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="491">
    <s id="491:1">1.</s>
    <s id="491:2">“Avaloki­teśvara, defilements arising in bodhisattvas have the defining characteristic of nondefilement.</s>
    <s id="491:3">Why?</s>
    <s id="491:4">Because they fully realize the domain of truth, which is only determined on the first stage.</s>
    <s id="491:5">On account of this, the defilements of bodhisattvas arise only with full awareness, not unconsciously.</s>
    <s id="491:6">Therefore, [defilements arising in bodhisattvas have] the defining characteristic of nondefilements.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="492">
    <s id="492:1">2.</s>
    <s id="492:2">“Because they do not have the capacity to produce suffering in [bodhisattvas’] own [mental] continuums, they are faultless.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="493">
    <s id="493:1">3.</s>
    <s id="493:2">“Because they are the cause dispelling the suffering from the world of beings, they have boundless positive qualities.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="494">
    <s id="494:1">“Blessed One, if even the defilements arising in this way in bodhisattvas outshine the roots of virtue produced by all beings, hearers, and solitary realizers to such an extent, what need is there to mention their other positive qualities?#305</s>
    <s id="494:2">The supreme value of the bodhisattvas’ awakening is truly amazing!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="495">
    <s id="495:1">$158“Blessed One, what was your underlying intention when you declared that the vehicle of the hearers and the Great Vehicle constitute the Single Vehicle?” [48.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="496">
    <s id="496:1">“In the vehicle of the hearers, I taught the essence of various phenomena, such as the five aggregates, the six internal sense domains, the six external sense domains, and so forth.</s>
    <s id="496:2">In the Great Vehicle, I presented exactly these same phenomena by teaching them in terms of a single principle, the domain of truth.</s>
    <s id="496:3">Therefore, I did not declare that [these two] vehicles are distinct from one another.</s>
    <s id="496:4">Those who conceptualize these teachings exclusively according to their literal meaning also conceptualize these [two] vehicles as being distinct—some by superimposing, others by negating.</s>
    <s id="496:5">As a consequence,</s>
    <s id="496:6">they think that the two vehicles are contradictory#306 and thus refute one another.</s>
    <s id="496:7">This is what I had in mind when I taught the Single Vehicle.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="497">
    <s id="497:1">$159Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="498">
    <s id="498:1">“The very teachings on the nature of various phenomenaTaught in the lower and higher vehiclesAre teachings of a single principle.</s>
    <s id="498:2">This is why I did not declare the vehicles to be distinct from one another.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="499">
    <s id="499:1">“Those who conceptualize according to the literal meaning of the teachingsThink that these vehicles are contradictory As a result of their superimpositions and negations,And so from delusion arise various opinions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="500">
    <s id="500:1">“The buddhas taught as the Great Vehicle What is included within the stages of a bodhisattva and a buddha,The names of these stages, and their adverse factors, specific arising, aspiration, and training.</s>
    <s id="500:2">Those who will exert themselves in this will become buddhas.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="501">
    <s id="501:1">Then, the bodhisattva Avaloki­teśvara asked the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="501:2">“Blessed One, what is the name of the teaching imparted in this Dharma discourse that unravels the Tathāgata’s intent?</s>
    <s id="501:3">How should I keep it in mind?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="502">
    <s id="502:1">The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="502:2">“Avaloki­teśvara, this is a teaching of definitive meaning on the stages and the perfections.</s>
    <s id="502:3">Keep it in mind as The Teaching of Definitive Meaning on the Stages and the Perfections.</s>
    <s id="502:4">As the Blessed One expounded this teaching,</s>
    <s id="502:5">seventy-five thousand bodhisattvas obtained the bodhisattva’s concentration, the light of the Great Vehicle. [49.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="503">
    <s id="503:1">This was the chapter of the bodhisattva Avaloki­teśvara—the ninth chapter.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="504">
    <s id="504:1">Chapter 10</s>
  </p>
  <p id="505">
    <s id="505:1">$160Then the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī addressed the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="505:2">“Blessed One, when you mention ‘the truth body of the tathāgatas,’ what is the defining characteristic of this truth body of the tathāgatas?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="506">
    <s id="506:1">The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="506:2">“Mañjuśrī, the truth body of the tathāgatas is characterized when one has fully achieved a shift in one’s basis of existence, the emergence [from cyclic existence] through the practice of the stages and the perfections.#307</s>
    <s id="506:3">Because of the two [following] reasons, you should know that this truth body is characterized by inconceivability:</s>
    <s id="506:4">(1) it is beyond mental elaborations and is not produced by intentional action,#308 (2) while beings are fixated on mental elaborations and produced by intentional action.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="507">
    <s id="507:1">$161“Blessed One, is the shift in the hearers’ and solitary realizers’ basis of existence also designated as the truth body?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="508">
    <s id="508:1">“Mañjuśrī, it is not.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="509">
    <s id="509:1">“Blessed One, how should it be called?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="510">
    <s id="510:1">“Mañjuśrī, it should be called the liberation body.#309</s>
    <s id="510:2">With regard to the liberation body, the tathāgatas are similar and equal to the hearers and solitary realizers, but,</s>
    <s id="510:3">on account of the truth body, they are distinctively superior to them.</s>
    <s id="510:4">This being so, they are also distinctively superior to them in terms of the distinctively immeasurable aspect of their positive qualities.</s>
    <s id="510:5">This is not easy to illustrate with examples.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="511">
    <s id="511:1">$162“Blessed One, how should we consider those who have the characteristic of manifesting themselves through the birth of a tathāgata?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="512">
    <s id="512:1">“Mañjuśrī, those who have the characteristic of the emanation body#310 resemble those who manifest in the world realms.</s>
    <s id="512:2">You should see them as those whose characteristic is to be established by the sovereign power#311 of the buddhas, being fully adorned with the ornaments of the tathāgatas’ qualities.</s>
    <s id="512:3">The truth body does not have this manifestation of arising.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="513">
    <s id="513:1">$163“Blessed One, how should we consider the skillful means employed by the emanation body [for the sake of liberating beings from cyclic existence]?”#312[49.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="514">
    <s id="514:1">“Mañjuśrī, being conceived in a family renowned to be powerful or honorable in all the buddha fields of the trichiliocosm, taking birth, growing up, enjoying desirous objects, leaving home, displaying immediately the practice of austerities, renouncing them, and displaying all the stages of the complete and perfect awakening should be considered as the skillful means of the emanation body.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="515">
    <s id="515:1">“Blessed One, through which teachings emanating from their sovereign power do the tathāgatas bring to maturity those spiritually immature beings who have been converted?</s>
    <s id="515:2">How do they liberate spiritually mature beings by means of the very referential object [taught in the Great Vehicle]?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="516">
    <s id="516:1">“Mañjuśrī, they bring them to maturity through three teachings: the sūtras, the Vinaya, and the mātṛkās.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="517">
    <s id="517:1">$164“Blessed One, what are the sūtras, the Vinaya, and the mātṛkās?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="518">
    <s id="518:1">“Mañjuśrī, it is like this: sūtras are teachings that gather the subject matter of various Dharma methods in four, nine, or twenty-nine topics.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="519">
    <s id="519:1">1.</s>
    <s id="519:2">“What are the four topics?</s>
    <s id="519:3">They are (i) what was heard, (ii) taking refuge, (iii) the training, and (iv) the awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="520">
    <s id="520:1">2.</s>
    <s id="520:2">“What are the nine topics?</s>
    <s id="520:3">They are (i) concepts of sentient beings, (ii) their possessions, (iii) their birth, (iv) their existence after birth, (v) their affliction and purification, (vi) their diversity, (vii) the teacher, (viii) the teaching, and (ix) the assembly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="521">
    <s id="521:1">3.</s>
    <s id="521:2">“What are the twenty-nine topics?</s>
    <s id="521:3">They are the topics related to affliction: (i) [the phenomena] included in the conditioned, (ii) their progressive activity, (iii) the cause of their arising in future lives once they have been conceptualized as a person, and (iv) the cause of their arising in future lives once they have been conceptualized as phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="522">
    <s id="522:1">“They are also the topics related to purification: [50.a] (v) the referential objects that are taken as reference points;#313 (vi) the exertion in [the practice of] these very [objects];</s>
    <s id="522:2">(vii) mental abiding;#314 (viii) blissful abiding in this very life;</s>
    <s id="522:3">(ix) the referential objects that liberate from all suffering;</s>
    <s id="522:4">(x) the three kinds of comprehension, which are the comprehension of the basis of error, the comprehension of the basis of error with respect to beings’ conceptions for nonpractitioners, and the comprehension of the basis of humility for those who practice Dharma;</s>
    <s id="522:5">(xi) the basis of practice;</s>
    <s id="522:6">(xii) the actualization [of practice];#315 (xiii) the practice;</s>
    <s id="522:7">(xiv) [the practice] as the central activity;</s>
    <s id="522:8">(xv) its aspects;</s>
    <s id="522:9">(xvi) its referential objects;</s>
    <s id="522:10">(xvii) the skills in the investigation of what has already been eliminated and what not yet been eliminated;</s>
    <s id="522:11">(xviii) [the factors] that are distractions from practice;</s>
    <s id="522:12">(xix) [the factors] that are not distractions from practice;</s>
    <s id="522:13">(xx) the source of nondistraction;</s>
    <s id="522:14">(xxi) the yoga of clear mindfulness#316 that is protected by#317 the practice;</s>
    <s id="522:15">(xxii) the benefit of practice;</s>
    <s id="522:16">(xxiii) its stability;</s>
    <s id="522:17">(xiv) the unification with the lord of the noble [practice];</s>
    <s id="522:18">(xv) the unification with its retinue and entourage;</s>
    <s id="522:19">(xxvi) the realization of true reality;</s>
    <s id="522:20">(xxvii) the attainment of nirvāṇa;</s>
    <s id="522:21">(xxviii) the fact that the well-expounded Dharma and Vinaya are superior to the correct views of mundane beings and all nonpractitioners;</s>
    <s id="522:22">and (xxix) the impairments resulting from not practicing.</s>
    <s id="522:23">Thus,</s>
    <s id="522:24">Mañjuśrī, without practicing the well-expounded Dharma and Vinaya, impairments will ensue, and this is not because one has faulty views.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="523">
    <s id="523:1">$165“Mañjuśrī, the Vinaya is my teaching on prātimokṣa for hearers and bodhisattvas, as well as that which is associated with it.” [50.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="524">
    <s id="524:1">“Blessed One, how many topics are included in [the teaching on the] prātimokṣa of bodhisattvas?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="525">
    <s id="525:1">“Mañjuśrī, there are seven topics: (1) the teachings on the ceremony of taking [the vows of the bodhisattva discipline], (2) the teachings on the basis of serious downfalls,#318 (3) the teachings on the basis of transgressions, (4) the teachings on the nature of transgressions, (5) the teachings on the nature of what are not transgressions, (6) the teachings on the emergence from transgressions, and (7) the teachings on the abandonment of the vows.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="526">
    <s id="526:1">$166“Mañjuśrī, the mātṛkās are the teachings that I imparted and categorized into eleven topics.</s>
    <s id="526:2">What are these eleven topics?</s>
    <s id="526:3">They are (1) the defining characteristic of the conventional, (2) the defining characteristic of the ultimate, (3) the defining characteristic of referential objects consisting of the awakening factors, (4) the defining characteristic of their features;</s>
    <s id="526:4">(5) the defining characteristic of the[ir] nature, (6) the defining characteristic of their result, (7) the defining characteristic of the description of the experience of them, (8) the defining characteristic of the factors disrupting them,#319 (9) the defining characteristic of the factors conducive to them, (10) the defining characteristic of the defects related to them, and (11) the defining characteristic of their benefit.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="527">
    <s id="527:1">1.</s>
    <s id="527:2">“Mañjuśrī, consider that the defining characteristic of the conventional has three subtopics:</s>
    <s id="527:3">(1) the teaching on persons, (2) the teaching on the imaginary nature, and (3) the teaching on the activity, movement, and action of phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="528">
    <s id="528:1">2.</s>
    <s id="528:2">“Consider the defining characteristic of the ultimate in terms of the teaching on the seven aspects of true reality.#320</s>
  </p>
  <p id="529">
    <s id="529:1">3.</s>
    <s id="529:2">“Consider the defining characteristic of referential objects in terms of the teaching on all the things corresponding to cognitive objects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="530">
    <s id="530:1">4.</s>
    <s id="530:2">“Consider the defining characteristic of [their] features in terms of the teaching on the eight features of the analysis of cognitive objects.</s>
    <s id="530:3">What are these eight?</s>
    <s id="530:4">They are (i) the truth of cognitive objects, (ii) their determination,#321 (iii) their faults, (iv) their positive qualities, (v) the methods for analyzing, (vi) the processes related to them, (vii) the principles of reason, and (viii) the condensed and extensive presentations of cognitive objects.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="531">
    <s id="531:1">i.</s>
    <s id="531:2">“With respect to these eight points, the truth of cognitive objects is true reality.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="532">
    <s id="532:1">ii.</s>
    <s id="532:2">“The determination of cognitive objects consists in establishing the person or the imaginary essence [51.a] or in establishing categorical, analytical, interrogative, and dismissive answers as well as secret instructions.#322</s>
  </p>
  <p id="533">
    <s id="533:1">iii.</s>
    <s id="533:2">“The faults of cognitive objects are the defects of phenomena related to affliction, which I have taught in several ways.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="534">
    <s id="534:1">iv.</s>
    <s id="534:2">“The positive qualities of cognitive objects are the benefits arising from phenomena related to purification, which I have taught in several ways.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="535">
    <s id="535:1">v.</s>
    <s id="535:2">“The methods for analyzing cognitive objects includes six points:</s>
    <s id="535:3">(a) the method for analyzing the meaning of true reality;</s>
    <s id="535:4">(b) the method for analyzing attainments;</s>
    <s id="535:5">(c) the method for analyzing explanations;</s>
    <s id="535:6">(d) the method for analyzing the elimination of the two extremes;</s>
    <s id="535:7">(e) the method for analyzing the inconceivable;</s>
    <s id="535:8">and (f) the method for analyzing the underlying intention.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="536">
    <s id="536:1">vi.</s>
    <s id="536:2">“The processes related to cognitive objects are the three times, the three defining characteristics of the conditioned, and the four conditions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="537">
    <s id="537:1">vii.</s>
    <s id="537:2">“There are four principles of reason in the analysis of cognitive objects:</s>
    <s id="537:3">(a) the principle of reason based on dependence, (b) the principle of reason based on cause and effect, (c) the principle of reason based on logical proof, and (d) the principle of reason based on the nature of phenomena itself.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="538">
    <s id="538:1">a.</s>
    <s id="538:2">“The arising of conditioned phenomena and the causes for their being expressed through conventions, as well as related causal conditions, constitute the principle of reason based on dependence.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="539">
    <s id="539:1">b.</s>
    <s id="539:2">“The causes that will bring about a result,#323 a completion, or an action once phenomena have arisen, as well as related causal conditions, constitute the principle of reason based on cause and effect.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="540">
    <s id="540:1">c.</s>
    <s id="540:2">“The causes establishing the meaning and bringing about the valid understanding of the thesis,#324 the demonstration, and the statement of a proof, as well as related causal conditions, constitute the principle of reason based on logical proof.#325</s>
    <s id="540:3">This logical proof is, moreover, of two kinds: valid and invalid.</s>
    <s id="540:4">Among these, five are characterized as valid#326 and seven as invalid.</s>
    <s id="540:5">What are the five logical proofs characterized as valid?</s>
    <s id="540:6">They are the logical proofs characterized by (I) a perception that is a direct cognition of the thing to establish,#327 (II) a perception that is a direct cognition of something existing in dependence on the thing to establish,#328 (III) a demonstration through an instance belonging to the same class,#329[51.b] (IV) an actual demonstration, and (V) a citation from a valid scripture.#330</s>
  </p>
  <p id="541">
    <s id="541:1">“With regard to those five logical proofs:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="542">
    <s id="542:1">I. “The logical proof characterized by the perception that is a direct cognition of the thing to establish consists [for example] in perceiving through a direct cognition that all conditioned phenomena are impermanent, suffering, and without a self as well as anything conforming to this.#331</s>
  </p>
  <p id="543">
    <s id="543:1">II.</s>
    <s id="543:2">“The logical proof characterized by a direct cognition of something existing in dependence on the thing to establish consists in inferring something not directly perceptible by means of something#332 [directly perceptible], as well as in anything conforming to this, [for example], (A) the perception as a direct cognition of the principle of impermanence that exists in dependence on the things to establish, [namely,] the momentariness of all conditioned phenomena, the existence of a next life, and the consequence of good and bad deeds;#333 (B) the perception as direct cognition of the diversity of beings that exists in dependence on the thing to establish, [namely,] the diversity of karma;</s>
    <s id="543:3">or (C) the direct cognition of the happiness and suffering of beings that exists in dependence on the things to establish, [namely,] virtue and nonvirtue].#334</s>
  </p>
  <p id="544">
    <s id="544:1">III.</s>
    <s id="544:2">“You should know that the logical proof characterized by a demonstration through an instance belonging to the same class of phenomena#335 consists in anything conforming to this, [for example] in the demonstration of external and internal conditioned phenomena through (A) the perception of death and rebirth, being born and other forms of suffering,#336 and causal dependence,#337 which are established as facts in all worlds or (B) the perception of wealth and misery, which are established as facts in all worlds, including those of future lives.#338</s>
  </p>
  <p id="545">
    <s id="545:1">IV.</s>
    <s id="545:2">“Thus, you should know that a logical proof characterized by one of the three proofs mentioned above#339 is an actual demonstration because it is conclusive with respect to the thing that must be established.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="546">
    <s id="546:1">V. “Mañjuśrī, you should know that the logical proof characterized by a citation from a valid scripture consists in the words taught by quoting the omniscient ones, such as ‘Nirvāṇa is peace’ and other similar statements. [52.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="547">
    <s id="547:1">“Therefore, on account of these five kinds of characteristics, an analysis of cognitive objects founded on the principle of reason based on logical proof is valid.#340 Because such an analysis is valid, you should rely on it.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="548">
    <s id="548:1">“Blessed One, how many qualities do those we should consider as having the defining characteristics of the omniscient tathāgatas have?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="549">
    <s id="549:1">“Mañjuśrī, they have five qualities:</s>
    <s id="549:2">(A) wherever they manifest, they are renowned in this world for their omniscience;</s>
    <s id="549:3">(B) they have the thirty-two marks of a great being;</s>
    <s id="549:4">(C) by means of their ten powers, they eliminate all qualms affecting beings;</s>
    <s id="549:5">(D) the words of the Dharma they teach through the four kinds of assurance cannot be refuted or disputed by any opponent;</s>
    <s id="549:6">(E) on the basis of their Dharma and Vinaya, the eightfold noble path as well as the four noble truths manifest for those who have renounced cyclic existence.#341</s>
    <s id="549:7">Thus, you should know that their manifestation, marks, elimination of doubts, freedom from refutations and disputes, and support [for those who have renounced cyclic existence] constitute the defining characteristic of the omniscient tathāgatas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="550">
    <s id="550:1">“Thus, the principle of reason based on logical proof is valid on account of the five characteristics included within these valid cognitions: direct cognitions, inferences, and authoritative scriptures.#342</s>
  </p>
  <p id="551">
    <s id="551:1">“What are the seven logical proofs characterized as invalid?</s>
    <s id="551:2">They are the logical proofs characterized by (I) a perception that conforms with something other than the thing to be established,#343 (II) a perception that does not conform with anything other than the thing to establish,#344 (III) a perception that conforms with all things,#345 (IV) a perception that does not conform with anything,#346 (V) a demonstration through an instance belonging to a different class of phenomena,#347 (VI) a demonstration that is not actually demonstrating anything, and (VII) a citation drawn from an invalid scripture.</s>
    <s id="551:3"/>
  </p>
  <p id="552">
    <s id="552:1">“The logical proof characterized by a perception that does not conform with anything#348 is ascertained when the defining characteristics of the proof and the premise do not conform with one another because they are incompatible in terms of reason, essence, karma, quality, or cause and effect.#349[52.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="553">
    <s id="553:1">“Mañjuśrī, the logical proof characterized by a perception that does not conform with anything#350 is comprised by the logical proof characterized by a perception that conforms with something other than the thing to be established#351 and similar instances.</s>
    <s id="553:2">This proof is therefore inconclusive with respect to the thing to establish.#352 This is called an unestablished logical proof.#353</s>
  </p>
  <p id="554">
    <s id="554:1">“Moreover, the logical proof characterized by a perception that conforms with all things#354 is comprised by the logical proof characterized by a perception that does not conform with anything other than the thing to establish#355 and similar instances.</s>
    <s id="554:2">This proof is therefore inconclusive with respect to the thing to establish.</s>
    <s id="554:3">This is also called an unestablished logical proof.#356</s>
  </p>
  <p id="555">
    <s id="555:1">“Because these logical proofs are not established, the analysis is invalid according to the principle of reason based on logical proof.</s>
    <s id="555:2">Since this analysis is invalid, you should not rely on it.</s>
    <s id="555:3">You should know that the logical proof characterized by a citation from an invalid scripture is invalid by nature.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="556">
    <s id="556:1">d.</s>
    <s id="556:2">“Whether tathāgatas manifest or not, the constancy of the domain of truth, the nature of phenomena, on account of the constancy of phenomena, constitutes the principle of reason based on the nature of phenomena.#357</s>
  </p>
  <p id="557">
    <s id="557:1">viii.</s>
    <s id="557:2">“The condensed and the extensive presentation of cognitive objects consists of first summarizing, then analyzing words and sections of the teaching, and finally concluding the explanation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="558">
    <s id="558:1">5.</s>
    <s id="558:2">“The defining characteristic of the nature of awakening factors consists in the apprehension of a referential object together with its aspects, as I have taught, such as the awakening factors, the four applications of mindfulness, and so on.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="559">
    <s id="559:1">6.</s>
    <s id="559:2">“The defining characteristic of their result is the accomplishment of their result, the mundane and supramundane positive qualities, by abandoning the defilements associated with the mundane or the supramundane phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="560">
    <s id="560:1">7.</s>
    <s id="560:2">“The defining characteristic of accounts telling how one experiences them as one proclaims them, explains them, and correctly teach them to others is the analytical knowledge of the gnosis#358 that liberates within true reality.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="561">
    <s id="561:1">8.</s>
    <s id="561:2">“The defining characteristic of the factors disrupting them is the afflicted phenomenon in the form of an obstacle to the practice of these very awakening factors. [53.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="562">
    <s id="562:1">9.</s>
    <s id="562:2">“The defining characteristic of the factors conducive to them is the phenomenon useful to [enhancing] them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="563">
    <s id="563:1">10.”</s>
    <s id="563:2">The defining characteristic of defects related to them is the fault interrupting them.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="564">
    <s id="564:1">11.</s>
    <s id="564:2">“Mañjuśrī, you should know that the defining characteristic of their benefit consists in their corresponding positive qualities.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="565">
    <s id="565:1">$167Then, the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī further said to the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="565:2">“Blessed One, please explain the meaning of the formula through which bodhisattvas comply with the underlying intention#359 of the profound Dharma expounded by the tathāgatas, the complete meaning of the sūtras, the Vinaya, and the mātṛkās that is not known by those not following you.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="566">
    <s id="566:1">“Mañjuśrī, listen.</s>
    <s id="566:2">I will explain to you the complete meaning of the formula so that bodhisattvas will in this way understand my underlying intention.</s>
    <s id="566:3">Mañjuśrī, the possessors of qualities resulting from affliction and purification#360 are all without movement and without a person.</s>
    <s id="566:4">This is why I taught that all phenomena are in every respect beyond activity.</s>
    <s id="566:5">It is not the case that the possessors of qualities resulting from affliction first became afflicted and will then become purified from these afflictions or that the possessors of qualities resulting from purification have become purified from afflictions they previously acquired.</s>
    <s id="566:6">Thus, foolish ordinary beings rely on views resulting from their latent dispositions, on account of which they wrongly conceive the body afflicted by corruption as the essence of phenomena and persons.</s>
    <s id="566:7">As a consequence,</s>
    <s id="566:8">reifying [the ego through concepts such as] ‘I’ and ‘mine,’ they mistakenly conceive of the following notions:</s>
    <s id="566:9">‘I see,’ ‘I hear,’ ‘I smell,’ ‘I taste,’ ‘I touch,’ ‘I am conscious,’ ‘I eat,’ ‘I do,’ ‘I am afflicted,’ and ‘I am purified.’ [53.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="567">
    <s id="567:1">“Thus, those who understand this fact as it really is abandon the body afflicted by corruption and instead obtain the body that is not a support for any defilement, being pure, free from mental elaborations, unconditioned, and unproduced by intentional action.</s>
    <s id="567:2">Mañjuśrī, you should know that this is the complete meaning of the formula.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="568">
    <s id="568:1">Then, at that moment, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="569">
    <s id="569:1">“The possessors of qualities resulting from affliction and purificationAre all without movement#361 and without a person;</s>
    <s id="569:2">Therefore, I declare them to be without activity,</s>
    <s id="569:3">As they are neither purified nor afflicted, be it in the past or the future.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="570">
    <s id="570:1">“Relying on views resulting from their latent dispositions, On account of which they wrongly conceive the body afflicted by corruption, They reify [the ego through concepts such as] ‘I’ and ‘mine.’</s>
    <s id="570:2">As a consequence, notions arise, such as ‘I see,’ ‘I eat,’ ‘I do,’ ‘I am afflicted,’ and ‘I am purified.’</s>
  </p>
  <p id="571">
    <s id="571:1">“Thus, those who understand this fact as it really is Abandon the body afflicted by corruption And instead will obtain a body that is not a basis for any defilement, Being free from mental elaborations and unconditioned.”#362</s>
  </p>
  <p id="572">
    <s id="572:1">$168“Blessed One, how should we know the defining characteristic of the arising of the tathāgatas’ mind?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="573">
    <s id="573:1">“Mañjuśrī, tathāgatas are not characterized by mind, thought, or cognition.#363 However,</s>
    <s id="573:2">you should know that, similar to an emanation,#364 the tathāgatas’ mind arises in the way of something that is not produced by intentional action.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="574">
    <s id="574:1">“Blessed One, if the truth body of the tathāgatas is not produced at all by intentional action, how then could their mind arise without being produced by intentional action?”#365</s>
  </p>
  <p id="575">
    <s id="575:1">“Mañjuśrī, their mind arises on account of a previous intentional action, namely, the practice of skillful means and wisdom.</s>
    <s id="575:2">Mañjuśrī, it is like this: although awakening from a state of sleep in which there is no thought ensues [spontaneously] without resulting from intentional action, [54.a] one will awaken due to previous intentional actions.</s>
    <s id="575:3">Although the emergence from the absorption in the state of cessation is not produced by intentional action, one will emerge from it merely due to previous intentional actions.</s>
    <s id="575:4">Just as the mind arises from a state of sleep or from the absorption in the state of cessation, you should know that the tathāgatas’ mind also arises due to previous intentional actions such as the practice of skillful means and wisdom.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="576">
    <s id="576:1">“Blessed One, should we say that the mind emanated by tathāgatas exists or not?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="577">
    <s id="577:1">“Mañjuśrī, [their] mind neither exists nor does not exist, because it is causally independent and causally dependent.”#366</s>
  </p>
  <p id="578">
    <s id="578:1">“Blessed One, what is the sphere of activity of the tathāgatas?</s>
    <s id="578:2">What is the domain#367 of the tathāgatas?</s>
    <s id="578:3">Should we consider these two as distinct?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="579">
    <s id="579:1">“Mañjuśrī, the sphere of activity of the tathāgatas consists in the pure buddha realms, the arrayed ornaments of inconceivable and boundless positive qualities common to all tathāgatas.</s>
    <s id="579:2">The domain of the tathāgatas comprises five domains: the domain of the surrounding universe, the domain of beings, the domain of Dharma, the domain of discipline, and the domain of methods of discipline.#368 There is a distinction between the two.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="580">
    <s id="580:1">$169“Blessed One, how should we understand the defining characteristic of the tathāgatas’ complete and perfect awakening, of their turning of the wheel of Dharma, and of their great parinirvāṇa?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="581">
    <s id="581:1">“Mañjuśrī, the tathāgatas are characterized by nonduality.#369</s>
    <s id="581:2">They are neither completely and perfectly awakened nor not completely and perfectly awakened;</s>
    <s id="581:3">[54.b] they neither turn the wheel of Dharma nor do not turn the wheel of Dharma;</s>
    <s id="581:4">they neither [attain] the great parinirvāṇa nor do not attain the great parinirvāṇa.</s>
    <s id="581:5">This is because the truth body is utterly pure and the emanation body constantly manifests.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="582">
    <s id="582:1">“Blessed One, why should we consider that the merit produced by beings on account of seeing, hearing, or serving the tathāgatas’ emanation body arises from the tathāgatas?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="583">
    <s id="583:1">“Mañjuśrī, it is because these activities consist in taking a superior referential object thanks to the tathāgatas, and also because the emanation body is the tathāgatas’ sovereign power.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="584">
    <s id="584:1">“Blessed One, since this does not seem to be produced by intentional action,</s>
    <s id="584:2">why is it that the great light of gnosis manifests in beings solely through the truth body of the tathāgatas and that innumerable emanated reflections also manifest [as the tathāgatas’ emanation body], while this light and its reflections do not manifest from the hearers’ and solitary realizers’ liberation body?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="585">
    <s id="585:1">“Mañjuśrī, while this does not seem to be produced by intentional action, on account of the power of very strong beings and the force of beings’ karma, a great light manifests to beings from water and fire crystals produced from the disks of the moon and sun.</s>
    <s id="585:2">However, it does not manifest from water and fire crystals produced from other sources.</s>
    <s id="585:3">From a precious gem that has been well polished through [intentional] action, reflections corresponding to its engraving manifest [when it is placed before a light source].</s>
    <s id="585:4">However, they do not manifest from another unpolished gem.</s>
    <s id="585:5">Likewise,</s>
    <s id="585:6">because the truth body of the tathāgatas also is established by having been purified through the practice of skillful means and insight focusing on the immeasurable domain of truth, [55.a]</s>
    <s id="585:7">the great light of gnosis manifests in beings, and innumerable emanated reflections arise.</s>
    <s id="585:8">However,</s>
    <s id="585:9">they do not manifest from the hearers’ and solitary realizers’ liberation body.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="586">
    <s id="586:1">$170“Blessed One, you said that, through the force of the tathāgatas’ and bodhisattvas’ sovereign power, one can obtain an excellent body in the realm of desire, such as that of a warrior or a brahman, a body that is like a great sāla tree, or the excellent body of a god residing in the realm of desire, the realm of form, or the realm of the formless.</s>
    <s id="586:2">Blessed One, what was your underlying intention with regard to this?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="587">
    <s id="587:1">“Mañjuśrī, by means of their sovereign power, tathāgatas teach as they are the path and practices through which one obtains all these excellent bodies.</s>
    <s id="587:2">Those accomplishing these path and practices will always obtain all these perfect bodies, while</s>
    <s id="587:3">those who reject or denigrate these path and practices, as well as those who have animosity or resentment toward them, will always obtain all kinds of miserable bodies upon their death.</s>
    <s id="587:4">Mañjuśrī, on account of this skillful means, you should know in this way that, because of the sovereign power of the tathāgatas, one will be reborn in a perfect body as well as in a miserable one.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="588">
    <s id="588:1">$171“Blessed One, in the universes that are impure and pure, what is abundant?</s>
    <s id="588:2">What is rare?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="589">
    <s id="589:1">“Mañjuśrī, in the universes that are impure, [55.b] eight things are abundant and two are rare.</s>
    <s id="589:2">Abundant are (1) followers of traditions other than mine;</s>
    <s id="589:3">(2) suffering beings;</s>
    <s id="589:4">(3) beings who are different in terms of lineages, families, and communities or wealth and poverty;</s>
    <s id="589:5">(4) beings engaging into wrongdoing;</s>
    <s id="589:6">(5) beings who have lost their discipline;</s>
    <s id="589:7">(6) beings in bad destinies;</s>
    <s id="589:8">(7) followers of inferior vehicles;</s>
    <s id="589:9">and (8) bodhisattvas with inferior intentions and practices.</s>
    <s id="589:10">Rare are (1) the actions of bodhisattvas having superior intentions and practices and (2) the manifestation of tathāgatas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="590">
    <s id="590:1">“Mañjuśrī, in the universes that are pure, it is the opposite of this.</s>
    <s id="590:2">You should know that these eight things are rare and these two things abundant.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="591">
    <s id="591:1">Then, the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī asked the Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="591:2">“Blessed One, what is the name of the teaching imparted in this Dharma discourse that unravels the Tathāgata’s intent?</s>
    <s id="591:3">How should I keep it in mind?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="592">
    <s id="592:1">The Blessed One answered,</s>
    <s id="592:2">“Mañjuśrī, this is a teaching of definitive meaning establishing the deeds of the tathāgatas.</s>
    <s id="592:3">Keep it in mind as The Teaching of Definitive Meaning Establishing the Deeds of the Tathāgatas.</s>
    <s id="592:4">As the Blessed One expounded this teaching,</s>
    <s id="592:5">seventy-five thousand bodhisattvas obtained the perfect analytical knowledge of the truth body.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="593">
    <s id="593:1">After the Blessed One had spoken these words,</s>
    <s id="593:2">the prince Mañjuśrī together with the entire retinue of gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="594">
    <s id="594:1">The [tenth chapter of the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī] called “The Chapter Establishing the Positive Qualities [of the Tathāgatas]” of [the sūtra of] the Great Vehicle called “Unraveling the Intent” is concluded.</s>
  </p>
</text>
