<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">The Noble</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">Teaching the Benefits of Generosity</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">$1 [95.b] Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">Thus did I hear at one time.</s>
    <s id="4:2">The Blessed One was dwelling in Śrāvastī in the Jetavana, in the park of Anāthapiṇḍada.</s>
    <s id="4:3">Then the Blessed One said to the monks,</s>
    <s id="4:4">“Monks, the wise give gifts in thirty-seven ways.</s>
    <s id="4:5">What are those thirty-seven?</s>
    <s id="4:6">They are as follows:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$2 “They give gifts with faith in order to rid themselves of stinginess.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">“They give gifts at the right time.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">“They give gifts, in a pure manner, of the three things suitable to be given by the Thus-Gone One.#8</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">$3 “They give gifts respectfully in order to rid themselves of all the faults of mental agitation.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">“They give gifts with their own hands in order to take hold of the essence from the essenceless body.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">“When they have given a gift that does not harm others, the ripening is that they will acquire great generosity.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">$4 “When they have given a gift with exquisite colors, the ripening is that they will acquire a beautiful complexion.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">“When they have given a gift with an exquisite scent, the ripening is that they will acquire the scent of fame.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">“When they have given a gift with an exquisite taste, the ripening is that they will acquire the excellent marks of supreme taste.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">$5 “When they have given a gift that is abundant, the ripening is that they will acquire abundant wealth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">“When they have given a gift that is vast, the ripening is that they will acquire vast wealth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">$6 “When they have given a gift of food, the ripening is that they will acquire the elimination of hunger in all future lives.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">“When they have given a gift of drink, [96.a] the ripening is that they will acquire the elimination of thirst in all future lives.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">“When they have given a gift of clothing, the ripening is that they will acquire a manifold wealth of clothing.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">$7 “When they have given the gift of a dwelling, the ripening is that they will acquire houses with parapets and multiple stories, and they will acquire courtyards, mansions, palaces, gardens, parks, and land.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">“When they have given a gift of bedding, the ripening is that they will acquire a higher caste-status.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">“When they have given the gift of a conveyance, the ripening is that they will acquire the four bases#9 of miraculous power.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">$8 “When they have given a gift of medicine, the ripening is that they will acquire the nirvāṇa that is free from aging and death and is the cessation of sorrow and defilement.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">“When they have given a gift of Dharma, the ripening is that they will acquire the recollection of former lives.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">$9 “When they have given a gift of flowers, the ripening is that they will acquire the flowers that are the branches of awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">“When they have given a gift of garlands, the ripening is that they will acquire the purification of the stains of attachment, aversion, and ignorance.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">$10 “When they have given a gift of incense, the ripening is that they will acquire total freedom from the stench of the defilements.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">“When they have given a gift of a parasol, the ripening is that they will acquire sovereign mastery of the Dharma.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">$11 “When they have given a gift of a bell, the ripening is that they will acquire a pleasing voice.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">“When they have given a gift of cymbals, the ripening is that they will acquire a voice like Brahmā’s.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">$12 “When they have given a gift of a lamp, the ripening is that they will acquire the divine eye, unobscured and pure.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="31">
    <s id="31:1">“When they have given a gift of silk, the ripening is that they will acquire the silken bond of liberation among gods and humans.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="32">
    <s id="32:1">$13 “When they have made an offering of fragrant oil or perfumed bathing water to a stūpa of the Thus-Gone One or an image of the Thus-Gone One, the ripening is that they will acquire the thirty-two marks [96.b] and eighty excellent signs of a great being.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="33">
    <s id="33:1">$14 “When they have given a gift of bathing necessities, the ripening is that in all their future lives they will acquire few illnesses, birth in the highest caste, and great beauty.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="34">
    <s id="34:1">“When they have given a gift of the five essential substances,#10 the ripening is that in all future lives they will acquire great power and irrepressible great joy.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="35">
    <s id="35:1">$15 “When they have given a gift while abiding in loving kindness, the ripening is that they will acquire freedom from ill will.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="36">
    <s id="36:1">“When they have given a gift while abiding in compassion, the ripening is that they will acquire harmlessness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="37">
    <s id="37:1">$16 “When they have given a gift while abiding in joy, the ripening is that they will acquire the ability to bestow fearlessness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="38">
    <s id="38:1">“When they have given a gift while abiding in equanimity, the ripening is that they will rid themselves of sadness.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="39">
    <s id="39:1">$17 “When they have given gifts of various kinds, the ripening is that they will acquire various riches.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="40">
    <s id="40:1">“When they have given a gift while abiding with no expectation of reward, the ripening is that they will acquire unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="41">
    <s id="41:1">$18 “Monks, the wise give gifts in these thirty-seven ways.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="42">
    <s id="42:1">The Blessed One having spoken thus, the monks rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One said.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="43">
    <s id="43:1">$19 This completes the noble “Teaching the Benefits of Generosity.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="44">
    <s id="44:1">Colophon</s>
  </p>
  <p id="45">
    <s id="45:1">{{milestone:{label:c.1,id:UT22084-061-003-60}}}This was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian preceptor Surendrabodhi and the translator-editor Bandé Yeshé Dé.</s>
  </p>
</text>
