<tmx version="1.4b">
	<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="XML aligned text"></header>
<body>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཕགས་པ་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ དྲན་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ གཞག་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The Noble Application of Mindfulness of the Sacred Dharma</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ །_ བྱང་ཆུབ་ སེམས་དཔའ་ དང་ །_ རང་ སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ །_ འཕགས་པ་ ཉན་ཐོས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་ ལོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$1 [F.82.a] Homage to all the buddhas, bodhisattvas, solitary buddhas, and noble hearers!</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་སྐད་ བདག་ གིས་ ཐོས་པ་ དུས་ གཅིག་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$2 Thus did I hear at one time.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཁབ །_ ན་ ལ་ ཏིའི་ གྲོང་ གི་ བྲམ་ཟེ འི་ གྲོང་ ན་ བཞུགས་ སོ །_། དེ འི་ ཚེ་ ན་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏི འི་ བུ །_ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཏུ་ སྔ་དྲོ འི་ དུས་ ཀྱི་ ཚེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཁབ་ ཏུ་ བསོད་སྙོམས་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱིར་ དོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>While the Blessed One was residing in the brahmin quarter of the village of Nālati near Rājagṛha, venerable Śāradvatīputra one morning went to Rājagṛha together with a great gathering of monks to collect alms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཚེ་ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ བསོད་སྙོམས་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱིར་ རྒྱུ་བ་ ན །_ གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ དག་ ག་ལ་བ་ དེར་ དོང་ སྟེ །_ གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ དག་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཏུ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ མགུ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ གཏམ་ བྱས་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As they were out receiving alms, a large group of the monks came across some wandering non-Buddhist practitioners#15 who were on the way to the same destination, and together they engaged in a Dharma discussion to everyone’s delight and appreciation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ དག་ གིས་ དྲིས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$3 During their discussions some of the non-Buddhists asked,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ ཤཱཀྱ་པ་ དག་ ཁྱེད་ཅག་ གི་ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མ་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ མི་དགེ་བ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ སྟོན་ ཅིང་ གཞན་དག་ གི་ ལ་ ཡང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་པ་ བདེན་ ནམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Ah, you Śākya followers, does not your mendicant Gautama teach that misdeeds of the body are unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant, and that one should refrain from rejoicing in them even when they are done by another?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ངེད་ ཅག་ ཀྱང་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ སྟོན་ ཅིང་ གཞན་དག་ གི་ ལ་ ཡང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>We also consider misdeeds of the body to be unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant, and we do not rejoice in them even when done by others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ ཁྱེད་ཅག་ གི་ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མ་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ སྟོན་ ཅིང་ གཞན་དག་ གི་ ལ་ ཡང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Does not your mendicant Gautama teach that misdeeds of speech are unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant, and that one should refrain from rejoicing in them even when done by another?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ངེད་ ཅག་ ཀྱང་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ སྟོན་ ཅིང་ གཞན་དག་ གི་ ལ་ ཡང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>We also consider misdeeds of speech to be unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant, and we do not rejoice in them even when done by others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྱེད་ཅག་ གི་ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མ་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ སྟོན་ ཅིང་ གཞན་དག་ གི་ ལ་ ཡང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Does not your mendicant Gautama teach that misdeeds of the mind are unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant, and that one should refrain from rejoicing in them even when done by another?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ངེད་ ཀྱང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ སྟོན་ ཅིང་ གཞན་དག་ གི་ ལ་ ཡང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>We also consider misdeeds of the mind to be unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant, and we do not rejoice in them even when done by others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྱེད་ ཀྱི་ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མ འི་ ཆོས་ [82b][83a] འདུལ་བ་ དང་ ངེད་ ཀྱི་ ཐ་དད་ དུ་ བྱ་བ་ ཅི་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What difference is there [F.82.b]#16[F.83.a] between your mendicant Gautama’s Dharma-Vinaya and our own?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསམ་པ་ ནི་ ཅི་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What are the ideas?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྱད་པར་ ནི་ ཅི་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What are the distinctive points?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གིས་ ན་ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མ འི་ ཆོས་ འདུལ་བ་ ནི་ ངེད་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ ཁྱད་པར་ དུ་ འཕགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What makes the Dharma-Vinaya of your mendicant Gautama superior to ours?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མ་ དེ་ ནི་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མཁྱེན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ་ ཞེས་ བདག་ཉིད་ སྒྲོགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The mendicant Gautama claims that he is omniscient.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ དག་ གིས་ དེ་སྐད་ དྲིས་པ་ དང་ །_ དགེ་སློང་ གསར་ དུ་ རབ་ཏུ་ བྱུང་བ་ དག་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏི འི་ བུ་ དང་ བྲལ་བ ས་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ ཡང་ མི་ བྱེད་ ལན་ ཡང་ མ་ བཏབ་བོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$4 When faced with these questions by the wandering non-Buddhist practitioners, the group of newly ordained monks neither approved nor responded because the venerable Śāradvatīputra was absent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏི འི་ བུ་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ དག་ བསོད་སྙོམས་ ཀྱི་ བྱ་བ་ བྱས་ ནས་ ན་ ལ་ ཏིའི་ གྲོང་ ག་ལ་བ་ དེར་ དོང་ སྟེ་ ཕྱིན་ ནས དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ ཟས་ ཀྱི་ བྱ་བ་ བྱས་ ནས་ འཁོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Once they had completed their alms round, the large group of monks returned to the town of Nālati where they had their meal and then took their places amid the gathering of monks.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏི འི་ བུ་ ཕྱི་ ཞིག་ ན་ བསོད་སྙོམས་ བླངས་ ཏེ །_ ན་ ལ་ ཏིའི་ གྲོང་ ག་ལ་བ་ དེར་ སོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$5 Later, venerable Śāradvatīputra also returned to the town of Nālati, having received his alms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏི འི་ བུ་ག་ ལ་བ་ དེར་ དོང་ སྟེ་ ཕྱིན་ ནས །_ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ གིས་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏི འི་ བུ་ ལ་ བསྙད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When he arrived, the great gathering of monks went to see him and related to him what had transpired.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏི འི་ བུས་ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ སྨྲས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Venerable Śāradvatīputra said,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ བདག་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཁྱེད་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཁབ་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་སྲང་ དང་ །_ བཞི་མདོ་ དང་ །_ སུམ་མདོ་ གཅིག་ ཏུ་ རིམ་གྱིས་ དོང་བ་ ལས །_ གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ རྣམས་ དང་ ཕྲད་པ ར་ གྱུར་ ན་ ནི་ དེས་ན་ བདག་ གིས་ གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ དེ་དག་ ཆོས་ དང་ འཐུན་ པས་ ཚར་ བཅད་ ཟིན་པ་ ཞིག་ ན །_ ཀྱེ་མ་ བདག་ ཀྱང་ ལམ་སྲང་ དང་ །_ བཞི་མདོ་ དང་ །_ སུམ་མདོ་ གཞན་ ནས་བསོད་ སྙོམས་ ལ་ རྒྱུ་ རྒྱུ་ ནས་ འདིར་ ཕྱིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“If I had been traveling with you, venerable ones, and had met those wandering non-Buddhist practitioners along the Rājagṛha highway, at a crossing, or at a fork in the road, I would have defeated them in accordance with the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ དག་ གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ རྣམས་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ གཏམ་ བྱས་པ འི་ འདྲི་བ འི་ ཚུལ་ དེ་ ནི་ བདག་ གིས་ ཚོར་ ཡང་ མ་ ཚོར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>But unfortunately, I did not witness what transpired in your discussion with those wandering non-Buddhist practitioners.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ དག་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱན་ མངའ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མངོན་སུམ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$6 “Venerable ones, the eyes of the Blessed One perceive everything directly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ དང་ འབྲས་བུ་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ མཁྱེན་པ་ དེ་ ཧ་ཅང་ མི་ རིང་ [83b] བ་ ཞིག་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He understands actions, their effects, and their ripening. [F.83.b] At present he is residing not far from here.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མུ་སྟེགས་ ཀྱི་ ལྟ་བ་ ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཟིལ་ གྱིས་ མནན་ ནས ཉན་ཐོས་ དང་ །_ དགེ་བསྙེན་ དང་ །_ ལྷ་ དང་ མི་ རྣམས་ ལ་ལ ས་ དང་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ འི་ ཆོས་སྟོན་ གྱིས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Subduing all those whose views are extreme, he is teaching the Dharma of actions and their ripening results to hearers and laypeople, gods and humans.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྱེད་ དེ་ ལ་ ཞུས་ ཤིག་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>You must bring what happened before him.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ ལས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྟོན་པ ར་ མཛད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will teach you everything about actions and their ripening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ ལྷ་ དང་ བཅས་པ །_ བདུད་ དང་ བཅས་པ །_ ཚངས་པ་ དང་ བཅས་པ །_ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ དང་ བྲམ་ཟེ ར་ བཅས་པ འི་ སྐྱེ་དགུ་ དག་ གིས་ མ་ མཐོང་བ་ དེ་ ཁྱེད་ ལ་ སྟོན་པ ར་ མཛད་ ཅིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will teach you that which is not seen by any god, māra, Brahmā, mendicant, brahmin, or any other being.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ བདག་ཅག་ གི་ མངོན་སུམ་ དུ་མ་ གྱུར་པ་ དེ་ཡང་ ཁྱོད་ ལ་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ མངོན་སུམ་ དུ་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What we fail to see the Blessed One sees directly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ དང་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ མཁྱེན་པ་ སྟོན་པ ར་ མཛད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With his knowledge of actions and their ripening results, he will teach you.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ག་ལ་བ་ དེར་ དོང་ ངོ་ །_། དེ་ནས་ དགེ་སློང་ དེ་དག་ གིས་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཉིན་ མོ འི་ གནས་པ ས་ བཞུགས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$7 The large group of monks then set off to see the Blessed One and came upon him during his afternoon rest.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རི་རབ་ ལྟར་ རང་ གི་ འོད་ ཀྱི་ དྲ་བ ས་ མངོན་པར་ འབར་བ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He was seated like Mount Sumeru, shining brightly within a sphere of light.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཉིན་ མོ འི་ ཉི་མ་ ལྟར་ སྣང་བས་ རབ་ཏུ་ གསལ་བ །_ མཚན་མོ འི་ ཟླ་བ་ ལྟར་ ཞི་བས་ རབ་ཏུ་ སིམ་པ ར་ མཛད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The Blessed One was resplendent like the sun at noon, peaceful and soothing like the moon at night.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཚོ་ ལྟར་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ གསལ་བ །_ རྒྱ་མཚོ་ ལྟར་ ཟབ་པ །_ རི་རབ་ ལྟར་ མི་གཡོ་བ །_ སེང་གེ་ ལྟར་ དཔའ་བ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He was clear like a lake, deep like the sea, unshakable like Mount Sumeru, and dauntless like a lion.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕ་མ་ ལྟར་ འབྱུང་པོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ སྐྱབས་ སུ་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Like a parent, he was the refuge for all.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐུགས་རྗེ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ བརླན་པ འི་ ཐུགས་ སེམས་ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ གཉེན་ གཅིག་པ ར་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With his mind permeated by great compassion, he was the universal friend of all beings.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱམས་པ་ དང་ །_ སྙིང་རྗེ་ དང་ །_ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཏང་སྙོམས་ ཀྱི་ རྟེན་ དུ་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He was an abode of love, compassion, joy, and equanimity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱང་ཆུབ་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ ཀྱི་ ཆོས་ ཆེན་པོ་ སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་བདུན་ གྱིས་ སྐུ་ བརྒྱན་པ །_ རབ་ཏུ་ དང་བ ས་ ལུས་ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ མིག་ མགུ་བ ར་ མཛད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With his body adorned by the thirty-seven great factors of awakening, its radiance delighted the eyes of all who beheld him.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟླ་བ་ དང་ ཉི་མ འི་ འོད་ ཟིལ་ གྱིས་ གནོན་པ །_ ཤཱཀྱའི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ སྲས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱན་ མངའ་བ །_ སྤྱན་ དྲི་མ་ གསུམ་ དང་ བྲལ་བ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Outshining the light of the sun and the moon, the son of the Śākya king was endowed with universal vision, and his eyes were free of the three stains.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདེན་པ་ གཉིས་ གསུང་བ །_ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ གཉིས་ མཁྱེན་པ །_ བསྒོམ་པ་ གཉིས་ བསྒོམས་ ཤིང་ མངོན་སུམ་ དུ་ མཛད་པ །_ ལམ་ གྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ མངོན་དུ་ མཛད་པ །_ འགོག་པ འི་ དེ་ཉིད་ མཁྱེན་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He had taught the two truths, comprehended the twofold suffering, accomplished and actualized the two cultivations, realized the result of the path, and gained the knowledge of the reality of cessation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁམས་ གསུམ་ མངོན་སུམ་ དུ་ མཛད་པ འི་ སྤྱན་ མངའ་བ །_ ཁམས་ གསུམ་ གཞན་ [84a]167 ཡང་དག་ པར་ སྟོན་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Endowed with eyes that perceive the three realms directly, he revealed the three realms to others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁམས་ བཅྭ་ བརྒྱད་ ཀྱི་ དེ་ཉིད་ མཁྱེན་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.84.a] He had fathomed the real nature of the eighteen elements.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མོས་པ་ ཡིད་ ལ་ བྱེད་པ འི་ དེ་ཉིད་ མཁྱེན་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He knew the essence of the inspired mind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡོན་ཏན་ གྱི་ ཀླུང་ རང་ གི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ བཅྭ་ བརྒྱད་ དག་ དང་ ལྡན་པ །_ སྲིད་པ འི་ འཆིང་བ་ ལས་ རྣམ་པར་ གྲོལ་བ །_ སྟོབས་ བཅུ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ །_ བསྙེངས་པ་ མི་ མངའ་བ་ བཞི ས་ མི་ བསྙེངས་པ །_ ཐུགས་རྗེ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ །_ དྲན་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ གཞག་པ་ གསུམ་ དང་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ ལྡན་པ་ དེ་ མཐོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He was endowed with the eighteen floods of unique qualities, liberated from the bonds of existence, in possession of the ten powers, fearless with the four types of fearlessness, endowed with great compassion, and constantly in possession of the threefold application of mindfulness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ ཆོས་གོས་ ཕྲག་པ་ གཅིག་ ལ་ གཟར་ ནས །_ པུས་མོ་ གཡས་པ འི་ ལྷ་ང་ ས་ ལ་ བཙུགས་ ཏེ །_ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱི་ ཞབས་ ལ་མགོ་ བོས་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་ ནས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$8  The many monks draped their Dharma robes over their shoulders, knelt on their right knees, and bowed their heads to the Blessed One’s feet.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དུལ་བ ས་ མགོ་ བཏུད་ དེ་ ཕྱོགས་ གཅིག་ ཏུ་ འཁོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Calmly and with heads bowed, they then stood to one side.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ དགེ་སློང་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ གིས་ དགེ་སློང་ གཅིག་ཅིག་ བསྒོ་བ་ དང་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ག་ལ་བ་ དེར་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ ཕྱིན་ ནས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A monk who had been appointed by the large gathering now stepped forth and approached the Blessed One.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱི་ ཞབས་ ལ་མགོ་ བོས་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When he was very close to the Blessed One, he bowed his head to his feet.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_། བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ འདིར་ བདག་ སྔ་དྲོ འི་ དུས་ སུ་ ལྷུང་བཟེད་ དང་ ཆོས་གོས་ འཚལ་ ནས །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཁབ་ ཏུ་ བསོད་སྙོམས་ ལ་ མཆི་ མཆི་ ན་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He then respectfully conveyed to the Blessed One how, in the morning, the monks had dressed in their Dharma robes, picked up their alms bowls, and gone to Rājagṛha to receive alms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ རྣམས་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ དང་ །_ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ སྔོན་ དུ་ འགྲོ་བ འི་ གཏམ་འདྲི་བ འི་ བར་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ ཏེ །_ དེ་དག་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He recounted how they had met the wandering non-Buddhist practitioners, and how the latter had begun to discuss physical, verbal, and mental misdeeds, up to the questions they had asked.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ དེ འི་ ཚེ་ དགེ་སློང་ དེ་དག་ དང་ ན་ ལ་ ཏིའི་ གྲོང་ གི་ བྲམ་ཟེ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$9  When the monk had finished his account, the Blessed One spoke the following words to the monks, as well as to the brahmins of Nālati, and the others:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་སློང་ དག་ ཁྱེད་ཅག་ ལ་ ཆོས་ བཤད་པ ར་ བྱ་བ་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ དྲན་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ གཞག་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་ གྲངས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Monks, I shall explain for you a teaching of the Dharma that is known as Mindfulness of the Sacred Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐོག་མ ར་ དགེ་བ །_ བར་ དུ་ དགེ་བ །_ ཐ་མ ར་ དགེ་བ །_ དོན་ བཟང་པོ །_ ཚིག་འབྲུ་ བཟང་པོ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Auspicious in the beginning, the middle, and the end, this teaching is of profound meaning and conveyed in excellent words.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ འདྲེས་པ །_ ཡོངས་སུ་ རྫོགས་པ །_ ཡོངས་སུ་ དག་པ །_ ཡོངས་སུ་ བྱང་བ །_ ཚངས་པ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ རབ་ཏུ་ བསྟན་པ ར་ བྱས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Unique, complete, and pure, it explains the perfect training and pure conduct.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལེགས་པ ར་ རབ་ཏུ་ ཉོན་ ལ་ [84b] ཡིད་ ལ་ ཟུང་ ཤིག་ དང་ བཤད་པ ར་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Listen keenly and [F.84.b] keep in mind what I say. I shall explain this for you.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ འཚལ་ ལོ་ ཞེས་ གསོལ་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One,” replied the monks, “we shall do just as you instruct.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་སློང་ དེ་དག་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ ཉན་པ་ དང་ །_ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ དེ་དག་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$10 As the monks listened, the Blessed One now spoke:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་སློང་ དག་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ དྲན་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ གཞག་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་ གྲངས་ དེ་ གང་ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Monks, you may wonder what is meant by the Dharma teaching known as Mindfulness of the Sacred Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཡང་ ཆོས་ཉིད་ དུ །_ ཆོས་མ་ ཡིན་པ་ ལ་ ཡང་ ཆོས་མ་ ཡིན་པ་ ཉིད་ དུ་ མཐོང་བ་ དེ་ དྲན་པ་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ གནས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ འདི་ ལ་ ཐེ་ཚོམ་ ཡང་ མི་ སྐྱེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Well, it is to remain constantly mindful of seeing Dharma as Dharma and non-Dharma as non-Dharma, while not having any doubts.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཆོས་ ཉན་པ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ ཡང་ འགྱུར །_ རྒན་རབས་ ལ་ ཡང་ རིམ་གྲོ་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is to delight in listening to the Dharma, and to venerate one’s elders.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ དང་ །_ ངག་གི་ལས་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ གསུམ་ གྱི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ དང་ །_ འཆི་བ་ དང་ །_ སྐྱེ་བ འི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཤེས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This yields knowledge of the effects of the karmic actions of body, speech, and mind, and of the ripening of those actions in terms of death and rebirth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྟ་བ་ མ་ ལོག་པ་ ཡིན་ ཞིང་ གཞན་ གྱིས་ ཁ་ མི་ ཕྱིན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One’s view thereby becomes unmistaken and impervious to being swayed by others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་སློང་ དག་ དེ་ ལ་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ སྟེ །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ དང་ །_ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ དང་ །_ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$11 “Monks, there are three misdeeds of the body: killing, stealing, and sexual misconduct.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What, then, is killing?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ཅན་ ཕ་རོལ་ ལ་ སེམས་ཅན་ དུ་ འདུ་ཤེས་ ཤིང་ བསམས་ བཞིན་ དུ་ སྲོག་ཆགས་ བསད་ དེ་ སྲོག་ དང་ བྲལ་བ ར་ བྱས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To take a life is to recognize another sentient being as a sentient being and knowingly slay it.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ སྟེ །_ ཆེན་པོ་ དང་ །_ འབྲིང་ དང་ །_ ཐ་མ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such an act may be of a great, intermediate, or minor kind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ཆེན་པོ་ ནི་ དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ ལ་སོགས་ པ་ བསད་པ་ སྟེ་ མནར་མེད་ པར་ འགྲོ་བ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Great killing is the murder of a worthy one or the like. Such acts lead to the Hell of Ultimate Torment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འབྲིང་ ནི་ ལམ་ ལ་ གནས་པ་ བསད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Intermediate killing occurs when one murders someone on the path.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐ་མ་ ནི་ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ འཆལ་པ་ སྤྱད་པ་ བསད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Minor killing is to kill an animal or someone of degenerate moral conduct.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ སྟེ །_ འདས་པ་ དང་ །_ མ་འོངས་པ་ དང་ །_ ད་ལྟ ར་ བྱུང་བ འིའོ །_། ཡང་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ སྟེ །_ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཀྱིས་ བྱས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཞེ་སྡང་ གིས་ བྱས་པ་ དང་ །_ གཏི་མུག་ གིས་ བྱས་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$12 “An act of killing can also be categorized with respect to the past, future, or present, or in terms of whether that act is carried out due to desire, anger, or delusion.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཀྱིས་ བྱས་པ་ ནི་ རི་ དག ས་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Of these latter, killing out of desire occurs in hunting deer and other game.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཞེ་སྡང་ གིས་ བྱས་པ་ ནི་ སྦྲུལ་ དང་ ནེའུ་ལེ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Killing out of hatred occurs in killing a snake, a mongoose, or the like.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཏི་མུག་ གིས་ བྱས་པ་ ནི་ མཆོད་སྦྱིན་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Killing due to delusion occurs in sacrificial killings and the like.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་ རྣམ་པ་ [85a] གསུམ་ སྟེ །_ རང་ གིས་ བྱས་པ་ དང་ །_ གཞན་ གྱིས་ བཅོལ་བ་ དང་ །_ གཉི་ག ས་ བྱས་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Killing can likewise be categorized in terms of [F.85.a] acts done by oneself, acts ordered by others, and acts done both by oneself and on the order of others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱུ་ལྔ ས་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བྱས་ ཀྱང་ ཁ་ན་མ་ཐོ་ བས་ གོས་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$13 “In five cases killing will not incur any stain of evil:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལམ་ དུ་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ ཞུགས་པ་ མི་ ཤེས་པ ས་ སྲོག་ཆགས་ ཕྲ་མོ་ དང་ །_ གྲོག་སྦུར་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ སྲོག་ དང་ བྲལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>unwittingly killing insects, ants, and so forth that happen to be in one’s a path;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ལ་ མཚོན་ཆ་ གཟས་པ་ ལས་ བསམ་པ་ དང་ མི་ ལྡན་པ ར་ གཞན་ ལ་ ཕོག་ སྟེ དེ་ སྲོག་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>unintentionally striking and killing someone with a weapon;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ནད་པ་ ལ་སྨན་པ་ ཕན་པ ར་ འདོད་པ ས་ ཉེས་པ ར་ མ་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_ སྨན་ བྱིན་པ་ ལས་ དེ་ ཤི་བ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>dispensing the wrong type of medicine to a sick person, thereby accidently causing the person’s death while trying to help;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་མ ས་ བུ་ གདུལ་བ ར་ བྱ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ བརྡེག་པ་ ལས་ དེ་ སྲོག་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>as a mother, causing the death of one’s child by disciplinary beating;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ འབར་བ འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྲོག་ཆགས་ མི་ འདོད་ བཞིན་ དུ་ ལྷུང་བ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>and unintentionally causing living beings to die due to their falling into fire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱུ་ རྣམ་པ་ དེ་ ལྔས་ སྲོག་ བཅད་པ ར་ གྱུར་ ཀྱང་ གོས་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When killing occurs under these five circumstances there will not be any stain.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ སྟེ །_ གཞན་ ལ་ བསྒོ་བ་ དང་ །_ བདག་ཉིད་ བྱེད་པ་ དང་ །_ གཉི་ག ས་ བྱེད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Further, killing may take place, again in three ways, by contracting others to do it, by performing the deed oneself, or by both of these methods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ རྫོགས་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$14 “What is understood by a complete act of stealing?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས །_ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A spiritual practitioner, who observes and adheres to the Dharma, may understand this through having received teachings or having seen it to be the case by means of the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕ་རོལ་ གྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བཟུང་བ་ ལ་ བདག་ གིར་ བྱ་བ འི་ བསམ་པ ས་ རྐུ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ རྫོགས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A complete act of stealing is to rob something that belongs to another with the intention of making it one’s own.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$15 “Which acts of this kind will have a minor effect?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཆད་པ ས་ ཉེན་པ་ དང་ །_ བླ་མ འི་ དོན་ དང་ །_ ཕ་མ་ ནད་པ་ དང་ །_ རང་ སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ །_ དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ དང་ །_ ཕྱིར་ མི་ འོང་བ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱུན་ དུ་ ཞུགས་པ་ ལ་སོགས་ པ་ དང་ །_ ནད་པ་ དང་ །_ ལྟོགས་པ་ དེ་དག་ གི་ དོན་ དུ་མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ བླངས་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one takes what was not given due to compliance with a royal decree; or if one takes what was not given for the sake of one’s guru, one’s sick parents, a solitary buddha, a worthy one, a non-returner, a stream enterer, or the like;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ འི་ སྡོམ་པ་ མ་ བླངས་པ ས་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>or if one does so for the sake of the sick or the hungry.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཆུང་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In such cases there will be a minor ripening of the act.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ནི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ བྱས་ ནས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such cases of taking what was not given, when performed by someone who has not taken vows to take what was not given, also involve only a minor ripening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ ཀྱིས་ འཆགས་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ འགྱོད་ ལ་ ཕྱིར་ཞིང་ མི་ བྱེད །_ ཕ་རོལ་ ཡང་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ལས་ ཕྱིར་ ཟློག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ སྡོམ་པ འི་ ལུང་ ཡང་ [85b] འབོགས་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ ལམ་ ལ་ ཡང་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ སྤོང་བ་ དག་ ལ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Minor effects will also arise when one takes what was not given, but then mentally confesses, feels remorse, and abstains in the future, and when one prevents others from taking what was not given, confers vows upon them, [F.85.b] establishes them upon the path, and establishes them in the practice of abstaining from taking what was not given.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ དང་ །_ ལས་ ཀྱི་ མཇུག་ མི་ བྱེད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Similarly, only minor effects occur when the preparations, act, or conclusion is incomplete.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$16 “What are the preparations for stealing?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་པོ ས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ལ་ གཡོ་སྒྱུ་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ གསང་ ཐབས་ སུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ དང་ །_ འཇལ་ ལུགས་ ལ་ གཡོ་ བྱེད་པ་ དང་ །_ མི་རིགས་པ འི་ ལས་ ལྷག་པ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ འདི་དག་ ནི་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They involve deceiving the victim, giving secret instructions, engaging in fraud, or some other form of inappropriate activity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What is the act itself?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གི་ ཚེ་ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བཟུང་བ འི་ རྫས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པ་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ལ ས་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is to take the possessions of another without them being given.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ ཀྱི་ མཇུག་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What is the act’s conclusion?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ བྱས་ ནས་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་ ཏེ །_ |#| རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ འཆབ་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ |#| ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ གཞན་མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ མཇུག་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This consists in rejoicing in, becoming habituated to, and increasing the act; |#| rejoicing in the act while keeping it hidden; |#| and making other disciplined individuals engage in such an act.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣམ་པ་ འདི་ གསུམ་ གྱིས་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ དང་ །_ མཇུག་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ མ་ བྱིན་པ་ ལེན་པ འི་ ཆད་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ ངེས་པ་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When a misdeed of stealing lacks any of these three aspects, which include preparations and conclusion, its effect will be minor and experienced in indeterminate ways.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$17 “What is sexual misconduct?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ ས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is understood by a spiritual practitioner who observes phenomena.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ན་ རང་ གི་ ཆུང་མ འམ་ གཞན་ གྱི་ ཆུང་མ་ དག་ གི་ སྐྱེ་གནས་ མ་ཡིན་པ ར་ འཇུག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ གཞན་ བྱེད་པ་ ལ་ ཡང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ མི་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡང་ ཐབས་ ཀྱིས་ བྱེད་ དུ་ འཇུག་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such a person will see that sexual misconduct occurs when one penetrates one’s own wife, or another man’s wife, through an opening other than the vagina, or when one rejoices in others performing such an act, or when one makes others engage in it even while refraining from doing so oneself.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$18 “In which cases will the effects of sexual misconduct be minor?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ བྱས་ ནས་ འགྱོད་ ཅིང་ འཆགས་ ཏེ །_ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད །_ གཞན་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཡང་ཕྱི ར་ ཟློག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ ལམ་ ལ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ དང་ །_ ལས་ ཀྱི་ མཇུག་ དང་ བྲལ་བ འི་ སེམས་ ཡིན་ ཞིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When the act is regretted and confessed, when one does not rejoice in it, when one discourages others from engaging in sexual misconduct and establishes them on the path, and when the preparation or conclusion is incomplete.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ དང་ [86a] ལྡན་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ ནི་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ མ་ངེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When such factors of intention and discipline are present [F.86.a] the effects of an act of sexual misconduct will be minor and their experience indeterminate.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པོ་ དེ་དག་ ནི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ་ དང་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཞན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When the three misdeeds of the body are of this kind their effects are lesser and weak.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ ནི་ ང འི་ ཉན་ཐོས་ སམ་ ང་ ལས་ ཐོས་ ནས་ ལས་ དང་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཤེས་ ཤིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$19 “Only those who hear these points from my hearers or from myself will understand the whole matter of karmic actions and their ripening effects.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ གྱིས་ ཁ་ དྲང་ དུ་ མི་ རུང་བ་ གཞན་ ལ་ རག་ མ་ལ ས་པ་ མ་གཏོགས་ པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, they will not be swayed by the accounts of others, but become independent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ རྣམས་ སམ །_ ལྷ་ དང་ བཅས་པ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ནམ །_ བདུད་ དང་ བཅས་པ འམ །_ ཚངས་པ་ དང་ བཅས་པ འམ །_ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ དང་ བྲམ་ཟེ ར་ བཅས་པ འི་ སྐྱེ་དགུ འམ །_ ལྷ་ དང་ །_ མི་ དང་ །_ ལྷ་མ་ ཡིན་ དུ་ བཅས་པ ས་ རྟོགས་པ འི་ ཡུལ་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These points are not realized by wandering non-Buddhist practitioners. Neither are they realized by the world with its gods; nor by the māras; nor by Brahmā, mendicants, and brahmins; nor by gods, humans, and asuras.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ ལྕི་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$20 “What are the misdeeds of speech?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཆོས་ དང་ལ ས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཤེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ བཞི་ ལ་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ བརྫུན་ དང་ །_ ཕྲ་མ་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ དང་ བཞི འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who understand phenomena, as well as karmic actions and their maturation, will know that there are four misdeeds of speech: lying, divisive talk, harsh words, and chatter.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ བརྫུན་ གང་ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$21 “What is lying?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདག་ཉིད་ ལ་ བདག་ཉིད་ སླུ་ ཞིང་ གཞན་ ཡང་ སླུ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Lying is to deceive oneself and others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྨྲས་པ འི་ ཚེ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འམ །_ བློན་པོ འི་ མངོན་སུམ་ དུ་ གཞན་དག་ ལ་ གནོད་པ འམ །_ འཕྲོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ལོག་པ ས་ བསྐྱེད་པ འི་ བརྫུན་ གྱི་ སྐྱོན་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇུག་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ རྫོགས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, when one expresses false complaints before a king or minister and so unjustly brings harm or ruin upon others, that constitutes a complete verbal misdeed of lying.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such acts lead sentient beings to experience life in hell.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ ཕྲ་མ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ནི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$22 “What is the misdeed of speech known as divisive talk?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དོན་ གཅིག་ ལ་ འཐུན་ པར་ ཞུགས་པ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ དབྱེན་ བྱ་བ འི་ བསམ་པ ས་ ཚིག་ རྗོད་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ ཕྲ་མ འི་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If, with the intention to sow discord, one speaks to a group that is otherwise in agreement on a certain subject, that is a verbal misdeed of divisive talk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྲ་མ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཆུང་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How can the effects of divisive talk be lessened?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདག་ གཏི་མུག་ གིས་ ངན་པ་ བྱས་ སོ་ ཞེས་ འཆགས་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By confession, thinking, ‘In my delusion I have done wrong!’;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཕྲ་མ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ ཟློག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>by hindering those who delight in sowing discord and by establishing them on the path;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལམ་ ལ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ དང་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ མཇུག་ མི་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>or by refraining from the act’s preparations or conclusion.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$23 “What are the preparations for such an act?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ ཕྲ་མ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ རྒྱགས་པ་ ལ་ [86b] མངོན་པར་ ཞུགས་པ འི་ ཚིག་ གཞན་ དུ་ བཏགས་ ནས་ གཞན་ ལ་ སྨྲ་བ་ འདི་ ནི་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.86.b] They consist in speaking to others out of a delight in sowing discord and the affliction of haughtiness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྲ་མ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ དང་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ རབ་ཏུ་ ལྡན་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What is the course of action in terms of divisive talk?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ སྡང་བ འི་ སེམས་ ཀྱིས་ ཡང་ དང་ ཡང་ དུ་ གཞན་ འབྱེད་ ལ་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་ ཞིང་ ཀུན་དགའ་ བར་ བྱེད་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ ཕྲ་མ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ དང་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྡན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is to repeatedly rejoice and delight in disharmony based on an aggressive mind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ ཀྱི་ མཇུག་ དང་ བཅས་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When is the conclusion of such an act complete?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ ཕྲ་མ་ བྱས་ ནས་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is complete when one rejoices in a performed act of divisive talk;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྱིར་ཞིང་ བྱེད་ བྱེད་པ་ ལ་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>when one anticipates further, repeated engagements in such acts with excitement and pleasure;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཉིད་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ ངང་ཚུལ་ གཞན་ དུ་ མི་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>and when one does not wish to rectify this inclination.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྡང་བ འི་ སེམས་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This mental state is one of aggression.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་དག་ གིས་ བཙལ་ ཅིང་ ཡིད་ཆེས་པ འི་ གནས་ སུ་ མི་འགྱུར་བ་ ཡིན །_ སྨོད་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When examined by others, one will be deemed untrustworthy and scorned.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ངོ་ཚ་ བར་མི་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ ཁྲེལ་མེད་ ལ་ བདག་ཉིད་ ལ་ སྨོད་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such an act exposes one as being shameless and without any sense of embarrassment or self-criticism.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ཕྲ་མ འི་ ཆད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is the verbal misdeed of divisive talk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ འི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$24 “What is the misdeed of harsh words?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཆོས་ དང་ །_ ལས་ དང་ ཀུན་འབྱུང་བ་ མཐོང་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ ས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who see phenomena, karmic actions, and their origin will understand this by means of knowledge derived from hearing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ ས་ བདག་ གདུང་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ རྣ་བ ར་ ཐོས་ ལ་ གླགས་ སྐྱེད་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In this regard, harsh words bring harm to oneself and impact others by creating the occasion for them to hear unpleasant words.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ གཞན་ ལ་ གནས་ ཏེ །_ མཁྱུད་པ་ དང་ །_ འཆགས་པ་ དང་ །_ དགོད་པ་ དང་ །_ ཁྲོ་བ འི་ བསམ་པ ས་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ དུ་མ་ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་མ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such acts ripen in various ways, depending on whether they were concealed or confessed, or whether they were done in a spirit of jest or malice.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ ནི་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ འི་ ཚོར་བ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ འཆགས་པ ས་ ནི་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ མ་ངེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The severe forms of harsh words cause the experience of life in hell, yet through confession the resultant experience can become indeterminate.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་དག་ ནི་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ གསུམ་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is the third verbal misdeed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ ཀྱི་ ཉེར་བསྡོགས་ དང་ །_ ལས་ ཀྱི་ མཇུག་ དང་ །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྡན་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ནི་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The preparations, conclusion, and full possession are as described above.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ བཞི་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$25 “What is the fourth verbal misdeed?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ལས་ དང་ ཆོས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ འི་ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་མ་ ཤེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ སྔ་ཕྱི་ འབྲེལ་བ་ མེད་པ འི་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ སྔ་མ་ དང་ ཕྱི་མ ར་ མི་ སྦྱོར་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who comprehend numerous forms of karmic action, phenomena, and ripening recognize chatter to be pointless and unrelated babble.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ མ་ ངེས་ ཤིང་ཁ་ ན་མ་ ཐོ་བ་ མི་ མང་བ་ ཡིན་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The resultant experiences are indeterminate, and the act involves less evil.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ངག་ གི་ [87a] ཆད་པ་ བཞི་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.87.a] Such is the fourth verbal misdeed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན །_ རྣམ་པ་ ནི་ དུ་ཞིག་ ཡོད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$26 “What are mental misdeeds, and how many of them are there?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ལས་ དང་ ཆོས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ལ་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ ས་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who consider karmic action, phenomena, and ripening know by means of knowledge derived from hearing that there are three mental misdeeds.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ བརྣབ་སེམས་ ནི་ གཞན་ གྱི་ འབྱོར་པ་ མཐོང་ ནས་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ སེམས་ ཀྱིས་ འདོད་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ རྫས་ འདི་ ནི་ བདག་ གིར་ བྱ འོ་ སྙམ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They understand that covetousness occurs when one sees the possessions of others, and that gives rise to thinking, craving, and the idea that ‘those things should be mine.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བརྣབ་སེམས་ འདི་ ནི་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ དང་པོ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such covetousness is the first among the mental misdeeds.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ནི་ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ མཐོང་ ནས་ ཡིད་ རབ་ཏུ་ སྡང་བ་ གནོད་སེམས་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$27 “There is also ill will, which is to give rise to a hostile and aggressive state of mind when seeing others’ agreeable circumstances.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ གཉིས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is the second mental misdeed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ གསུམ་པ་ ནི་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ ས་ ཕྱིན་ ཅི་ ལོག་ ཏུ་ མཐོང་བ་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ འི་ ཆད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$28 “The third mental misdeed is wrong view, a mistaken perception of things.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ རྣམ་པ་ གཉིས་ ཏེ །_ ཡོད་པ་ འཇིག་པ་ དང་ །_ ལོག་པ ར་ ཤེས་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This has two aspects: denying what is, and misunderstanding.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ཡོད་པ་ འཇིག་པ་ ནི་ འདི་ལྟར་ སྦྱིན་པ་ མེད །_ སྦྱིན་སྲེག་ མེད །_ མཆོད་སྦྱིན་ མེད །_ ལེགས་པ ར་ བྱས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཉེས་པ ར་ བྱས་པ་ དག་ གི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ མེད་ དོ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ རྒྱ་ ཆེ ར་ སྦྱར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Denying what is means to deny the relevance of such things as generosity, fire offerings, and sacrificial worship, or that good and bad deeds will ripen into karmic consequences.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོག་པ ར་ ཤེས་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ནི །_ བདེ་བ་ དང་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ ལྷ ས་ བྱས་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ ས་ ནི་ མ་ བྱས་ སོ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Misunderstanding is the belief that happiness and suffering are bestowed by gods and not the result of karmic action.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ རྣམ་པ་ གཉིས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is the second form of wrong view.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ན་ ལུས་ དང་ ངག་ དང་ ཡིད་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ གྱི་ ཆད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ བཅུ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$29 “If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases these ten misdeeds that pertain to body, speech, and mind, their consequences may become certain as they ripen in the present life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འདི་ཉིད་ ལ་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ ངེས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཤི་ ནས་ གཞན་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ དེ འི་ རྒྱུ་ཅན་ གྱི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དང་ རྒྱུ་ འཐུན་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་པ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདིར་ སྐྱེས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The karmic effects may also be experienced in accordance with the causal actions following one’s death and rebirth into another realm, or they may be experienced in various ways following rebirth in this realm.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་ དེ་དག་ ཅི་འདྲ་ བར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How is that?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ལས་ དང་ ཆོས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ལ་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A spiritual practitioner who considers karmic action, phenomena, and ripening will understand this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ ཀྱི་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ དང་པོ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$30 “Killing is the first of the misdeeds of the body.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་ [87b] བ་ དང་ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ ཡི་དགས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases the amount of killing, one will take birth in the realms of hell beings, [F.87.b] animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ དག་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ དེ་ ཚེ་ ཐུང་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, one will have a short life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ རྔོན་པ་ ལྟ་བུ་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ ས་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བྱས་ ན །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བྱས་པ་ དེ་ ཉམས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If, for example, one is a hunter who has killed due to attachment, one will suffer a downfall because of that.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ རི་ དག ས་ དང་ །_ ཕག་ དང་ །_ སྲེག་པ་ དང་ །_ ཁྱིམ་བྱ་ དང་ །_ གོང་མ་སྲེག་ དང་ །_ ཉ་ ལ་སོགས་ པར་ གྱུར་པ་ ན །_ རྒྱ འམ་ མཆིལ་ བས་ གསོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Having become a deer, pig, partridge, chicken, pheasant, fish, or the like, one will be killed by a trap or a hook.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་བ་ ན་ ལས་ དེ་ལྟ་ བུ འི་ རྒྱུས་ འབྲེལ་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the causal relationships associated with the acts of killing in cyclic existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ཡང་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ དེ་ ཚེ་ ཐུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, one’s life will be short.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཁས་པ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_ མཚོན་ མང་པོ ས་ འཁྲུག་པ འི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ མྱུར་བ་ ཉིད་ དུ་ གསོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will not be born in a land of wise people and instead one’s birthplace will be plagued by many armed conflicts. There, one will soon be killed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཆུང་ངུ་ དང་ འབྲིང་ དང་ ཆེན་པོ འི་ ཚིགས་ སུ་ བཅད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Here is a verse on lesser, intermediate, and severe killing:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁ་ཅིག་ མངལ་ དང་ དེ་བཞིན་ གཞན །_། བཙས་པ འི་ ཁྱིམ་ དང་ གཞན་དག་ ནི །_། གོག་པ་ ཙམ་ དང་ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ །_། གཞན་དག་ ཡོངས་སུ་ རྒྱུག་ ན་ འཆི །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$31 “Some die in the womb, Others at childbirth, Others while only being able to crawl, And still others who have already learned to walk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ནི་ ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ ཚེ་ ལ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ ས་ དབང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ ལས་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$32 “Such is the ripening of the act of killing in terms of the present life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པོ་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ མྱོང་བ་ དང་ ཚེ་ འདི་ དང་ རྒྱུ་ འཐུན་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$33  “Resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing acts of stealing yields three forms of ripening: the experience of life in hell, present life consequences, and concordant effects in future lives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What are these like?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ལས་ དང་ ཆོས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ལ་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ ས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who consider karmic action, phenomena, and ripening perceive this based on the knowledge derived from hearing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases acts of stealing, one will take birth in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ དབུལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, one will be destitute.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ བསྒྲུབས་པ་ གང་དག་ ཡོད་པ་ དེ་དག་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཆད་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆུ་ དང་ །_ མེ་ དང་ །_ མཚོན་ དང་ །_ ཆོམ་རྐུན་ གྱི་ འཇིགས་པ་ དག་ གིས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Whatever enjoyable things one might have will be taken by punitive legislation, water, fire, weapons, robbers, or thieves.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསགས་ བསགས་པ་ དག་ ཆུད་ ཟ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ ནམས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་བ ར་ མི་ [88a] འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, whatever one may have gathered will be wasted and what is obtained will not yield any enjoyment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ འི་ ཆད་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.88.a] These are the three effects of stealing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ནང་ གི་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$34  “What are the three effects of resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing acts of sexual misconduct?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ལས་ དང་ ཆོས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ལ་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who observe karmic action, phenomena, and ripening will perceive the following either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases acts of sexual misconduct, one will take birth in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མིར་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ རྒྱུ་ འཐུན་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ ས་ དེ འི་ ཆུང་མ་ གུས་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར །_ མཚན་གཉིས་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་ པས་ བརྙས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one is born as a human, the causally concordant effect will be such that one’s spouse is disrespectful, one becomes a hermaphrodite, or one is held in contempt by the world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པ འི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$35  “Such are the threefold effects of the ripening of the three physical misdeeds.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ མུ་སྟེགས་ ཅན་ སྤྱོད་པ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྒྱུ་བ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ ནས་ རྒྱས་པ ར་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ འི་ བར་ ནི་ དེ་ལྟ་ བུ་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>However, the wandering non-Buddhist practitioners do not accept any of this, from the physical misdeeds up to and including their ripening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Why is that?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཏི་མུག་ དང་ འགྲོགས་པ་ བསྒོམས་པ འི་ སེམས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ གཞན་ གྱིས་ ནི་ ང འི་ ལས་ དང་ ཆོས་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ འི་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ འདི་ མི་ མཐོང་ གི _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Because those who develop and cultivate ignorance do not perceive my teaching on karmic action, phenomena, and ripening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟར་ ང འི་ ཉན་ཐོས་ དང་ །_ ང འི་ རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ དག་ གིས་ རྗེས་སུ་ མཐོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>However, my hearers and my spiritual practitioners do see this.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཚིག་ དང་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$36  “Furthermore, what is meant by a spoken or verbal misdeed?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣམ་པ་ ནི་ དུ་ཡོད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What forms does it assume?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ ས་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ བཞི་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ བརྫུན་ དང་ །_ ཕྲ་མ་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who abide by the observation of phenomena perceive four verbal misdeeds by means of knowledge derived from hearing: lying, divisive talk, harsh words, and chatter.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ བརྫུན་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ ཀྱི་ སྐྱེ་གནས་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases acts of lying one will take birth in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ །_ སེམས་ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱིས་ ཚིག་ གཟུང་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, others will disregard what one has to say.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཕོ་བྲང་ འཁོར་ དང་ ཁྱིམ་བདག་ གི་ འཁོར་ [88b] དང་ རྒྱལ་རིགས་ ཀྱི་ འཁོར་ དང་ རང་ གི་ བུ་ དང་ ཆུང་མ ས་ ཀྱང་ ཚིག་ གཟུང་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nobody will listen, whether in royal courts, among householders, [F.88.b] amid the nobility, or even in the company of one’s own children and spouse.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཁ་ ནས་ དྲི་ མནམ་པ་ འབྱུང་ །_ སོ་ དང་ཁ་ དང་ མདོག་ དང་ པགས་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One’s breath will carry a foul odor, and one’s teeth, mouth, complexion, and skin will be unpleasant to behold.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ ཀྱང་ ལོག་པ འི་ མངོན་པར་ སྤྱོད་པ ས་ མངོན་པར་ སྦྱོར་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ རྟག་ ཏུ་ འཇིགས་ པར་ ཡང་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Mistreated by all worldly individuals, one will live in perpetual fear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ མཛའ་བཤེས་ དང་ །_ གཉེན་ དང་ །_ སྐྱེ་བོ་ སྙིང་ དུ་ སྡུག་པ་ དག་ བསྟེན་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Family, friends, and loved ones will be unreliable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱེད་པ་ བརྩམས་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འབྲས་བུ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར །_ དོན་མེད་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>All projects one undertakes will come to naught, and one will instead be driven to pursue all sorts of meaningless activities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ བརྫུན་ གྱི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ མི་འདོད་པ་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant karmic effects of the act of lying.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ངག་ གི་ ཆད་པ་ གཉིས་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$37  “What are the effects of resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing the second verbal misdeed?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe phenomena perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྲ་མ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases divisive talk one will take birth in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ དེ་ ལྐུགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_ འོན་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_ དེ འི་ ཁ་ ནས་ དྲི་ མནམ་པ་ འབྱུང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among human beings, sharing in their good fortune, one may be dumb, deaf, or suffer from bad breath.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཚིག་ ལ་ སུ་ ཡང་ ཡིད་ མི་ ཆེས་ ཤིང་ དེ་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ གྱི་ བཞད་གད་ པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nobody will trust one’s words and one will become the laughingstock of all.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གདོང་ གི་ མདོག་ མི་ སྡུག་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One’s facial complexion will be unattractive.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནས་ གཅིག་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will be unable to feel at ease at any single location.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ གཡོ་ བར་ འགྱུར །_ སེམས་ འཐས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One’s mind will be restless yet rigid.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ཕྲ་མ འི་ ཆད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the misdeed of divisive talk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$38  “What are the effects of resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing harsh words?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These are understood either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases harsh words, one will take birth in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ སུ་ ལས་ ཀྱང་ དབུགས་ ཕྱིན་པ་ མི་ འཐོབ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, one will not be consoled by anyone.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ ཀྱང་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ མངོན་ [89a] པར་ གཙེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ སུ ས་ ཀྱང་ དབུགས་ འབྱིན་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Constantly the target of everyone’s abuse, [F.89.a] one will not be offered relief by anyone.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུ་ དང་ ཆུང་མ་ ལས་ དགའ་བ འི་ ཚིག་ གཅིག་ ཙམ་ ཡང་ མི་ འཐོབ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Not a single word of appreciation will come from one’s own children or spouse.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རི་ དག ས་ ལྟར་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ འཇིགས་ པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Like a deer, one will have to live in fear of all humans.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ འི་ བཤེས་གཉེན་ དང་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར །_ སྡིག་པ འི་ གྲོགས་པོ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Without access to spiritual teachers, one will fall in with bad company.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པོ་ འདི་ ནི་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These three are the effects of harsh words.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$39  “What is it like to resort to, become habituated to, and increase the misdeed of chatter?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena#17 will perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ འགྲོ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing chatter, one will end up in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ མི་ དགའ་ ཞིང་ ཡ་ང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, one will not be appreciated by others but will be considered unimportant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཕོ་བྲང་ དང་ མཛའ་བཤེས་ དང་ གཉེན་ དག་ གི་ ཁྱིམ་ དུ་ ཡང་ སྨྱོན་ ཐབས་ མཁན་ ལྟ་བུ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Whether at the royal palace or in the homes of family and friends, one will be looked at as one gone mad.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ འི་ ཆད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the misdeed of chatter.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ མི་དགེ་བ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པོ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$40  “What is it like to resort to, become habituated to, and increase the three mental misdeeds?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena will understand this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བརྣབ་སེམས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one resorts to, becomes habituated to, and increases covetousness, one will take birth in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ དེ འི་ རྫས་ བསགས་ བསགས་པ་ དག་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཆུ་ དང་ །_ མེ འི་ གནོད་པ ས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, all that one accumulates will be seized by the authorities, or destroyed by water or fire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཕྲོག་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ དབུལ་བ ར་ ཡང་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, one will live in constant poverty.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ གནོད་སེམས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$41  “What is it like to resort to, become habituated to, and increase the mental misdeed of ill will?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena will perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནོད་སེམས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ [89b] བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ འི་ སྐྱེ་གནས་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When resorting to, [F.89.b] becoming habituated to, and increasing ill will, one will end up in the realms of hell beings, animals, or starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ དེ་ རི་བྲགས་ དང་ །_ ཀླ་ཀློ་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ མཚོན་ གྱིས་ འཁྲུག་ ཅིང་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ འཇིགས་པ་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born among humans, sharing in their good fortune, one will be born in rocky mountains, among barbarians who are constantly afflicted by armed conflict, and one will live in permanent fear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྟག་ ཏུ་ གཡང་ས་ རྣམས་ སུ་ ལྟུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Continuously one will suffer from falling down into a precipices.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ སེམས་ ནམས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་བ ར་ གནས་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_ གནོད་པ་ དག་ གིས་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ གནོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One’s mind will never be at ease and all sorts of harm will continuously befall one.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ འི་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཆད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$42  “What is it like to resort to, become habituated to, and increase the mental misdeed of wrong view?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena will perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ མནར་མེད་པ་ ལ་སོགས་ པར་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ གྱི་ ཚོར་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མྱོང་བ ར་ སྐྱེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing wrong views will lead to the experience of the whole gamut of suffering that is associated with life in hells such as that of Ultimate Torment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དུད་འགྲོ འི་ སྐྱེ་གནས་ སུ་ ཚེ་ བྱེ་བ་ བརྒྱ་ ཕྲག་ དུ་མ ར་ འཕོ་ ཞིང་ སྐྱེ །_ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ ཡི་དགས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Moreover, one will go from one animal life to the next billions of times, and the same will occur within the realm of starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ བརྒྱ་ལ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ སྐལ་བ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ མི འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In the rare event that one is born among humans and shares the fortune of humans,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་ དེ་ ཇི་སྐད་ བཤད་པ འི་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ གྱི་ སྐྱོན་ སྟོང་ དུ་ སྒྱུར་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དེ་ ལ་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>one will nevertheless encounter thousands of variations of the flaws that are taught with respect to these unvirtuous actions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ རྣམ་པ་ གཞན་ གང་ གིས་ ན་ མི་དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ཆོས་ དག་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ ཕྲ་བ་ རྗེས་སུ་ སེམས་ ན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་བ་ ན་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ རྣམས་ སུ་ འཁྱམ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$43 “Moreover, when one contemplates the very subtle aspects of the ten unvirtuous actions in other ways, one will understand how they lead sentient beings to roam through the realms of hell beings, starving spirits, and animals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྟེན །_ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ སྒོམ །_ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$44 “In this regard, you may wonder how one may resort to, become habituated to, and increase acts of killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ གྲོགས་པོ་ ངན་པ འམ །_ སློབ་མ འམ །_ དེ འི་ གྲོགས་ ལ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྟེན་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Regarding the first of these, one may associate with negative companions, students, or friends who kill.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ རྩེ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ གནས་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One may enjoy their company, fool around with them, work with them, and stay with them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ཆེས་པ འི་ གནས་ སུ་ བྱེད །_ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཡོན་ཏན་ དུ་ ལྟ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ [90a] དེ འི་ ཚུལ་ གྱིས་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One may find such people trustworthy and in possession of good qualities, [F.90.a] and thus adopt their behavior.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་དགེ་བ འི་ བཤེས་གཉེན་ ནམ །_ སློབ་མ་ དེས་ མི་སྲོག་ གཅོད་པ འི་ ཚུལ་ ཅན་ དེ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ འི་ རྒྱུ་བྱེད་པ་ གཏམ་ སྣ་ཚོགས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Unvirtuous teachers and students who have the habit of killing people will tell all sorts of stories to justify killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལམ་ མ་ཡིན་པ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ དང་ །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These are not the path and only lead others to indulge in killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ མཆོད་སྦྱིན་ གྱི་ གཏམ་ མམ །_ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ རི་ དག ས་ ཀྱི་ གཏམ་ མམ །_ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ རོ་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ་ རབ་ཏུ་ ཉེས་པ འི་ གཏམ་ མམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In this manner, they may tell stories about sacrificial offerings, stories about wild game, or wicked stories based on their gustatory cravings.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ དགྲ་བོ་ མི་ མཛའ་བ་ དང་ འབྲེལ་བ་ ལ་ ལན་ལྡོན་པ འི་ གཏམ་ མམ །_ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ དེ འི་ རྫས་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ འི་ གཏམ་ མམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Similarly, they may tell stories about retaliation against hostile adversaries or relations, or stories based on their craving for these people’s belongings.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ སྤྲོ་བ་ རྫས་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ་ དང་ །_ གྲགས་པ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ གཏམ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Similarly, taking great in delight in affliction, they will tell stories based on their craving for material things or about deeds for acquiring fame.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ དེ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ཆེས་པ འི་ གནས་ སུ་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ་ ན །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྟེན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In these ways, they lead others on. If one trusts and adheres to such people, one may also end up resorting to killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བསྟེན་པ་ ནི །_ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ ར་ འགྲོ །_ ཡི་དགས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ འགྲོ །_ དུད་འགྲོ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ འགྲོ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Resorting to killing results in entering the realms of hell beings, starving spirits, and animals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་འདོད་པ །_ མི་ སྡུག་པ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ མཁས་པ་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ སྨད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such effects are unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant, and are condemned by all wise people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མིར་ སྐྱེས་ ན་ ཡང་ ཚེ་ ཐུང་བ འི་ རྒྱུ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if one is born human, one’s life will be short.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ ན་ བཤེས་གཉེན་ ངན་པ འི་ ས་བོན་ ཅན་ གྱི་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྟེན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, the taking of life stemming from a wicked teacher makes one become totally habituated to killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ ངན་པ་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$45 “What does it mean to become habituated to unwholesome people?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ ངན་པ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བསྟེན་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ སྦྱར་ ཏེ །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བྱས་ ནས་ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ མགུ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཡོན་ཏན་ དུ་ ལྟ་བ འི་ བློ་ ཅན་ དུ་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Based on the taking of life that is influenced by unwholesome people as just described, one rejoices in, appreciates, contemplates, and condones acts of killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཉིད་ ལ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ རྣམ་པ་ མང་པོ ས་ གཞན་ གྱི་ སྲོག་ འཕྲོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Setting one’s mind on killing, one succeeds in slaying others by numerous means.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ སྐྱོན་ དུ་ མི་ འགྲང་ །_ དེ་ ལ་ སྨོད་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད །_ དེ་ ལ་ དགའ་བ་ དང་ འབྲལ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད །_ |#| ཕྱིར་ཞིང་ དེ འི་ ངང་ཚུལ་ དུ་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Without counting it as a fault and condemning it, one delights in killing and does not refrain from it. |#| In this way, killing becomes second nature.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་ མི་ གཅོད་པ འི་ ཚུལ་ ཅན་ གཞན་དག་ ཀྱང་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ དེ་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those who otherwise have the habit of not killing will be drawn into the practice of killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཏམ་རྒྱུད་ དང་ བཅས་པ་ སྣ་ཚོགས་ དག་ གིས་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ སྦྱར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will also engage in the kinds of conversation, and so on, alluded to previously.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ [90b] དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is what it is like to grow habituated to killing. [F.90.b]</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$46 “What does it mean to increase killing?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ན་ གང་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བྱས་ ནས་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ སྦྱར་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ ལ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ བྱེད་པ་ ན །_ དེ་ ལ་ གོམས་པ་ དང་ །_ སྡིག་པ འི་ གྲོགས་པོ་ དང་ ཕྲད་པ ས་ རྒྱ་ འབྲེ་ བར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Once habituated to killing in the way just described, one may associate with evil companions and thereby greatly expand one’s murderous activities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་དུག་ མདའ་ བྱེད །_ ཁྱི་ སོགས་ པར་ བྱེད །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ འི་ བྱ་ སྡུད་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ གཏུམ་པོ་ དང་ སྟེན་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, one may craft poisonous arrows, gather dogs and raptors, and accept the protection of barbarous people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐབ་མོ་ ལ་ དགའ་ སྟེ །_ ཡ་ལད་ དང་ །_ མཚོན་ཆ་ དང་ །_ རལ་གྲི་ དང་ །_ མདའ་བོ་ ཆེ་ དང་ །_ སྟེའུ་ ཀ་ དང་ །_ འཁོར་ལོ་ དང་ །_ གོ་མཚོན་ ལ་སོགས་པ འི་ ངང་ཚུལ་ ཅན་ ཡིན །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་ པར་ བྱེད་པ འི་ རྒྱུ་ གཞན་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱང་ ཡོངས་སུ་ འཛིན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Fond of warfare, one may wear chain mail, weapons, swords, lances, axes, disks, helmets, and so on—thus adopting all possible instruments for killing others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ དེ་ལྟ་ བུ་ ནི་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the person who increases killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱུ་ དེ་ དང་ །_ གཞི་ དེ་ དང་ །_ རྐྱེན་ དེས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་ སྟེ །_ གནོད་པ་ མི་བཟད་པ ས་ མངོན་པར་ གནོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$47 “Through such causes, bases, and conditions one will be born in the realms of hell beings, animals, and starving spirits, and so be tormented by unbearable harm.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཐ་མ་ དང་ །_ འབྲིང་ དང་ །_ ཆེན་པོ ས་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཐ་མ་ དང་ །_ འབྲིང་ དང་ །_ ཆེན་པོ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Based on whether one’s killing was minor, intermediate, or severe, there will be a corresponding experience of minor, intermediate, or severe ripening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ བྱས་ ལ་ བསགས་པ ས་ ནི་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ མི་འགྱུར་བ་ མེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$48 “Whenever an act has been carried out and accumulated it will also ripen.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ ན་ བདག་ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ བྱས་པ འི་ ལས་ ནི་ བདག་ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཉེ་བ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Therefore, acts that were done by oneself will also be experienced by oneself.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ གལ་ཏེ་ འཁོར་བ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ བྱུང་ ན་ སྡིག་པ་ སྤངས་ ནས་ དགེ་བ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱད་པ ར་ བྱ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Hence, if one has become disenchanted with cyclic existence one should give up evil acts and pursue what is virtuous.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྟེན་ ཅིང་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These are the explanations of resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing the taking of life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ན་མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྟེན་ ཅིང་ སྒོམ་ སྟེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$49 “How does one resort to, become habituated to, and increase acts of stealing?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ ས །_ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How does resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing such acts lead to the experience of life in hell?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ འཆལ་པ འི་ མི་ ནི་ ངོ་བོ་ ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ འི་ ངང་ཚུལ་ ཅན་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“People whose discipline has degenerated will naturally be disposed to thievery.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གྲོགས་པོ་ ངན་པ འམ །_ སློབ་མ་ དང་ འབྲེལ་བ ས་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཐ་མ་ དང་ །_ འབྲིང་ དང་ །_ ཆེན་པོ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When they associate with negative companions or students they will engage in minor, intermediate, or great acts of stealing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ཐ་མ་ ནི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཆད་པ ས་ སྐྲག་ ནས་ གཞན་ གྱི་ ལེན་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Minor acts of stealing occur as described earlier, when one takes others’ possessions out of fear of otherwise being punished by the authorities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འབྲིང་ ནི་ [91a] དངོས་པོ་ ཆུང་ངུ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ ཞིང་བཟང་པོ་ ལ་ བརྐུས་པ་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ འབྲིང་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Intermediate acts occur [F.91.a] when one steals smaller things as long as one does not steal from a field of excellence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ དང་ །_ དགེ་འདུན་ དག་ ལས་ ནི་ ཆུང་ངུ་ ཞིག་ བླངས་ ན་ ཡང་ ཆེན་པོ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if a minor thing is taken from the Buddha, Dharma, or Saṅgha, the result will be great.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ དང་ །_ དགེ་འདུན་ གྱི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ བླངས་པ་ དེ་དག་ ལས་ ཀྱང་ རིས་ སུ་ འཐུན་ པར་ སླར་ ཕུལ་ ན །_ སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ ནི་ དག་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>However, if one has improperly taken from the Buddha, Dharma, or Saṅgha but later makes proportionate offerings to them, the negative act can be purified, especially in the case of the Buddha and the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་འདུན་ གྱི་ བརྐུས་པ་ ནི་ ཚོར་བ་ མ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ དག་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ མེད་ དེ་ ཞིང་ ལྕི་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one steals from the saṅgha, it cannot be purified without experiencing some painful effects because the saṅgha is a field with a particularly strong karmic charge.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ཞལ་ དུ་ འདུ་བ འི་ སྒོ་ ཞིག་ ན་ ནི་ དེ་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ ཆེན་པོ ར་ ལྟུང་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one steals a means of sustenance from the congregation one will fall into the great hells.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ཞལ་ དུ་ འདུ་བ འི་ སྒོ་མ་ ཡིན་ ན་ ནི །_ དེ འི་ ནང་ གི་ བར་ མནར་མེད་པ འི་ འཁོར་ མུན་ནག་ ཆེན་པོ་ ལ་སོགས་ པར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one steals something else from the congregation, one will instead be born in one of the hells that surround that of Ultimate Torment, such as Great Darkness.#18</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཆུང་ངུ་ ཞིག་ བླངས་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྟེན་ ཅིང་ སེམས་ ལ་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་ ན །_ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཆུང་ངུ་ དེས་ ཀྱང་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$50 “If one takes up, resorts to, rejoices in, becomes habituated to, and increases stealing, even minor forms of stealing will lead to birth among hell beings, animals, and starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ འཆགས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ལ་ འགྱོད་ ན་ དེ འི་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ མ་ངེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one does not develop attachment to and rejoice in the act, and instead regrets it, the ripening will become indeterminate.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ འི་ ངང་ཚུལ་ ཅན་ ཞིག་ དེ་ ཐབས་ དུ་མ ས་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱོད་ ན །_ འདི་ ནི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$51 “Resorting to stealing occurs when someone who is inclined to take what was not given engages in various ways in acts of thievery.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$52 “What is meant by becoming habituated to stealing?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ འི་ རྫས་ ཐོབ་ ནས་ མགུ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ ཆོམ་རྐུན་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_། དེ་ རྫས་ དེ་ ཐོབ་ ནས་ བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བགོ་བ་ བྱས་ ཤིང་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Having obtained something that was stolen, one may rejoice and delight in the robbers and thieves, and happily consume or employ what was stolen.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡོན་ཏན་ དུ་ བཟུང་ ནས་ གཞན་དག་ ཀྱང་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ འཇུག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ འཛིན་ དུ་ བཅུག་ ཅིང་ བྱེད་ དུ་ འཇུག་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Considering such conduct to be a good quality, one may encourage and help others to steal.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་ བུ་ ནི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is becoming habituated to stealing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$53 “How is stealing increased?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ བྱས་ ནས །_ མལ་ཆ་ དང་ །_ བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཅའ་བ་ དང་ །_ [91b] གོས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ དང་ །_ བཏུང་བ་ དང་ །_ སྨད་ འཚོང་བ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་པོ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This occurs when one steals in order to enjoy linens, food, drink, [F.91.b] clothing, jewelry, beverages, prostitutes, and ornaments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ སེམས་ ཀྱིས་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Delighted, one may think,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདེ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ འདི་ ནི་ ལེགས་པ ར་ བྱས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>‘Among all pleasures, those which comes from stealing are the best!’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱུ་ དེས་ བདག་ མལ་ཆ་ དང་ །_ བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཅའ་བ་ དང་ །_ གོས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ དང་ །_ བཏུང་བ་ དང་ །_ སྨད་ འཚོང་བ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་པོ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ གིས་ མཆོག་ ཏུ་ བདེ་བ་ མྱོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With such thoughts one enjoys linens, food, drink, clothing, jewelry, beverages, prostitutes, and ornaments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ དེ་ བདག་ གིས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱད་པ ར་ བྱ་ སྟེ །_ དེ་ བདག་ ལ་ བདེ་བ་ རབ་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ ཏུ་ འགྱུར་ རོ་ སྙམ་ ན་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ སྦྱར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thinking, ‘I must continue stealing because it brings me so much pleasure,’ one then proceeds as described above.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ དེ་ ནི་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ རྣམས་ སུ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ ངེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is what it means to increase the act of stealing and as a result of that it is certain that sentient beings will experience life in a hell.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ །_ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$54 “What does it mean to resort to, become habituated to, and increase acts of sexual misconduct?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ ཚུལ་བཞིན་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ ཡིད་ ལ་ བྱེད་པ ས་ ཟིལ་ གྱིས་ ནོན་པ་ ནི་ འདོད་ཆགས་ དང་ བཅས་པ འི་ རིས་ འཐུན་པ་ གཞན་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ བྱེའུ་ མཆིལ་པ་ དང་ །_ ངུར་བ་ དང་ །_ གོང་མ་སྲེག་ དང་ །_ ནེ་ཙོ་ དང་ །_ རྨ་བྱ་ དང་ །_ སྲེག་པ་ དང་ །_ ཉ་ དང་ །_ སྲོག་ཆགས་ དུད་ ཀ་དག་ ནི་ ལྷ་མ་ ཡིན་ གྱི་ རིས་ དག་ ནས་ ཤི་འཕོས་ ནས་ འདིར་ སྐྱེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཤས་ ཆེ་བ འི་ གྲོགས་པོ་ ངན་པ་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཡན་ལག་ མ་ཡིན་པ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Overcome by an inappropriate mentality, one may become a type of being with a propensity for desire such as a swallow, duck, pheasant, parrot, peafowl, partridge, fish, or smoky creatures.#19 When such beings die and transfer out of the family of asuras they may be born among humans and associate with bad companions who are full of desire. With them they may then have inappropriate sexual relationships.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཚུལ་བཞིན་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ ཉིས་འགྱུར་ གྱིས་ མངོན་པར་ ཞེན་ ལ་ དེ་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཚིམ་པ་ མེད་པ་ དང་ བཅས་པ འི་ སེམས་ ཀྱིས་ ཚུལ་བཞིན་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱོད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Being mistaken in these two ways, they are filled with attachment, and they act in inappropriate ways to sate their insatiable desires.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ དྲི་ཟ་ དེར་ ཉེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ གང་ གིས་ དེར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ཚུལ་བཞིན་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ སྐྱེ་གནས་ ཀྱི་ ཞིང་ ལ་ སྐྱོན་ ཡོད་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དེར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This makes it impossible for the gandharvas, otherwise destined to be born there, to take birth, because it desecrates the birthplace.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱུ་ དེས་ན་ ཚུལ་བཞིན་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ དང་ བཅས་པ འི་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནི་ ངན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the reasons why sexual misconduct, which is based on improper desire, is a misdeed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ དེ་ རེག་བྱ འི་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཤས་ ཆེ་བ ས་ དེ་ དང་ དེ་ཉིད་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་ སྟེ །_ དེ་ ནི་ འདི་ལྟར་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ འདི་ ཡང་ དང་ ཡང་ དུ་ སྟེན་ [92a] ཅིང་ རེག་བྱ་ ངན་པ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟར་ འདི་ ནི་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$55 “Resorting to sexual misconduct occurs when a person with an inordinate desire for carnal contact [F.92.a] indulges in such acts and continuously repeats them, finding intense gratification in physical sensations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What does it mean to become habituated to sexual misconduct?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལས་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ཡང་ དང་ ཡང་ དུ་ སྟེན་ ཅིང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ དེ འི་ ཡིད་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ གཞན་ སྤངས་ ཏེ །_ དེ་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ འདི་ཉིད་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱས་ ནས །_ ཡང་ ཡུལ་ བདེ་བ་ དེ་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This refers to repeatedly engaging in sexual misconduct and thinking about it, becoming so infatuated with it that one gives up other pleasures only to focus on sexual misconduct and the object of one’s desire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What is meant by increasing sexual misconduct?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ ཚུལ་བཞིན་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ ཡིད་ ལ་ བྱེད་པ ས་ བརླན་པ འི་ བྱིས་པ་ སོ་སོ འི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ནི །_ འདི་ལྟར་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ནི་ མཆོག་ ཏུ་ བཟང་བ་ ཡིན་ ལ །_ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ མི་ གཡེམ་པ་ ནི་ མ་ ཡིན་ ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Infantile, ordinary beings consumed by inappropriate mental activity feel that sexual misconduct is the best thing possible and they think that it is a mistake to classify such behavior as a form of misconduct.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡོན་ཏན་ མཆོག་ དང་ འདྲ་བ ར་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ འཛིན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_། དེ་ གཞན་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ ཀྱང་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ འཇུག་ ཅིང་ བྱེད་ དུ་ འཇུག་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Instead they regard sexual misconduct as a supreme quality and therefore encourage many others to engage in it.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is what it means to increase sexual misconduct.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པོ་ འདི་དག་ ནི་ བྱིས་པ་ སོ་སོ འི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ མི་དགེ་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These three physical misdeeds are unvirtuous actions in which infantile, ordinary beings engage.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ངག་ གི་ ནི་ རྣམ་པ་ བཞི་ སྟེ །_ བརྫུན་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཕྲ་མ་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ འོ །_། དེ་ ལ་ བརྫུན་ གང་ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$56 “What about the four verbal misdeeds: lying, divisive talk, harsh words, and chatter?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ བདག་ཉིད་ ལ་ བདག་ཉིད་ སླུ་ ཞིང་ གཞན་ ཡང་ སླུ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ འདི་ ནི་ བདག་ དང་ གཞན་ སླུ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Lying is to deceive oneself and others, for by speaking lies one does indeed deceive both oneself and others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ རྒྱུ་ལྔ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ འདོད་ཆགས་ དང་ །_ ཞེ་སྡང་ དང་ །_ འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ རྙེད་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ ལོག་པ འི་ འདུལ་བ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྡུད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>There are five causes for lying: desire, anger, fear, personal gain, and indoctrination into the prescribed practices of a misguided religion.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How does one lie?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཕོ་བྲང་ འཁོར་ ན་ འདུག་ ཀྱང་ རུང་ །_ ཁྱིམ་བདག་ གི་ འཁོར་ གྱི་ ནང་ ན་ འདུག་ ཀྱང་ རུང་ །_ ཉེ་དུ འི་ ནང་ ན་ འདུག་ ཀྱང་ རུང་ སྟེ །_ མཛའ་བཤེས་ དང་ །_ མཛའ་བཤེས་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ དག་ སྨྲ་བ་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Whether at the royal court, in an assembly of householders, or among one’s relatives, one may lie to both those who are dear to oneself and those who are not.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཛའ་བཤེས་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱིར་ ནི་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཀྱིས་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་ ལ །_ མཛའ་བཤེས་ མ་ ཡིན་ [92b] པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ནི་ ཞེ་སྡང་ གིས་ ཀྱང་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One may lie to those who are dear to oneself out of desire and to those who are not dear to oneself [F.92.b] out of anger.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྙེད་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ཡང་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་ སྟེ །_ ནོར་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ་ དེ་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One may also lie for the sake of personal gain and for the sake of wealth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཆོས་ ལོག་པ འི་ ཚིག་ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྡུད་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$57 “Moreover, indoctrination into the prescribed practices of a misguided religion is also a way of lying.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ བྲམ་ཟེ་ རྣམས་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གྱི་ ཕྱིར་ དང་ །_ ནོར་ འཕྲོག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དང་ །_ རང་ གི་ སྲོག་ ལ་ གནོད་པ་ དང་ །_ བག་མ་ ལེན་པ་ དག་ གི་ ཕྱིར་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲས་ ཀྱང་ མི་ གོས་ སོ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>For example, brahmins may declare that lying will not carry any blemish as long as it is done to obtain desirable qualities, or to safeguard one’s wealth, protect one’s life, or obtain a bride.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ ཆོས་ ལོག་པ འི་ ཚིག་ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྡུད་པ འི་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ མི་ གཏི་མུག་པ་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ འི་ ཚིག་ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྡུད་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ མི་བཟད་པ ར་ ཡང་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such declarations are a form of lying by means of indoctrination into the discipline of a misguided religion, and through such indoctrination into ignorant and wrong views one will come to live in an unbearable hell.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ འགྲུབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ ས་བོན་ དག་ ནི་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་བ་ ཡིན་པ ས་ རང་ གི་ སྲོག་ གི་ ཕྱིར་ རམ །_ གཞན་ གྱི་ སྲོག་ གི་ ཕྱིར་ བརྫུན་ ཅུང་ཟད་ ཀྱང་ སྨྲ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱ་བ་ འདི་ ནི་ མཆོག་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Since lying plants the seeds of the hell realms it is best to entirely avoid any form of lying, even at the expense of one’s own life or that of others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིགས་ པས་ ཀྱང་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་ སྟེ །_ གང་ བདག་ གིས་ བརྫུན་ འདི་ མ་ སྨྲས་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$58 “One may also tell lies out of fear, as when someone thinks,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ བདག་ གི་ སྲོག་ ལ་ དམན་པ་ དོན་མེད་པ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ་ སྙམ་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>‘Unless I lie now, I may expose my life to serious danger for no reason.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ གང་ ལས་ འཇིགས་ པར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དེ འི་ དོན་ དུ་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In such cases one lies motivated by fear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱུ་ལྔ་པོ་ འདི་དག་ གིས་ བྱིས་པ་ དག་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་བ་ སྨྲ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Thus, these five factors cause infantile beings to lie.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཏི་མུག་ ནི་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ གནས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>All of them are based on delusion.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདིར་ ཚིགས་ སུ་ བཅད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$59 “At this point, there are some verses:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཁྱད་གསོད་ ཅིང་ །_། ཆོས་ གཅིག་ ལས་ ནི་ འདའ་ བྱེད་པ །_། བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ འི་ ལུས་ཅན་ གྱིས །_། སྡིག་པ་ མི་ བྱེད་ ཅི་ཡང་ མེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Disregarding what lies beyond this world And transgressing the one Dharma, Liars will not shy away From any form of negative act.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ ཡི་ ལུས་ སུ་ སྐྱེས་མ་ ཐག _། ཁ་ ནས་ སྟ་རེ་ ལྟ་བུ་ ཡི །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$60 “As soon as they are born with a human body, Axe-like words will spout from their mouths.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ འབྱུང་ ངན་པ ར་ བརྗོད་ སྨྲ་བ །_། དེ་ ཡིས་ བདག་ཉིད་ གཅོད་པ ར་ བྱེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And thus, those who speak wrongly Only undermine themselves.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདེན་པ ར་ སྨྲ་ ཞིང་ འཁྲུག་ མི་ བྱ །_། བསླངས་ ན་ ཆུང་ ཡང་ སྦྱིན་པ ར་ བྱ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$61 “Speaking truthfully, not starting fights, And giving when asked, even if one has only a little—</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནས་ འདི་ གསུམ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ནི །_། ལྷ་ རྣམས་ དག་ གི་ དྲུང་ དུ་ འགྲོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those who carefully observe these three key points Will enter the divine assemblies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ རྒྱུ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དང་ །_ རྐྱེན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱིས་ བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱ་ ཞིང་ གཞན་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་བ་ ན་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$62 “Therefore, regardless of the causes and conditions, one should refrain from lying and should not rejoice in lies told by others, either.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་བ་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ འབེལ་བ འི་ གཏམ་ ཟེར་ དུ་ མི་ འགྲོ །_ མི་ གནས །_ འདུག་པ ར་ མི་ བྱ འོ །_། གཞན་ དུ་ ན་ འདི་ ཡང་ བརྫུན་ སྨྲ་བ་ [93a] མངོན་དུ་ ཟེར་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ་ ཞེས་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ གཞན་དག་ གིས་ བསམས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$63 “Nor should one seek out, take part in, or participate in conversations with liars, [F.93.a] lest others will think that one is a liar oneself.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ ན་ ལས་ དྲི་མ་ ཅན་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ འི་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་ འགྲོགས་ པས་ ལས་ དྲི་མ་ ཅན་ དུ་ གཞན་དག་ སེམས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, if one befriends people who are fond of tainted activities, others will come to think of oneself as tainted as well.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ སྡིག་པ འི་ གྲོགས་པོ་ དང་ འགྲོགས་ པར་ མི་ བྱ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is to say, one ought not keep negative company.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ སྡིག་པ འི་ གྲོགས་པོ་ དང་ འགྲོགས་པ་ ནི་ འཁོར་བ འི་ འཆིང་བ་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ གནས་ ཡིན་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Negative company leads to bondage in cyclic existence and birth in the realms of hell beings, starving spirits, and animals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ འི་ བཤེས་གཉེན་ དང་ འགྲོགས་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ ཐར་པ་ མཆོག་ ཡིན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Virtuous company, on the other hand, leads to supreme liberation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་དག་ ནི་ བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ མདོར་བཤད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is a brief explanation of lying.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཕྲ་མ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན །_ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་ཡོད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$64 “What is divisive talk and what forms does it assume?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྲ་མ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ནི་ འཐུན་ ཞིང་ འབྱོར་པ་ དག་ ལ་ དབྱེ་བ འི་ བསམ་པ ས་ ཚིག་ བརྗོད་པ་ ནི་ ཕྲ་མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Divisive talk occurs when words are spoken to sow discord among those who otherwise enjoyed harmonious relationships.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ རྣམ་པ་ གཉིས་ ཏེ །_ ཕ་རོལ་ དང་ སྦྱོར་བ་ དང་ །_ མི་ སྦྱོར་བ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>There are two forms of divisive talk: direct and indirect.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ཁྱོད་ ཀྱིས་ མི་ གཉིས་ དང་ དབྱེ་བ འི་ སྦྱོར་བ་ གྱིས་ ཤིག་ ཅེས་ དགྲ འམ །_ དགྲ་ ཆུང་ངུ་ གཞན་དག་ གིས་ སྦྱོར་བ་ བྱེད་པ་ དང་ །_ བདག་ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ འབྱེད་ པར་ འདོད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is to say, one might instruct someone to cause a rift among two people so that they become enemies or adversaries, or one might also seek to do so personally.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན །_ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་ཡོད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$65 “What then are harsh words, and what forms do they assume?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ནི་ བདག་ དང་ གཞན་ ལ་ གནོད་པ་ བྱེད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Harsh words are harmful to oneself and others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྲོ་བ འི་ རྒྱུ་ འཐུན་ པར་ གྱུར་པ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ །_ མི་ སྡུག་པ །_ མི་ དགའ་བ འི་ ཚིག་ བརྗོད་པ་ ཉན་པ་ དང་ །_ མི་ འཐུན་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They are the concordant cause of anger, and they are unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant to listen to.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདོད་ཆགས་ དང་ །_ ཞེ་སྡང་ དང་ །_ གཏི་མུག་ དང་ བཅས་པ །_ བྱིས་པ་ སོ་སོ འི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ ཚིག་ སྨྲ་བ་ འདི་ ནི་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་ སྟེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They involve desire, anger, and delusion, and they are engaged in by all infantile, ordinary individuals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣམ་པ་ དུ་མ །_ དམིགས་པ་ དུ་མ །_ རྒྱུ་ དུ་མ །_ སེམས་ ཀྱི་ ཀུན་ ནས་ ལྡང་བ་ དུ་མ །_ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ དུ་མ །_ བདེ་འགྲོ ར་ འགྲོ་བ་ རྣམ་པར་ འཇིག་པ་ དུ་ [93b] མ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They take numerous forms and involve numerous observations, causes, mental states, and types of ripening, as well as numerous ways of destroying the joyful destinations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མི་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ལྡང་བ འི་ རྒྱུ ར་ གྱུར་པ །_ འཐུན་ པར་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.93.b] They make everyone unhappy and they cause and support anger in the world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣམ་པར་ འཇིག་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_ ཡིད་ མི་ ཆེས་པ འི་ གནས་ སུ་ གྱུར་པ །_ ཡིད་ གཅུགས་པ་ མ་ཡིན་པ །_ ལྕེ་ དུག་ ལྟ་བུ ར་ གྱུར་པ འི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They provoke destruction, breed distrust and unkindness, and emerge from a poisonous tongue.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ དག་ གི་ དྲི་མ་ ནི་ ཚངས་པ་ མཚུངས་པ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ས་ རྣམ་པར་ སྤངས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, the stains of harsh words are to be avoided by all who practice pure conduct.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདིར་ ཚིགས་ སུ་ བཅད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$66 “At this point, there are some verses:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བརྟན་པ ས་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་ སྤང་བྱ་ ཞིང་ །_། རྟག་ ཏུ་ ཡང་དག་ ཚིག་ སྨྲོས་ ཤིག _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“The steadfast should give up harsh words And always speak words that are genuine.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ སྙན་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ འི་ མི །_། མྱ་ངན་ འདས་ ལ་ཉེ་ བར་གནས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The person fond of speaking in pleasant ways Will be close to the transcendence of suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ ཞི་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ སྨྲ་ བྱ་ ཞིང་ །_། དྲི་མ་ ཡོད་པ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྤང་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$67 “Always speak words of peace And give up words that are tainted.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ གི་ དྲི་མ ས་ ཟིལ་ ནོན་པ །_། མི་གང་ དེ་ ནི་ དམྱལ་བ ར་ འགྲོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A person destroyed by stained words Is a person heading for hell.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ གི་ དྲི་མ ས་ ཟིལ་ ནོན་པ །_། གང་ཡིན་ དེ་ ལ་ བདེ་བ་ མེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$68 “A person possessed by tainted words Does not find any happiness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེང་གེ་ སྦྲུལ་ ནི་ འཕགས་ མིན་ ལྟར །_། དེ་དག་ ལ་ ནི་ མཐོ་རིས་ མེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Like treacherous lions and snakes, Such people will not reach the higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ ཚིག་རྩུབ་ མི་སྨྲ་ ཞིང་ །_། གང་དག་ གཡོ་ ནི་ རྣམ་ སྤངས་པ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$69 “Those who refrain from words That are harsh and deceptive,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དགའ་ སྐྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_། བདེ་བ་ དང་ ནི་ དབུགས་ འབྱིན་ བྱེད །_། སྐྱེ་བོ་ དེ་ ནི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདིར །_། དགའ་ ཞིང་ ཕ་རོལ་ མཐོ་རིས་ འགྲོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And instead bring joy, Happiness, and relief, $70 Will be happy in this world And proceed to the higher realms thereafter.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ འདྲ་བ་ ཡི་ མི་ དག་ ནི །_། མཁས་པ་ དེ་ ལ་ ཕྱག་ བྱར་ འོས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such people are worthy Of the veneration of the wise.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདེན་ཚིག་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ ཞི་བ་ དང་ །_། གཡོ་སྒྱུ་ མེད་ ཅིང་ དྲང་པོ འི་ སེམས །_། གཞན་ ལ་ གནོད་པ་ བྱེད་ དང་ བྲལ །_། དེ་ ནི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྒྱལ་མཚན་ དགའ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$71 “Those speakers of the truth who are always tranquil, Who are sincere, free from deceit, And who refrain from harming others, Are joyful banners of the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལག་པ་ བརྡབས་པ འི་ སྒྲ་ ལྟ་བུ ར །_། མི་ ནི་ ཆུང་བ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ ཡིན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$72 “Those who rattle on like the sound of clapping hands Are inferior among humans.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ དེ་ ཐོབ་ ཆོས་ མི་ ཤེས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Obtaining that, they do not know the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ ནི་ རྨོངས་པ་ དག་ གིས་ བསླུས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They are fooled by those who are deluded.#20</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ བདག་ སྡུག་ མི་ འགྱུར་ དང་ །_། གང་དག་ བདེ་བ་ མི་འདོད་པ །_། དེ་ ནི་ སྡིག་ གི་ ལས་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_། སྲེད་པ འི་ རྒྱུ་ ཡིས་ རྣམ་པར་ བསླུས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$73 “Not rectifying their own suffering And not wanting to be happy, People engage in negative acts And are fooled by the causes of craving.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ དུ་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་འགྲོ་བ །_། ནོར་ དང་ བུ་ དང་ ཆུང་མ་ དང་ །_། མཛའ་བཤེས་ ཉེ་དུ་ གཉེན་འདབ་ དང་ །_། དེར་ ནི་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$74 “In consequence of their acts They cannot come close To wealth, children, or spouse, Nor to friends and relatives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལེགས་པ ར་ བྱས་ དང་ ཉེས་པ ར་ བྱས །_། དེ་དག་ འགྲོ་བ འི་ རྗེས་སུ་ འགྲོ །_། མཁའ་ ལ་ བྱ་ དག་ གནས་པ་ ཡིན །_། དེ འི་ གྲིབ་ ལྷན་ [94a] ཅིག་ འགྲོ་བ་ བཞིན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$75 “Good deeds and bad deeds Follow people wherever they go, Just as birds in the sky [F.94.a] Are followed by their shadows.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ལམ་རྒྱགས་ ཉུང་བ་ དག _། ལམ་ ཞུགས་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ འགྲོ་བ་ ལྟར །_། དེ་བཞིན་ ལས་བཟང་ མ་ བྱས་པ འི །_། སེམས་ཅན་ དག་ ནི་ ངན་འགྲོ ར་ འགྲོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$76 “Just as travelers with insufficient provisions Will suffer on their journey, So beings who have failed to do good Will be heading for the lower realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ལམ་རྒྱགས་ མང་ བདོག་པ །_། ལམ་ ཞུགས་ བདེ་བ ར་ འགྲོ་བ་ ལྟར །_། དེ་བཞིན་ ལས་བཟང་ བྱས་པ་ ཡི །_། སེམས་ཅན་ དག་ ནི་ བདེ་འགྲོ ར་ འགྲོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$77 “Just as travelers with abundant provisions Will be happy on their journey, So beings who have done good Will be heading for the higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡུན་རིང་ ཡུལ་ གཞན་ གནས་པ་ ཡི །_། མི་ དག་ བདེ་བ ར་ འོངས་པ་ ལྟར །_། གཉེན་ དང་ སྡུག་པ་ མཛའ་བཤེས་ དག _། འདིར་ འོངས་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ ལྟར །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$78 “When people have spent a long time abroad And are delighted to return home, Their homecoming will be celebrated By happy friends and dear ones.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ བསོད་ནམས་ བྱས་པ འི་ མི །_། འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདི་ ནས་ ཕ ར་ འགྲོ་བ །_། བསོད་ནམས་ ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ མངོན་དགའ་ སྟེ །_། གཉེན་ སྡུག་ དག་ ནི་ འོངས་པ་ བཞིན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$79 “Likewise, when those who have created merit Set out from this world to the other side, Their merits will create a joyous celebration, Like a happy party of friends and dear ones.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ ཚེ་ ཕྱི་མ འི །_། བསོད་ནམས་ དག་ ནི་ བྱ་ ཞིང་ བསགས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$80 “Therefore, create and accumulate Merit for lives to come.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསོད་ནམས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ །_། སྲོག་ཆགས་ རྣམས་ ནི་ དྲན་ གནས་ ཡིན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Beings should be mindful Of creating merit for the next world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྤྱོད་པ་ འཐུན་ པར་ གང་ སྤྱོད་པ འི །_། བསོད་ནམས་ དག་ ལ་ ལྷ་ བསྟོད་ ཅིང་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$81 “Acting harmoniously, people of merit Will be praised by the gods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ འདིར་ ནི་ མངོན་དགའ་ ལ །_། ཕ་རོལ་ མཐོ་རིས་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will be happy here And happy in the realms beyond.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནས་ འདི་ གཞན་ གྱིས་ མཐོང་བ་ ཡི །_། མཁས་པ་ དག་ གིས་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ བསྲུངས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$82 “As the wise perceive this key point They will maintain their discipline.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཕགས་པ་ མཐོང་བ་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས །_། འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདིར་ ནི་ ཞི་བ་ བསྟེན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Noble beings with supreme sight Practice peace within this world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེ་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ གྱི་ ཚིག་ བཞི་པ འི་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ ལ་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$83 “Moreover, spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena understand chatter, the fourth verbal misdeed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་ཡོད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What forms does chatter assume?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ འབྱུང་བ་ སྔ་ཕྱི་ འབྲེལ་བ་ མེད་པ འི་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ དང་ །_ སེམས་ འཇུག་པ་ ཡང་བ ས་ སྔ་ཕྱི་ འབྲེལ་བ་ མེད་པ འི་ ཚིག་ བརྗོད་པ འི་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Chatter is unrelated babble, the expression of random words based on shallow thinking.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱགས་པ་ དང་ བཅས་པ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱགས་པ་ མེད་པ འི་ དུས་ ཀྱིས་ བསླངས་པ་ ཡང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Some forms of chatter are careless, whereas others are not.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱེད་པ འི་ རྒྱུ འི་ ངོ་བོ་ སྐྱེད་པ་ དེ་ ཚེ་ འདི་ ལ་ ཡིད་ གཅུགས་པ འི་ གནས་ སུ་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ ཚེ་ འདི འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ སྐྱེད་པ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ སྨོད་པ འི་ གནས་ ཀྱི་ རྒྱུ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By engaging in chatter, one will be considered untrustworthy in this life, and the people of the world will despise one’s course of activities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དོན་མེད་ པར་ སྨྲ་བ་ ནི་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ སྟེ །_ [94b] ཚིག་ གི་ དྲི་མ་ བཞི་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ བསྐྱེད་པ་ དང་ །_ སྐྱེད་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ སྨྲ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱ་ ཞིང་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཡི་ རང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱ་ ལ །_ གཞན་ གྱི་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ སྨྲ་བ་ དེ་ ལ་ གནས་པ ར་ མི་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Chatter is pointless prattle, [F.94.b] and thus one ought to refrain from either directly or indirectly engaging in, or rejoicing in, this fourth verbal stain. And neither should one keep company with those who engage in chatter.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ནི་ བརྣབ་སེམས་ དང་ །_ གནོད་སེམས་ དང་ །_ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$84 “Covetousness, ill will, and wrong view belong to the path of unvirtuous mental acts.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ བརྣབ་སེམས་ ནི་ གཞན་ གྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བཟུང་བ འི་ ནོར་རྫས་ དང་ །_ ནོར་རྫས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པ་ ལ །_ ངག་ དང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Among these, covetousness is the state of being mentally and verbally obsessed with the substances and features of wealth procured by others,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ བདག་ གིར་ བྱ འོ་ སྙམ་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>thinking, ‘This should be mine!’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་དག་པ་ མ་ཡིན་པ འི་ ཚུལ་བཞིན་ ཡིད་ ལ་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ དེ་ གཞན་ གྱི་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལ་ འཕྲལ་ ལ་ སེམས་ ལྡང་ སྟེ །_ དོན་ ལ་ འཆུམས་པ་ རྒྱུ་ མེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Covetousness is that form of inappropriate mental engagement that is an impulsive reaction to, and craving for, the fine circumstances of others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ བརྣབ་སེམས་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ མི་འདོད་པ །_ མི་ སྡུག་པ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ མི་ འོང་བ འི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Covetousness is an unvirtuous action, and its ripening is unattractive, ugly, and unpleasant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡིད་ མ་ ཞི་བ །_ མ་ སྦྱངས་པ འི་ བྱིས་པ་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ བརྣབ་སེམས་ ཀྱིས་ རབ་ཏུ་ བསླུས་པ་ དེ་ གཞན་ གྱི་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལ་ འཕྲལ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ རྟོག་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Covetousness fools restless and untrained, childish beings by creating a compulsive obsession with the fine circumstances of others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རོ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཡང་ དང་ ཡང་ དུ་ བྱེད །_ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྒྱུར་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ རྟག་ ཏུ་ འདོད་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ རྟག་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ གཞན་ གྱི་ ནོར་རྫས་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ མཐོང་ ན་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, one seeks to obtain their fine circumstances, repeatedly and all-encompassingly, while wishing for and craving them to the extent that the very perception of such circumstances becomes painful.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ བརྣབ་སེམས་ ཞེས་ བྱ་ སྟེ །_ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ གྱི་ དྲི་མ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is covetousness, a great stain among mental actions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ སེམས་ལས་ བྱུང་བ་ གནོད་སེམས་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$85 “How does the mental state of ill will constitute a negative course of action?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས །_ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by means of the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>!གཞན་དག་ གིས་ རྒྱུ་མ་ ཡིན་པ་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཉེས་པ འི་ གནོད་སེམས་ དང་ །_ གཞན་དག་ གི་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ འམ །_ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ མ་ཡིན་པ་ མཐོང་ ནས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They see how the illusory mental flaw of ill will may arise#21 when observing others, regardless of whether of they are excellent or not.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>!རྒྱུ་མ་ ཡིན་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འདོད་པ་ བཞིན་ བྱས་པ་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ཉེས་པ་ མི་བཟད་པ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, one might act as one pleases with regard to that illusion,#22 and so sustain an extremely severe mental flaw.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནོད་སེམས་ དེ་ ནི་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such ill will leads to the experience of life in hell.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ ལོ་ཏོག་ ཏུ་ གྱུར་པ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ སེར་བ །_ ཡང་ [95a] དག་པ འི་ ཤེས་རབ་ ཀྱི་ མིག་ གི་ མི་ འཐུན་ པར་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is like hail to the crops of virtuous qualities [F.95.a] and is antithetical to the eye of true insight.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མུན་ནག་ སྙིང་ ལ་ གནས་པ འི་ མེ་ དེ་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྲེག་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This fire within the heart of darkness burns away spiritual discipline.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མདོག་ ངན་པ འི་ རྒྱུ །_ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ སྟེགས་ གཅོད་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is a cause of ugliness and cuts through the supports for the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདི་ དང་ །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ དགྲ་ ནང་ དུ་ ཞུགས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is the enemy of both this world and the worlds to come.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ རྩེ་གཅིག་པ་ ཉིད་ འཇིག་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_ བྱམས་པ་ དང་ མི་ འཐུན་ ཞིང་ །_ འཕགས་པ འི་ བདེན་པ་ བཞི་པོ་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ དང་ །_ ཀུན་འབྱུང་ དང་ །_ ལམ་ དང་ །_ འགོག་པ་ རྣམས་ འཇིག་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It destroys one-pointedness, combats love, and demolishes the noble one’s four truths of suffering, origin, path, and cessation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནོད་སེམས་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ འི་ ཕོ་ཉ་ མཆོག་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Ill will is the supreme harbinger of life in hell.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ སྐྱེས་བུ་ དམ་པ་ དང་ །_ འཕགས་པ་ ཉན་ཐོས་ དང་ །_ ཐོས་པ་ དོན་ དུ་ གཉེར་བ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ སྤོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Ill will is therefore abandoned by all holy beings, noble hearers, and people in pursuit of learning.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ མི་ འཐུན་ པར་ གྱུར་པ་ ལྟ་བ་ ངན་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ མུན་ གནག་ སྙིང་ ལ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$86 “What is the function of wrong view, this darkness that grows in the hearts of beings in the form of negative beliefs that run counter to the sacred Dharma?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena perceive this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by seeing with the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐོག་མ་ མེད་པ འི་ དུས་ ནས་ ཞུགས་ཤིང་ སྐྱེས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Wrong view has been present and has arisen since time without beginning.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ འི་ འགྲོ་བ འི་ རྒྱུ་ སྐྱེད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is the cause of becoming a hell being, a starving spirit, or an animal.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མུན་པ་ མུན་ནག་ ཏུ་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is pitch-black darkness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྟ་བ་ ངན་པ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is a fondness for negative beliefs.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་དག་པ འི་ ལམ་ གྱི་ མི་ འཐུན་ པར་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is antithetical to the genuine path.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཚོན་ དང་ །_ མེ་ དང་ །_ དུག་ དང་ །_ གཡང་ས་ ལྟ་བུ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is like a weapon, fire, poison, and an abyss.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ རྣམ་པར་ འཇིག་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It destroys all beings.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྱིན་ ཅི་ ལོག་ ཏུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is a view that is wrong and mistaken.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ རྣམ་པ་ གཉིས་ ཏེ །_ རྐྱེན་ ཡོད་པ་ དང་ །_ ལས་ དང་ འབྲས་བུ་ ལ་ སྐུར་པ་ འདེབས་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$87  “There are two kinds of wrong view: those that accept the existence of conditions and those that deny karmic actions and results.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ རྐྱེན་ ཡོད་པ་ ནི་ བདེ་བ་ དང་ །_ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་དག་ ནི །_ དེ་དག་ ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ བྱས་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ དང་ །_ འབྲས་བུ ས་ བྱས་པ་ ནི་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To accept conditions is to claim that all happiness and suffering is the result of actions carried out by oneself.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ དང་ འབྲས་བུ་ ལ་ སྐུར་པ་ འདེབས་པ་ ནི །_ སྦྱིན་པ་ མེད་ དོ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To deny karmic actions and results is to deny the relevance of generosity, and so forth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ དེ་དག་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ མི་དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ འདི་དག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དོན་ ཐམས་ [95b] ཅད་ མེད་པར་ བྱེད་པ འི་ རྩ་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །།_།།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, as the basis of all ten unvirtuous actions, [F.95.b] wrong view functions as the fundamental destroyer of all meaningful objectives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ མི་དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ འདི་དག་ བཟློག་ ནས །_ ཟག་པ་ དང་ བཅས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པ་ དག་ གི་ ལས་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$88 “Having turned away from the path of these ten unvirtuous actions, how does one instead engage in defiled or undefiled acts?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this either through knowledge derived from hearing or by means of the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ རེ་ཞིག་ འཁོར་བ འི་ འཆིང་བ །_ ཆོས་ ཟད་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ འཆིང་བ འི་ རྒྱུ་ མི་དགེ་བ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Unvirtuous actions lead to bondage in cyclic existence and the exhaustion of Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐར་པ འི་ རྒྱུ འི་ དངོས་པོ་ ནི་ དགེ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Virtue, on the other hand, is what causes liberation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ སྤངས་པ ས །_ འཁོར་བ ར་ གཏོགས་པ འི་ སེམས་ཅན་ རྣམས་ ལ་ མི་ འཇིགས་པ་ སྦྱིན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Giving up killing, one gives freedom from fear to all the beings in cyclic existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཚེ་ འདི་ཉིད་ ལ་ བསྔགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_ དེ འི་ བཞིན་ གྱི་ མདོག་ དང་ དབང་པོ་ རྣམས་ གསལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ ཚེ་རིང་པོ ར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ ལས་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will be praised in the present life, have a beautiful countenance, enjoy bright faculties, and carry out acts that engender longevity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ སྲིན་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཤ་ཟ་ དང་ །_ གྲུལ་བུམ་ གྱི་ རིགས་ དང་ །_ གཞན་ ཡང་ སེམས་ཅན་ འཚེ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ དེ་དག་ ཀྱང་ ཉིན་མཚན་ དུ་ སྲུང་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ ཕྱི་བཞིན་ དུ་ ལྷ་ དག་ ཀྱང་ མངོན་པར་ སྲུང་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ །_ ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ལྷ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those who day and night protect even harmful creatures such as rākṣasas, piśācas, or kumbhāṇḍas of different kinds will thereafter be protected by the gods, and when they separate from their bodies, they will be born in the joyful divine realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འདོད་ ན་ ཡང་ །_ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ བརྩོན་འགྲུས་ བརྩམས་པ་ བཞིན་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If you want to experience the effect of such ripening, then know that such experience is proportionate to your diligence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ཐ་མ་ དང་ །_ འབྲིང་ དང་ །_ ཆེན་པོ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ སོ་སོ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འདོད་ ན །_ དེ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པོ་ འདིར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$89  “If one wishes to experience the minor, intermediate, or great paths of awakening, then this is how they follow.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ཉན་ཐོས་ ཀྱི་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ ཏུ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ དགྲ་བཅོམ་ པར་ གྱུར་ ནས །_ ཡོངས་སུ་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འད འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Dedication toward the awakening of a hearer will turn one into a worthy one and one will go completely beyond suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ འབྲིང་ དུ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ རང་ སངས་རྒྱས་ སུ་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Dedication toward intermediate awakening will make one a solitary buddha.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ བླ་ ན་ མེད་པ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ རྫོགས་པ འི་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ ཏུ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ཡང་ དག་པ ར་ རྫོགས་པ འི་ སངས་རྒྱས་ སུ་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If one’s dedication is toward unsurpassable and perfect awakening, one will become a perfect buddha.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིག་པ་ དང་ ཞབས་ སུ་ ལྡན་པ །_ བདེ་བ ར་ [96a] གཤེགས་པ །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་ མཁྱེན་པ །_ སྐྱེས་བུ་ འདུལ་བ འི་ ཁ་ལོ་ སྒྱུར་བ །_ བླ་ ན་ མེད་པ །_ ལྷ་ དང་ མི་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ སྟོན་པ །_ སངས་རྒྱས་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ སུ་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Endowed with knowledge and its support, one will become a blissful one, [F.96.a] a knower of the world, a steersman who tames beings, an unexcelled one, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed buddha.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཆོས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ རྩ་བ་ ནི་ སྲོག་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$90  “Life is the root of all qualities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ སྲོག་ དེ་ མངོན་པར་ སྲུང་བ་ དེས་ ནི་ བདེ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྦྱིན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Hence, protecting life is a gift that grants all forms of happiness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྦྱིན་པ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ མཆོག་ ནི་ འདི་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ སེམས་ལས་ བྱུང་བ་ སོ་སོ ར་ བསྒོམས་པ་ སྲོག་ བྱིན་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Among all forms of generosity, the mental state of wishing to give life is supreme.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ མཐོ་རིས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ འི་ མཆོག་ ནི་ འདི་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ སྲོག་ བྱིན་པ འི་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Among all forms of discipline, the discipline of giving life is the supreme way to gain rebirth in the higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ཡུལ་ གྱི་ བདེ་བ་ ཀུན་ ནས་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ སྲེད་པ འི་ རྒྱུ ར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ ཚངས་པ འམ །_ བདུད་ དམ །_ བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ དུ་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If the practice of such discipline is dedicated toward the enjoyment of objects that serve as causes of affliction and craving, then one will become Brahmā, Māra, or Śakra.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ མི འི་ བདག་ཉིད་ ཆེན་པོ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ དང་ ལྡན་པ །_ གླིང་བཞི་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If it is dedicated to becoming a great human being, then one will become a universal monarch, possessing the seven treasures and ruling the four continents.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ལྷ་མ་ ཡིན་ གྱི་ བདག་ཉིད་ ཆེན་པོ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ ལྷ་མ་ ཡིན་ གྱི་ རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If it is dedicated to becoming a great asura, one will rule the realm of the asuras.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ གྱི་ བདག་ཉིད་ ཆེན་པོ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ གྱི་ རྒྱལ་སྲིད་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If it is dedicated to becoming a great yakṣa one will rule the realm of the yakṣas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྙིང་རྗེ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འདི་ ནི་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ ས་བོན་ དུ་ གྱུར་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This great compassion is the seed of the sacred Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་བ འི་ སྐྱབས་ སུ་ གྱུར་པ །_ འཁོར་བ འི་ མུན་ གནག་ ཏུ་ ཞུགས་པ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ སྒྲོན་མ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is a protection against cyclic existence and a lamp for those who are lost in the darkness of cyclic existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ སྤོང་བ་ ཞེས་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the practice of refraining from killing.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ སྤངས་པ་ བྱམས་པ་ བསྒོམས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_ སྙིང་རྗེ འི་ རྒྱུད་ ལ་ གནས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By giving up killing one cultivates love and becomes a compassionate being.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསམས་ ནས་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ སྤངས་ ན་ གཙང་ ཞིང་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Deciding to refrain from killing brings purity and joy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གི་ ཚེ་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ བསྲུང་བ ར་ མ་ནུ ས་པ་ དེ འི་ ཚེ་ བཏང་སྙོམས་ སུ་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When one is unable to actually save others, one should remain impartial.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཚངས་པ འི་ གནས་ བཞི་ ལ་ གནས་པ འི་ རྒྱུད་ དུ་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This will make one’s mind rest in the four abodes of Brahmā.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ སྤངས་པ འི་ དགེ་བ འི་ རྩ་བ འི་ སྙིང་པོ་ ནི་ བསམ་ གྱིས་ མི་ ཁྱབ་པ་ སྟེ །_ རྣམ་པ་ གང་དང་གང་ གིས་ ཇི་ལྟ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་བ་ དེ་ལྟ་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ འགྲུབ་བོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$91 “In essence, the roots of virtue that ensue from having given up killing are inconceivable because they accomplish whatever aim one may dedicate them to in whatever applicable way.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དཔེར་ན །_ གསེར་མགར་ མཁས་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ [96b] གསེར་ བཟང་པོ་ བླངས་ ནས །_ ཇི་ལྟ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འདོད་པ་ དེ་ལྟ་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ གསེར་ དེ་ ལ་ བྱེད་ དེ །_ དེ་ལས་ རྒྱན་ ནམ །_ དེ་ལས་ བུམ་པ འམ །_ དེ་ལས་ མི འི་ གཟུགས་ སམ །_ དེ་ལས་ སངས་རྒྱས་ ཀྱི་ གཟུགས་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As an analogy, when an expert goldsmith works with fine gold, [F.96.b] he can turn it into anything he wants: ornaments, vases, human figures, or buddha figures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ བསྲུངས་ ཏེ །_ མ་ ཉམས་ ཤིང་ མ་ རལ་ ལ །_ མ་ ཞིག་ ན་ ཇི་ལྟ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་བ་ དེ་ལྟ་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ འགྲུབ་བོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Similarly, someone who guards against killing and maintains that practice unerringly without violating it may accomplish whatever aim he or she is dedicated to in whatever applicable way.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ སྤངས་པ འི་ སེམས་ཅན་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཉེ་བ ར་ གནས་ ཤིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, those who give up killing are close to the transcendence of suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ དགེ་བ འི་ བཤེས་གཉེན་ དང་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ སྤྱོད །_ སེམས་ཅན་ དེ་ བདག་ དང་ གཞན་ ལ་ ཕན་པ འི་ སྐལ་བ་ དང་ ལྡན་ ཞིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will enjoy the company of spiritual teachers and possess the fortune of benefiting themselves and others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འགྲོ་བ་ ལ་ བསོད་ནམས་ ཀྱི་ ཞིང་ དུ་ གྱུར་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They are a field of merit for hell beings, animals, and starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ འཁོར་བ་ ན་ ཆོས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Within cyclic existence they possess and follow the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཆོས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ འི་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྟོག་པ་ རྣམས་ འགྲུབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_ གྲུབ་པ་ ཡང་ བརྟན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will accomplish the ideals of those who possess the Dharma and also become stable in this accomplishment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཆོམ་རྐུན་ དང་ །_ ཆུ་ དང་ །_ མེས་ འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཐུན་མོང་ མ་ཡིན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They are not frightened or oppressed by rulers, robbers, water, or fire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདག་ཉིད་ ཉེ་བ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Rather, they find joy within.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཆོས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ འི་ འགྲན་ཟླ་ གཞན་དག་ གིས་ མི་ ནོན་པ ར་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They are seen as unassailable by other peers who possess the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ སྤང་བ ར་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, killing should be given up.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ སྤངས་པ ས་ ལེགས་པ ར་ བྱས་པ་ མཐོང་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$92 “What goodness comes of refraining from stealing?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ སྤངས་པ་ ནི །_ གཞན་ གྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བཟུང་བ འི་ ཆགས་པ་ ཆེན་པོ འི་ དྲ་བ་ ལས་ གྲོལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By giving up stealing one will escape the net of great avarice for objects owned by others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འདི་ཉིད་ ལ་ དེ་ དབུགས་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will find relief in the present life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ འམ །_ བློན་པོ འི་ ཡིད་བརྟན་ པར་ འགྱུར །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ འཁོར་ དང་ །_ ཁྱིམ་བདག་ གི་ འཁོར་ དང་ །_ རྒྱལ་རིགས་ ཀྱི་ འཁོར་ དང་ །_ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གི་ འཁོར་ དང་ །_ བྲམ་ཟེ འི་ འཁོར་ དུ་ ཡིད་བརྟན་པ་ དང་ །_ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_ སྡུག་པ་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ འོང་ཞིང་ ཚིག་ ཡོངས་སུ་ གཟུང་ [97a] བར་ འོས་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Taken into confidence by kings and ministers, as well as by courts, households, noble families, monastic congregations, and priestly gatherings, one will be regarded as delightful, dear, attractive, and authoritative.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་དག་ རྟག་ ཅིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.97.a] The enjoyments of such a person will be constant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ལ་ གནོད་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཆུ་ དང་ །_ ཆོམ་རྐུན་ དང་ །_ མེ འི་ འཇིགས་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And without bringing harm to others, one will have no fear of rulers, water, robbers, or fire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ བསམས་པ ར་ དེ་དག་ འཕྲལ་ ལ་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Unanticipated, such enjoyments will arise spontaneously.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱུང་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ ཞིང་ དང་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ དང་ །_ ལམ་བཟང་པོ་ ལ་ ཞུགས་པ་ དང་ །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ ཉེ་བ ར་ སྦྱོར་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Once these have arisen, one will be a field of merit, embody discipline, embark upon a good path, and develop close ties with worldly beings.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ཀྱི་ ལྷ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Furthermore, when separating from the body one will be born in the joyful divine realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ངེས་པ ར་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ ལམ་ གྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ ངེས་པ ར་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ་ སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ ཚངས་པ འམ །_ བདུད་ དམ །_ བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ ནམ །_ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ གླིང་བཞི་ ལ་ དབང་བ །_ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If the merit of this is dedicated by means of the path of deliverance, one will find deliverance and, in the same way as before, become a Brahmā, Māra, Śakra, or a universal monarch who rules the four continents and possesses the seven treasures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟར་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ དེ་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ རྣམས་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, those who delight in discipline will attain their respective forms of awakening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ སྤངས་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$93 “What are the effects of giving up sexual misconduct?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ སྤངས་པ་ ནི་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་བཟང་པོ་ སྤྱོད་ ཅིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Giving up sexual misconduct leads to good deeds and virtuous action.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འདི་ཉིད་ ལ་ དེ་ བསྔགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_ ཡིད་ཆེས་པ འི་ གནས་ སུ་ ཡང་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will be praised and trusted in the present life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུད་མེད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ འདུག་ ཀྱང་ དོགས་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will not feel nervous around women.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ འམ །_ བློན་པོ འི་ ཡིད་བརྟན་ པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Kings and ministers will take one into their confidence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཆུང་མ་ ནམ་ཡང་ གཞན་ གྱིས་ འཕྲོག་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ དེ འི་ རིམ་གྲོ་ བྱེད་པ ར་ བརྩོན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ་ བསམ་པ་ དང་ འཐུན་ པར་ ཡང་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One’s spouse will never be stolen by someone else, but always act with respect and in accordance with one’s own intentions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཉམ་ཐག་ པར་ གྱུར་པ་ ན་ ཡང་ ཁྱད་ དུ་ གསོད་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ ཚུལ་ དང་ མི་ འཐུན་ པར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_ གཅིག་ ལ་ གཅིག་ གནོད་པ་ བྱེད་པ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even in hard times there will not be any mockery, disrespect, or inclination to attack one another.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཆུང་མ་ དེ་ ལ་ བརྙས་པ་ བྱེད་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་མ་ དང་ སྲིང་མོ་ ལྟ་བུ ར་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ [97b] ལ་ དེ འི་ ཆུང་མ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ལ་ ཁྲོ་བ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One’s spouse will not be blamed by anyone and she will act like a mother or sister to the whole world, [F.97.b] being free from any anger at the world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ཀྱི་ ལྷ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$94 “As before, when separating from one’s body, one will take birth within the joyful divine realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གི་ ཚེ་ ལྷ་ དག་ ལས་ འཆི་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དེ འི་ ཚེ །_ ལྷ འི་ བུ་ གཞན་ ཞིག་ དེར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When later the time has come to die in that god realm, one will be reborn as another god there.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གིས་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ བྱས་པ ར་ གྱུར་ ན་ དེ་ ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ ར་ ལྷ་ གཞན་ ཞིག་ ལྷ འི་ བུ་མོ་ དེ་དག་ གི་ ནང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ་ དེ་ཡང་ དེ་ དང་ མངོན་སུམ་ དུ་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If, on the other hand, one has engaged in sexual misconduct, another god will, while one is still alive in that realm, be born among the divine maidens and become visible to them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ དང་ ལྷ་ གཞན་དག་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཏུ་ དགོད་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ འཛུམ་པ ར་ བྱེད །_ དགའ་མགུ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The divine maidens will then jest, smile, and have fun with that god.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ འཆི་བ་ ན་ དེ འི་ ཆུང་མ ས་ མཐོང་ ནས་ གཞན་ དུ་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Later, when one’s wife sees one is dying, she will abandon one to be with that other god.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྲག་དོག་ གི་ ཞགས་པ ས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བཟུང་བ་ དག་ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, caught by the shackles of envy, one will take birth as a hell being.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟེན་ ཅིང་ བསྒོམས་ ཏེ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱས་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ བར་ཆད་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Resorting to, becoming habituated to, and increasing acts of sexual misconduct is a great obstacle.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་བས་ན་ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ སྤོང་བ་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ འཛིན་ ཅིང་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ འི་ སྐལ་བ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Therefore, giving up sexual misconduct will allow one to follow the great path of virtue and gain the fortune to transcend suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ དགེ་བ འི་ ཕྱོགས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དང་ མི་ འཐུན་ པར་ གྱུར་པ འི་ བརྫུན་ སྤངས་པ ས་ དགེ་བ འི་ ཕྱོགས་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ འཛིན་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$95 “By giving up lying, which is incompatible with all virtuous inclinations, one upholds highly virtuous inclination.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འདི་ ལ་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What, then, are the ripened effects of this in this present life?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ སྤངས་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ གྱི་ མིག་ དང་ རྣ་བ འི་ ལྐོག་ ཏུ་ གྱུར་ ཀྱང་ ཡིད་ཆེས་པ འི་ གནས་ཆེན་པོ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By giving up lying one will be trusted even by people who have never seen or heard of oneself.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ནོར་རྫས་ མེད་ ན་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ དང་ རྒྱལ་པོས་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འདོད་པ་ བཞིན་ མཆོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Should one be lacking in terms of wealth, all one’s wishes will be fulfilled by both the people and the king.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ནམ་མཁའ་ ལ་ གཟའ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱུ་སྐར་ གྱི་ དབུས་ ན་ ཟླ་བ་ རབ་ཏུ་ གསལ་བ་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ ར་ སྨྲ་བ་ དེ་ རབ་ཏུ་ གསལ་ ལོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Like the moon that shines brightly in the midst of the other planets and celestial bodies, those who speak the truth will shine brightly amid all worldly people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ མཆོག་ ཏུ་ བཟང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Among all jewels, the great jewel of the truth is supreme and sublime.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལས་ སྒྲོལ་བ འི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ ར་ སྒྲོལ་བ་ ཁྱད་པར་ [98a] དུ་ འཕགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Among all that liberates us from all cycles of existence, the liberator of the truth is particularly exalted.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ངན་འགྲོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལས་ ཕྱིར་ ཟློག་པ འི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ ས་ ཕྱིར་ ཟློག་ གོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.98.a] Among all that turns us away from the lower realms, the repellent of the truth is supreme.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྒྲོན་མ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ་ སྒྲོན་མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_། ལམ་ སྟོན་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ་ ལམ་ སྟོན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Truth is the lamp of all lamps and the guide of all guides.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདུ་བྱེད་ ཀྱི་ རྫས་ འབྱུང་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ འི་ རྫས་ གཞན་ གྱི་ ནད་ འཕྲོག་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Among all forms of substance, it is the substance of truth that removes the sickness of others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྩལ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ་ རྩལ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_། སྐྱོབ་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ་ སྐྱོབ་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_། མཛའ་བཤེས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ ན་ བདེན་པ་ མཛའ་བཤེས་ ཁྱད་པར་ འཕགས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Truth is the force among all forces, the protector among all protectors, and the most exalted among all friends.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ བདེན་པ འི་ ནོར་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ འཛིན་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ ནམས་ ཀྱང་ འཁོར་བ འི་ ངན་འགྲོ་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟུང་བ་ དབུལ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$96 Those who possess the wealth of truth will never experience the poverty of falling into the lower realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ རྣམས་ དང་ ཉེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Instead, they will be close to the gods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དང་གང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ དེ་ དང་ དེར་ སྐྱེ་བ འི་ རིགས་ ཆེ་ ཞིང་ །_ གཟུགས་བཟང་པོ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Wherever such people are born they will take birth in a fine family and have an excellent physique.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ སྡུག་པ་ དང་ །_ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ འོང་བ་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་ ཡིད་ཆེས་ པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Everyone will find them appealing, delightful, attractive, and trustworthy.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ དང་ །_ ཤ་ཟ་ དག་ གིས་ མི་ མཐོང་ ལ་ གཙེ་བ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ ཤིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such people will be imperceptible to rākṣasas and piśācas, and invulnerable to their harm.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡུལ་ གཞན་ དུ་ ཕྱིན་ ན་ ཡང་ མལ་ཆ་ དང་ །_ ན་བ འི་ གསོས་ སྨན་ གྱི་ རྐྱེན་ མང་པོ་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Whenever such people travel they will find plentiful and excellent lodging and medical treatment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ འདོད་པ་ གང་དག་ ཡིད་ ལ་ བསམས་པ་ དེ་དག་ ཀྱང་ དེ་ལས་ འགྲུབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Anything they may wish for will be fulfilled.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ མི འི་ བདེ་བ་ མཆོག་ མྱོང་ ནས་ གལ་ཏེ་ འཆི་བ འི་ དུས་ བྱེད་ ན །_ དེ་ ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ ཚེ་རིང་བ་ དང་ །_ ཤིན་ཏུ་ རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ ཆེ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཤིན་ཏུ་ གནས་ མཐོ་བ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such people will experience supreme human happiness and, when the time of their death comes, they will separate from their bodies only to be born in the joyous divine realms, where they will enjoy extremely long lives, tremendous miraculous powers, and an exceedingly exalted status.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ གལ་ཏེ་ རྣམ་པར་ བྱང་བ་ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པ འི་ ལམ་ གྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྔོ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ན །_ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ འི་ མཐ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Just as before, if one dedicates this in a pure and undefiled manner, it will bring the liberation of transcending suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ །_ ཕྲ་མ་ སྤངས་པ ས་ ཚེ་ འདི་ དང་ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ ར་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$97 “As one practices virtuous actions, what are the effects of giving up divisive talk, as they ripen in this life and beyond?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས །_ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྲ་མ་ [98b] སྤངས་པ ས་ ཚེ་ འདི་ ལ་ལ ས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ནི་ མཛའ་བཤེས་ དང་ །_ གཉེན་འདབ་ དང་ །_ རྩ་ལག་ དང་ །_ ཆུང་མ་ དང་ །_ བྲན་ ཕོ་ དང་ །_ བྲན་མོ་ དང་ །_ ལས་ བྱེད་པ་ དང་ །_ ཞོ་ཤས་འཚོ་བ་ བརྟན་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The ripened effect that is experienced in this life due to giving up divisive talk [F.98.b] is to have steadfast friends, acquaintances, relatives, spouses, male servants, female servants, workers, and employees.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ གྱིས་ ཁ་ དྲང་ དུ་ མི་ རུང་ ཞིང་ བཤེས་པ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཕོ་བྲང་ འཁོར་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ མི་ འཐུན་པ་ དག་ གིས་ དབྱེ་བ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will not be led along by others, and none among one’s friends, the members of the royal court, or discordant relatives will be able to create any factions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ནོར་ དང་ བྲལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ ནོར་ དང་ བྲལ་བ ར་ གྱུར་ ན་ ཡང་ མི་ གཏོང་ ཞིང་མུ་ གེ་ དང་ །_ འབྲོག་ དགོན་པ་ དང་ །_ རི་ དང་ །_ གཡང་ས་ དང་ །_ གནས་སྐབས་ མི་ འཐུན་ པར་ ཆུད་ ན་ ཡང་ མི་ གཏོང་ སྟེ ནམས་ ཀྱང་ འབྲལ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Should one lose one’s wealth, one will not become destitute. Neither will one suffer any loss when encountering famine, isolated places, mountains, precipices, or temporary adversities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ དེ འི་ སྐྱོན་ སྨྲ་ ན་ དེ་དག་ དེ་ ལ་ ཐབས་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ ཉན་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Should one criticize others, one will not be persecuted.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཕོ་བྲང་ འཁོར་ དུ་ བརྟན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ཆུ་ དང་ །_ མཚོན་ཆ་ དང་ །_ མི་ མཛའ་བ འི་ འཇིགས་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>At the royal court one will prevail, and one will not have any fear of water, weapons, or animosity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དྲི་མ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཕྲ་མ་ སྤངས་པ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ དེ་དག་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the qualities associated with giving up the great stain that is divisive talk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཤི་བ འི་ འོག་ ཏུ་ ཡང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ལྷ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Having died and separated from the body, one will be born in the joyful and divine higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དེ ར་ ཡང་ ལྷ འི་ རིས་ འཐུན་པ འི་ ལྷ་མོའི་ ཚོགས་ མང་པོ་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཆགས་པ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྐོར་ ཅིང་ མེ་ཏོག་ ཕྲེང་ དང་ །_ ཕྱེ་མ་ དང་ །_ བྱུག་པ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ ཐོགས་པ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ འི་ མཆོག་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>There great gatherings of affectionate goddesses of similar ilk will please one with flower garlands, colored powders, perfumes, and jewelry.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ གལ་ཏེ་ ཕྲ་མ་ སྤངས་པ་ རྣམ་པར་ བྱང་བ་ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པ འི་ བསམ་གཏན་ གྱི་ ལམ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ་ ཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Just as before, if one’s relinquishment of divisive talk is dedicated in a pure and undefiled manner, one will achieve the transcendence of suffering through the path of undefiled concentration.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྐྱོ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$98 “Speaking harsh words is an unvirtuous action that saddens the entire world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ སྤངས་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What are the effects that ripen by giving up harsh words?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་རྩུབ་པོ་ སྤངས་པ་ དེ་ ནི་ དགེ་བ་ མཐོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those who give up harsh words come to witness what is virtuous.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དྲང་པོ འི་ རང་བཞིན་ དང་ །_ དབུགས་དབྱུང་བ འི་ གནས་ [99a] དང་ །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ རྟོགས་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such people are naturally honest and a source of comfort. [F.99.a] They are esteemed by the whole world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་འཇམ་ ཞིང་ དེས་ ལ་ སྙན་པ་ དང་ །_ གཞན་ ལ་ རྣམ་པར་ འཚེ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ དབུགས་ འབྱུང་བ་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They speak gently and pleasantly, while refraining from harming anyone and bringing everyone comfort.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ རྒྱང་རིང་པོ་ ནས་ མཐོང་ ནས །_ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ ཉེ་བ ར་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When such people are seen in the distance, everyone wants to approach them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཛའ་བཤེས་ ཀྱང་ མང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ ནོར་རྫས་ མེད་ ན་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཀུན་ དེ འི་ བྲན་ དང་ འདྲ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such people have many friends, and even if they lack material wealth, everyone will act like servants toward them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ དེ་ལས་ གཞན་ ཞིག་ གིས་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ བྱུང་ ན་ ཡང་ དེ་དག་ གིས་ དེ་ ནམས་ ཀྱང་ གཏོང་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if they should happen to disturb anyone, others will not abandon them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ དོན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ མེད་པར་ ཉེ་བ ར་ སྒྲུབ་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>All their objectives will be accomplished without any trouble.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ མི་ མཛའ་བ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཆུ་ དང་ །_ མེ་ དང་ །_ མཚོན་ གྱིས་ འཇིགས་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such people will never have to fear animosity, the authorities, water, fire, or weapons.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ཀྱི་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When they later separate from their bodies, they will take birth among the gods in the joyful and divine higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེར་ སྐྱེས་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ ཚིག་ གི་ རྒྱུ་ འཇམ་པ་ དང་ །_ ཕན་པ་ དང་ །_ སྙན་པ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ ཆེ་བ་ དང་ །_ མཐུ་ ཆེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even then, their words will be gentle, beneficial, and delightful, and they will possess great miracles and great powers.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ གལ་ཏེ་ ངེས་པ ར་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ བསམ་གཏན་ བདེ་བ འི་ གནས་ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ གསུམ་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As before, if this is dedicated in an undefiled manner toward the blissful abode of the concentration of deliverance, one will attain the three kinds of awakening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ སྤངས་པ ས་ ཚེ་ འདི་ ལ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ ཕྱི་མ་ ལ་ གང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$99 “Which effects of giving up the unvirtuous action of chatter will be attained in this life, and what form of rebirth does such relinquishment lead to?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ཀྱལ་པ་ སྤངས་པ་ ནི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ན་ རིགས་ བཙུན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ དེ་ བཀུར་བ ར་ ཡང་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those who give up chatter will be of a pure family and held in high esteem.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ སྔ་ཕྱི་ འབྲེལ་བར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ ཚིག་ ལ་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Their words will be meaningful and greatly appreciated by everyone.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ སྐྱོན་ གྱིས་ སུ་ ཡང་ རྣམ་པར་ འཚེ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will never be punished for verbal mistakes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚིག་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ འབྲེལ་ ཅིང་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ན་ བཙུན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Their speech will be perfectly articulate and respected in the world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དལ་བ་ དང་ །_ སྙན་པ་ དང་ །_ ཁོང་ དུ་ ཆུད་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ དང་ །_ འཇམ་པ་ དང་ །_ ཟབ་མོ འི་ རྒྱུ འི་ ཚུལ་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ཉིད་ དང་ མི་འགལ་བ འི་ གཏམ་ སྨྲ་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, their words will be calm, beautiful, clear, meaningful, gentle, profound, and never in conflict with the way things are.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་ ན་ བླ་མ་ དང་ [99b] འདྲ་བ ར་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ ནོར་རྫས་ བརྟན་པ ར་ ཡང་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The world will regard them as teachers [F.99.b] and their wealth will be secure.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོག་པ ར་ སྤངས་པ་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཕ་རོལ་ དག་ གིས་ ཡོན་ཏན་ དུ་ འཛིན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ དེས་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ དག་ གཟུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Others will acknowledge their relinquishment of error as an excellent quality, and they will be inspired to uphold such virtues themselves.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When they separate from their bodies, such people will take birth in the joyful higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེར་ སྐྱེས་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ ལྷ འི་ བུ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སེམས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ ཆེ་བ་ དང་ །_ ལྷ འི་ བདེ་བ་ དཔེ་མེད་པ་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Once born there they will be held in regard by all the gods. Their miraculous powers will be great, and they will enjoy unparalleled divine pleasures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ གལ་ཏེ་ རྣམ་པར་ བྱང་བ་ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པ འི་ བསམ་གཏན་ གྱི་ བདེ་བ ར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ གསུམ་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As before, if this is dedicated toward the blissful concentration of undefiled purification, one will achieve the three kinds of awakening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ དང་ །_ ངག་ གི་ རྣམ་པ་ བཞི་ མི་དགེ་བ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ སྤངས་ ན་ མཐ ར་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$100 “Thus, by giving up the three physical and four verbal forms of unvirtuous action one will eventually transcend suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྒྱུ་ ཡིན་ ལ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ན་ ཡང་ བསྔགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ ནང་ དུ་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such causes of virtuous action will also yield praise within the world and rebirth among the gods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལུས་ དང་ ངག་གི་ལས་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ གྱུར་པ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ འི་ རྒྱུ་ ནི་ རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་བ་ ནང་ གི་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ གྱུར་པ་ རྗེས་སུ་ མཐོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These are the causal factors and ripened effects of authentic physical and verbal action as perceived by spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena and are authentic within.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ དགེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$101 “How may mental action be virtuous?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ མི་དགེ་བ་ དེ་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་པོ་ དེ་དག་ ཟློག་པ ས་ དགེ་བ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཚེ་ འདི་ ལ་ བདེ་བ་ གནས་པ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By stopping the three unvirtuous mental acts one will, as the result of such virtue, experience happiness in this life and, when separating from the body, take birth among the gods in the joyful higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ འཁོར་བ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ བྱུང་ ན་ དེ་ རྒྱུ་ དེས་ ཕུང་པོ་ ལྷག་མ་ མེད་པ འི་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ འི་ དབྱིངས་ སུ་ འཇུག་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Furthermore, if one becomes disenchanted with cyclic existence, it will cause one to enter the field of nirvāṇa without any remainder of the aggregates.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡིད་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ ནི་ རྣམ་པ་ གསུམ་ སྟེ །_ བརྣབ་སེམས་ དང་ །_ གནོད་སེམས་ དང་ །_ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$102 “The three mental acts are covetousness, ill will, and wrong view.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ བརྣབ་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ ས་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཞིག་ འབྱུང་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Among these three unvirtuous courses of action, what effects will be ripened by specifically giving up covetousness?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་ [100a] པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing [F.100.a] or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བརྣབ་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ་ ནི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འམ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ བློན་པོ འི་ ནོར་རྫས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པ་ མང་པོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ གང་ ལ་ ཡང་ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ དབྲོག་པ འི་ དོན་ དུ་ སེམས་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By giving up covetousness one will not harbor any intent to take possession of the diverse and abundant wealth of kings or royal ministers.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ནོར་རྫས་ གཞིག་ ཏུ་ སྟོར་ ན་ ཡང་ གཞན་ གྱིས་ རྙེད་ ཅིང་ དེ་ ལ་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ དེ་ དང་ །_ གཙོ་བོ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ ཞིག་ ན་ ཡང་ སླར་ སྦྱིན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Should the wealth of such a person be lost, those who find it will return it, even if they are in a superior position.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ནོར་ དང་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ ལྡན་ ཞིང་ གཞན་དག་ གིས་ མི་ ཐུབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those who abandon covetousness will always be wealthy and never subjugated by others.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When they separate from their bodies, such people will take birth among the gods in the joyful higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེར་ སྐྱེས་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ ལྷ་ དང་ ལྷ་མ་ ཡིན་ དུ་ གཡུལ་འགྱེད་པ འི་ ཚེ་ལྷ་མ་ ཡིན་ གང་ གིས་ ཀྱང་ ཡོངས་སུ་ ཐུབ་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, born as gods, no asura will be able to defeat them in the battles between gods and asuras.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྡེག་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_ རྣམ་པར་ ཐོ་ འཚམ་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>No asura will be able to strike them, or even simply mock them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ ལས་ རྣམ་པར་ ཕྱེ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ ལྷ འི་ བུ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ འདོད་པ་ དང་ །_ སྡུག་པ་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ འོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will never be shunned by the other gods, who will always regard them as agreeable, delightful, and attractive.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྒྲ་ དང་ །_ རེག་བྱ་ དང་ །_ རོ་ དང་ །_ གཟུགས་ དང་ །_ དྲི་ སྡུག་པ་ དཔེ་མེད་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will experience unparalleled sounds, textures, tastes, forms, and scents.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྔ་མ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ གལ་ཏེ་ ངེས་པ ར་ འབྱུང་བ་ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པ འི་ བསམ་གཏན་ གྱི་ འབྲས་བུ འི་ ལམ་ དུ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ གསུམ་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As before, if this is dedicated toward the effect of the undefiled concentration of deliverance, one will attain the three kinds of awakening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ གནོད་སེམས་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ སྤངས་པ ས་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$103 “What effects of virtuous action will be attained by giving up the unvirtuous action of ill will?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནོད་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ ས་ ཚེ་ འདི་ཉིད་ ལ་ འབྱོར་པ་ དང་ བདེ་བ ར་ གནས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By giving up ill will, one will be wealthy and happy in the present life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ འོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Everybody will regard one with joy and delight.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕ་རོལ་ གྱིས་ འཇིགས་ ཤིང་ ཉམ་ང་བ་ མི་བཟད་པ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དང་ རྣམ་པར་ གཙེ་བ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ ཤིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nobody will be able to inflict great and unbearable terror, misfortune, or harm.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ འཁོར་ གྱི་ འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆོམ་རྐུན་ དང་ །_ གཡང་ས འི་ འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ མེ འི་ འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ གནོད་པ འི་ འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ གཡོ འི་ འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆུ འི་ འཇིགས་ [100b] པ་ དང་ །_ འཇིགས་པ་ དུ་མ་ ཉམ་ང་བ་ དག་ དང་ བྲལ་ ཞིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will not have to fear the authorities, robbers and thieves, falling into an abyss, other people, injury, deceit, floods, or many other such unpleasant terrors.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིགས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཉམ་ང་བ་ དག་ ལས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ ཐར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.100.b] Thus one will be free from fear and misfortune.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ སྡུག་པ་ དང་ །_ མཆོག་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Everybody will look upon one with appreciation and delight.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྡིག་པ འི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ དང་ །_ དགེ་བ འི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ལ་ བུ་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ དང་ འདྲ་བ ར་ སྡུག་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Everyone, whether evil or good, will show one affection as if one were their own child or sibling.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$104 “When separating from the body, one will take birth among the gods in the joyful higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེར་ ཡང་ རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ ཆེ་བ་ དང་ །_ མཐུ་ ཆེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ གཟུགས་ དང་ །_ སྒྲ་ དང་ །_ རེག་བྱ་ འདོད་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འབྱོར་པ་ ལ་ གནས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>There, one will master great miraculous feats and powers, and enjoy a wealth of delightful forms, sounds, and textures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགའ་བ འི་ ཚལ་ དང་ །_ ཡོངས་སུ་ འདུ་བ་ དང་ །_ རྣམ་པར་ མཛེས་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will enjoy delightful parks, perfectly arrayed and of the most beautiful kind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤིང་ རྟ་ སྣ་ཚོགས་ ཀྱི་ ཚལ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྣམས་ སུ་ ལྷ འི་ བུ་མོ འི་ ཚོགས་ ཀྱིས་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྐོར་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ དེ འི་ ལུས་ དང་ །_ ངག་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ ལ་ ལྷ་ གང་ གིས་ ཀྱང་ རྣམ་པར་ གཙེ་བ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ ཤིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In sprawling gardens filled with delights one will be the center of attention for great gatherings of goddesses, and no god will be able to bring any harm upon one’s body, voice, or mind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ལྷ་ འབུམ་ སྙེད་ དག་ གིས་ དགའ་བ་ སྐྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_ ལྷ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ གྱི་ འདོད་པ་ དང་ །_ སྡུག་པ་ དང་ །_ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཡིད་ དུ་ འོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Instead, hundreds of thousands of gods will make one happy, and one will be as successful, attractive, happy, and appealing as Śakra, king of the gods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ དང་ ལྷ་མ་ ཡིན་ གྱི་ གཡུལ་འགྱེད་པ འི་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ དག་ ཀྱང་ མེད་ ཅིང་ འཁྲུག་པ་ དག་ དང་ འབྲལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Never afflicted by the warfare between gods and asuras, one will remain free from all conflicts.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ ངེས་པ ར་ འབྱུང་བ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ལས་ འདས་པ འི་ ལམ་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ མེད་པར་ ཡོངས་སུ་ བསྔོ་ ན །_ དེ་ ལྷ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དེ་ནས་ ཤི་ ནས་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ གླིང་བཞི་ ལ་ དབང་བ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ ལ་ཉེ་ བར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་མ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$105 “When this is dedicated without affliction toward the supramundane path of deliverance, one will, after dying as a god, become a universal monarch who holds sway over the four continents and partakes of the seven treasures. Those seven treasures are as follows:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུད་མེད་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ནི་ དེ འི་ བུད་མེད་ ཀྱི་ ལུས་ ལས་ ཙན་དན་ དང་ སྤོས་ འབྱུང་ ཞིང་ཁ་ ནས་ ཨུད་པ་ ལ འི་ དྲི་ འབྱུང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$106 (1) The precious lady whose body emits a scent of sandalwood and incense powder, while her mouth is redolent of blue lotuses.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱ་ ཀ་ ལིང་ ག་ ལྟར་ རེག་ ན་ བདེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>She is as delightful to touch as the kaliṅga bird.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱ་ ཀ་ ལིང་ ག་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ནི་ རྒྱ་མཚོ འི་ གླིང་ ལ་ གནས་པ འི་ བྱ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is a bird inhabiting islands in the ocean that has such power that whoever touches it is freed from physical discomfort.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ འདི འི་ མཐུ ས་ གང་ ལ་ རེག་པ་ ཉིད་ ཀྱི་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_ གླིང་ དེ་ ན་ གནས་པ འི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ བཀྲེས་པ་ དང་ །_ སྐོམ་པ་ དང་ །_ མྱ་ངན་ དང་ བྲལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, the people who live on those islands are free from all hunger, thirst, and ailments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུད་མེད་ དེ་ལྟ་ བུ་ དེ་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོས་ མཐོང་ ནས་ གྲང་བ འི་ དུས་ སུ་ ནི་ དྲོ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ དྲོ་བ འི་ དུས་ སུ་ ནི་ [101a] བསིལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When the universal monarch beholds the precious lady, who is similar to that kaliṅga bird, the sight of her warms him during winter and cools him during summer.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ མི་ གཞན་ གང་ གིས་ ཀྱང་ རེག་པ ར་ བྱ་བ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.101.a] All the while, no one but the monarch himself is allowed to touch her.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ གནོད་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ འི་ མཐུ ས་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཞུགས་པ་ དགེ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ རྟོགས་པ འི་ མི་ དེ་དག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱིས་ མ་ དང་ སྲིང་མོ་ ལྟར་ མཐོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As a result of having given up ill will, this precious lady pursues virtuous actions such that anyone who understands virtue will regard her as their mother or sister.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ དེ འི་ ཡིད་ དུ་ འོང་ཞིང་ དེ་ ལ་ གུས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ་ དེ འི་ སྙིང་ དུ་ སྡུག་པ་ དང་ །_ རྟག་ ཏུ་ བདེ་བ འི་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The monarch is dear to her and she treats him with respect. She loves him and follows him joyfully.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུད་མེད་ ཀྱི་ སྐྱོན་ རྣམ་པ་ ལྔ་ སྤངས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“The precious lady is free of the following five flaws of a woman:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེས་པ་ གཞན་ ལ་ སེམས་པ་ དང་ །_ སེར་སྣ་ དང་ །_ མི་རིགས་ པར་ ཆགས་པ་ དང་ །_ མི་རིགས་པ འི་ གནས་ ལ་ རྗེས་སུ་ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཁྱིམ་ཐབ་ ཀྱི་ སྲོག་ གཅད་པ ར་ འཛིན་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>having interest in other men, being stingy, having unreasonable attachments, taking inappropriate pleasures, and killing the lord of the household.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུད་མེད་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ལྔ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Instead the precious lady has these five qualities:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསམ་པ་ དང་ འཐུན་ པར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ བུ་ མང་པོ་ བཙའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ རིགས་ འཐུན་ པར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ སྲིད་ མཐོ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ ཁྱིམ་ཐབ་ བུད་མེད་ གཞན་ ལ་ སེམས་ ན་ ཕྲག་དོག་ མི་ བྱེད་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>she is obliging, bears many sons, is friendly, is of high status, and is not jealous when the lord of the household shows interest in other women.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ བུད་མེད་ ཆེན་ མོ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གསུམ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>She also possesses three further qualities of great women:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ ཚིག་ ཅལ་ཅོལ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དང་ །_ ཁྱིམ་ཐབ་ མེད་ ཀྱང་ སྒྲ་ དང་ །_ དྲི་ དང་ །_ རོ་ དང་ །_ རེག་བྱ་ དག་ གི་ དབང་ དུ་ མི་འགྱུར་བ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>she refrains from idle talk, avoids wrong views, and does not fall under the power of sounds, smells, tastes, or textures, even when her husband is absent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ རྒྱུ་ དེས་ ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ བདེ་འགྲོ་ མཐོ་རིས་ ཀྱི་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As the result of this, once she separates from her body, she is born among the gods in the joyful higher realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ བུད་མེད་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ལ་ཉེ་ བར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is the precious lady belonging to the universal monarch. $107</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ གནོད་སེམས་ ཀྱི་ དྲི་མ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སྤངས་པ ས་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ ས་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ ར་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(2) “What else characterizes the universal monarch, an attainment that is due to the ripening of the virtuous action of relinquishing the great stain of ill will?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ གྱི་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྒྱུ་ འཐུན་པ་ གནོད་སེམས་ ཆེན་པོ་ སྤངས་པ ས །_ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ གཉིས་པ་ ནོར་བུ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ལ་ཉེ་ བར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By giving up severe ill will, which is the concordant cause for other unvirtuous actions, one will come to enjoy the second treasure, the precious jewel.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཡོན་ [101b] ཏན་ བརྒྱད་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.101.b] Such a jewel is endowed with eight qualities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ མཚན་མོ་ རབ་ཏུ་ གསལ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ སྟོན་ཀ འི་ ཟླ་བ་ ཉ་བ་ ནི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It shines at night, like the full moon in autumn.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྟོན་ཀ་ འོད་གསལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ ནོར་བུ་ ཡང་ མཚན་མོ འི་ མུན་པ་ མུན་ནག་ དག་ ལ་ དཔག་ཚད་ བརྒྱ ར་ འོད་ འབྱུང་ ཞིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Just like the radiant autumn moon, the precious jewel illumines the darkest of nights and it bathes everything within a hundred leagues in its light.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཉིན་པ ར་ ཚ་བ ས་ གདུངས་པ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ ནི་ འོད་ བསིལ་བ་ འབྱུང་ སྟེ ཚ་བ་ སེལ་བར་ བྱེད་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those tormented by heat during the day are cooled by the jewel’s soothing light.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གཅིག་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, cooling others is the jewel’s first quality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གཉིས་པ་ ནི་ གང་ གི་ ཚེ་ ལམ་ དུ་ ཞུགས་པ་ ལ་ ཆུ་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ དེ འི་ ཚེ །_ སྐོམ་པ ས་ གདུངས་པ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ ཆུ་ཆེན་པོ་ ཡན་ལག་ བརྒྱད་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ་ དེས་ སྐོམ་པ་ དེ་དག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སེལ་བར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As for the second quality, when travelers suffer from thirst, rivers of water endowed with eight qualities will gush forth from the jewel, quenching everyone’s thirst.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གཉིས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is the jewel’s second quality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གསུམ་པ་ ནི་ གང་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོས་ བསམས་པ་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ་ལས་ འབྱུང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Third, whatever the monarch may want, the jewel will provide.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གསུམ་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is its third quality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ བཞི་པ་ ནི །_ ཡན་ལག་ བརྒྱད་ པར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ དེ འི་ ཆ་རེ་ རེས་ འོད་ ཀྱི་ ཁ་དོག་ སྣ་ཚོགས་ གཏོང་ སྟེ །_ སྔོན་པོ་ དང་ །_ སེར་པོ་ དང་ །_ དཀར་པོ་ དང་ །_ དམར་པོ་ དང་ །_ བཙོད་ ཀ འི་ ཁ་དོག་ ལྟ་བུ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Fourth, the jewel has eight facets, and from each one of them shines multicolored light: blue, yellow, white, red, and the color of madder.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ལྔ་པ་ ནི་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ་ གང་ ན་ འདུག་པ་ དཔག་ཚད་ བརྒྱ ར་ ཉེ་བ་ དག་ གི་ ནད་མེད་ པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Fifth, all diseases will be healed within a hundred leagues of the jewel.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྟག་ ཏུ་ ཡིད་ མཉམ་པ ར་ གཞག་པ་ དང་ དེ འི་ འདོད་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལས་ ཇི་ལྟ་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ འབྲས་བུ་ མེད་པར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The minds of everyone will enter equipoise, and no wish will go unfulfilled.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ དྲུག་པ་ ནི་ ཀླུ་ ངན་པ ས་ ཆར་ མི་བཟད་པ་ མངོན་པར་ དབབ་པ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Sixth, the jewel prevents evil nāgas from causing calamities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ བདུན་པ་ ནི་ མྱ་ ངམ་ དང་ །_ གཡང་ས་ དང་ །_ དགོན་པ་ དང་ །_ ཤིང་ ལྗོན་པ་ དང་ །_ ཡུལ་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ རྣམས་ ཤིང་ ལྗོན་པ་ དང་ །_ མཚེའུ་ དང་ །_ ཚལ་ དང་ །_ པད་མ་ དང་ །_ ནགས་ཚལ་ དང་ །_ ནེའུ་གསིང་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Seventh, those lost in deserts, ravines, and wilderness, and those who lack trees or a place to stay, will all find perfect trees, ponds, lotuses, forests, and meadows.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ནོར་བུ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ བརྒྱད་པ་ ནི་ མི་གང་ ཡང་ དུས་ མ་ཡིན་པ ར་ འཆི་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ འི་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The jewel’s eighth quality is that it prevents untimely death among humans as well as rebirth in the animal realm.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དུད་ [102a] འགྲོ འི་ འགྲོ་བ་ དག་ གིས་ ཀྱང་ གནོད་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_། མི་ འཐུན་ པས་ ཡང་ མི་ འཐུན་པ་ ལ་ གནོད་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ ནེའུ་ལེ་ དང་ །_ སྦྲུལ་ ལྟ་བུ་ སྟེ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.102.a] Also, animals will not harm each other, even if they belong to opposing species, as in the case of mongooses and snakes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡོན་ཏན་ ཆེན་པོ་ བརྒྱད་པོ་ དེ་དག་ དང་ ལྡན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, the jewel is endowed with these eight great qualities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ དེ འི་ གནོད་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ནི་ དེ འི་ བུ་ ཡང་ སྟོང་ ཐམ་པ ར་ འབྱུང་ སྟེ །_ དཔའ་ ཞིང་ རྟུལ་ཕོད་ ལ་ ཡན་ལག་ མཆོག་ གི་ གཟུགས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ །_ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ སྡེ་ མངོན་པར་ འཇོམས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Moreover, due to the ripening of the universal monarch’s practice of giving up ill will, he will father a thousand sons, each of them bold and heroic, endowed with supreme physiques, conquerors of enemy armies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསམ་པ འི་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ །_ ཆོས་ དང་ ལྡན་ ཞིང་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>All of them will follow through on their plans, be endowed with the Dharma, and act in accordance with the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིགས་ འཐུན་པ །_ འཁོར་ གྱི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དགའ་ ཞིང་ རང་བཞིན་ གྱིས་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཆགས་པ་ དག་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will be in harmony with their family, and everyone around them will regard them with natural joy and affection.$108</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ གནོད་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ ས་ གསུམ་པ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འབྱུང་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(3) “How does the precious wheel, which is the third result of giving up ill will, manifest within the world?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ བརྟགས་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ལྔ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They perceive a precious wheel endowed with five qualities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ འཛམ་བུ འི་ ཆུ་བོ འི་ གསེར་ ལས་ བྱས་པ །_ ཚད་ དཔག་ཚད་ ལྔ་ བརྒྱ་ ཡོད་པ །_ རྩིབས་ སྟོང་ ཡོད་ ཅིང་ །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ན་ ཉི་མ་ གཉིས་པ་ ལྟ་བུ ར་ རྣམ་པར་ མཛེས་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ ནི་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ དང་པོ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As for the first quality, the wheel is made of gold from the Jambu River, measures five hundred leagues, has a thousand spokes, and shines beautifully, like a second sun in the world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གཉིས་པ་ ནི་ ནམ་མཁའ་ ལ་ དཔག་ཚད་ འབུམ་ དུ་ ཉི་མ་ གཅིག་ གིས་ ཐོགས་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྲོ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The second quality is that the wheel travels unhindered through the sky, crossing a hundred thousand leagues in a single day.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ གསུམ་པ་ ནི་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ནུབ་ ཀྱི་ བ་ལང་ སྤྱོད་ དང་ །_ ཤར་ གྱི་ ལུས་འཕགས་པོ་ དང་ །_ བྱང་ གི་ སྒྲ་ མི་ སྙན་ དང་ །_ རྒྱལ་ཆེན་ བཞི འི་ ལྷ འི་ གནས་ གང་ དུ་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ འདོད་པ་ དེ་ དང་ དེར་ ནམ་མཁའ་ ལ་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རྩིབས་ སྟོང་ ཡོད་པ ས་ འགྲོ་ ཞིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Third, whether the universal king wishes to go to Godānīya in the west, Videha in the east, Kuru in the north, or to any of the divine realms of the Four Great Kings, the wheel with its thousand spokes travels ahead of him in the sky.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ མཐུ ས་ དེ འི་ དཔུང་ གི་ ཚོགས་ ཡན་ལག་ བཞི་པ་ གླང་པོ་ དང་ །_ རྟ་ དང་ །_ ཤིང་རྟ་ དང་ །_ རྐང་ཐང་བ་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཏུ་ ནམ་མཁའ་ ལ་ འགྲོ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>By the power of the precious wheel his entire army with its four divisions of elephants, horses, chariots, and infantry will follow after, traversing the sky.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ [102b] ཡང་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ བཞི་པ་ ནི །_ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ གང་ མི་ ཐོས་པ་ དེ་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དེས་ གྲོགས་ བྱས་ ཏེ་ ཐོས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.102.b] Fourth, the precious wheel articulates and makes audible all that the universal monarch cannot hear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ལྔ་པ་ ནི་ སྔོ་བ་ གང་ཡང་ མེད་ དེ །_ ཆོས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ལ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འམ །_ བློན་པོ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ གྲོགས་པོ ས་ མཐོང་ མ་ ཐག་ ཏུ་ དེ་དག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འབུལ་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The fifth quality is that, as soon as they see him, all kings and ministers who support the Dharma will without any hesitation offer themselves to the monarch, who is endowed with the Dharma and follows the Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ འཁོར་ལོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ལྔ་ དང་ ལྡན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the wheel’s fifth quality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཆེན་པོ་ གསུམ་པ་ བཤད་ ཟིན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This concludes the explanation of the third royal treasure.$109</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ གནོད་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ འི་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ མཐའ་ སྤྱད་པ་ དག་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ བཞི་པ་ གླང་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ དུ་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(4) “How does the universal monarch’s precious elephant manifest in the world to those who pursue the virtuous practice of giving up ill will?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆོས་ དང་ ལྡན་ ཞིང་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ འཇུག་པ འི་ གླང་པོ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ནི་ ཅང་ཤེས་པ །_ མཆོག་ ཏུ་ བཀའ་ མཉན་པ །_ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ སྡེ་ ལས་ རྒྱལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A universal monarch who is endowed with the Dharma and follows the Dharma will possess a purebred and perfectly obedient elephant that is victorious against his enemies in battle.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡན་ལག་ བདུན་ ལེགས་པ ར་ གནས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The elephant is endowed with seven perfect appendages:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ རྐང་ལག་ བཞི་ དང་ མཇུག་མ་ མ་ ཟེགས་པ་ དང་ །_ རླིག་པ་ མདོམས་ ཀྱི་ གནས་ ན་ འདུག་པ་ དང་ །_ སྣ་ ལེགས་པ ར་ གནས་པ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>four legs, a tail that does not hang down, a penis in its groin, and a well-poised trunk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ དེ འི་ ཡན་ལག་ བདུན་ དག་ས འི་ སྟེང་ ན་ ལེགས་པ ར་ རབ་ཏུ་ གནས་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With these attributes the precious elephant stands firmly on the ground.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྟོབས་ ཆེ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ རང་བཞིན་ གྱིས་ གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ སྟོང་ གི་ སྟོབས་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ འཛིན་པ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is powerful and possesses the strength of one thousand normal elephants.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྐན་ འཇམ་པ་ དང་ ལྡན་ ཞིང་ མདོག་ དཀར་བ་ ཁ་བ་ དང་ དངུལ་ གྱི་ མདོག་ ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Its tusks are smooth and of a snowy white, silvery color.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ གྱི་ གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ལ །_ གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ གཞན་དག་ དེ འི་ དྲི་ ཚོར་ ནས་ མདུན་ དུ་ འདུག་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It resembles the elephant of Śakra, and as soon as they smell it no other elephants can stand before it.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནས་ གསུམ་ དུ་ གཡུལ་འགྱེད་ པར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ ཆུ་ དང་ །_ སྐམ་ས་ དང་ །_ བར་སྣང་ ལ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The elephant can battle in three environments: water, dry land, and the sky.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤུགས་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ ཉིན་ གཅིག་ གིས་ འཛམ་བུ འི་ གླིང་ ལན་ གསུམ་ དུ་ [103a] སྐོར་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With its perfect powers it can circle the outskirts of Jambudvīpa three times in a day.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐུད་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ དཀྲིར་ རུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ་ གང་ གི་ ཚེ་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ གླང་པོ་ ཅང་ཤེས་ ལ་ ཞོན་པ་ དེ འི་ ཚེ་ སེམས་ དང་ འཐུན་ པར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ གང་ དུ་ སེམས་ འཇུག་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དེར་ གླང་པོ་ ཅང་ཤེས་པ་ དེ་ མ་ བསྐུལ་ ཀྱང་ འཇུག་ གོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.103.a] The elephant can be led along by a rope, but whenever the universal monarch rides it, this purebred will tune into the monarch’s thoughts and go wherever he wishes without being otherwise instructed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དལ་ གྱིས་ འགྲོ་ ཞིང་ འགྱིང་བ ས་ སྤྱི་བོ་ བསྐྱོད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The precious elephant moves leisurely, turning its head with majestic poise.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནོད་པ་ མེད་ ཅིང་ འཁྲུག་པ་ མེད་ ལ །_ སྡུག་པ་ དང་ མཛེས་པ ར་ འགྲོ་བ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Without causing any harm or disturbance, it moves with delightful beauty.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱིས་པ འི་ ནང་ དུ་ སོང་ ན་ ཡང་ བྱིས་པ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ འཇིགས་ པར་ མི་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Even if it should come into the midst of young children it will not cause any fear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལམ་སྲང་ དང་ །_ བཞི་མདོ་ དང་ །_ བ་གམ་ གྱི་ ནང་ དུ་ སོང་ སྟེ །_ ཕན་ཚུན་ འགྲོ་བ་ ན་ བུད་མེད་ ཀྱིས་ ཀྱང་ རེག་པ ར་ བཟོད་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>On the highway, at crossings, or as it walks back and forth within fine courtyards, even girls will dare to touch it.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཡུལ་འགྱེད་པ འི་ དུས་ སུ་ དྲག་ ལ །_ གནས་པ འི་ དུས་ སུ་ ནི་ སྐུད་པ ས་ དཀྲིར་ རུང་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The elephant is terrifying on the battlefield, yet when at rest it can be pulled along by a rope.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ གླང་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ དེ་དག་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the qualities of the monarch’s elephant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོས་ དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ རེ་རེ་ སྤྱད་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ ས་བོན་ འདི་དག་ འགྲུབ་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When a universal monarch engages in just one of these ten virtuous actions, it produces these seeds of universal royalty.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ མཐའ་དག་ གི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ཞུགས་པ་ ལྟ་ སྨོས་ ཀྱང་ ཅི་ དགོས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>So, it goes without saying that they also ensue from the practice of all ten virtues together.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ དེ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ བཞི་པ་ གླང་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ མཐོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is how a spiritual practitioner perceives the precious elephant, the fourth royal treasure, by seeing with the divine eye.$110</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ རྟ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ དུ་ཞིག་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(5) “What are the qualities of the universal monarch’s precious horse?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྟ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ངང་པ་ དང་ མེ་ཏོག་ ཀུ་མུ་ད་ ལྟར་ དཀར་བ་ ཡིན །_ ཀུན་ ནས་ ལྷ འི་ ནོར་བུ འི་ གཙུག་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ མཚན་ བཟང་པོས་ བརྒྱན་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The universal monarch possesses a precious horse that is white like a swan or white lotus and is adorned with excellent marks such as the divine jewel crest.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བོང་ སྟོང་ དང་ །_ མདོག་ དང་ །_ དབྱིབས་ ཕུན་སུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This horse has the strength of a thousand horses and is of perfect color and shape.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསྒོ་ ན་ ཉིན་ གཅིག་ གིས་ འཛམ་བུ འི་ གླིང་ ལན་ གསུམ་ དུ་ སྐོར་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If told to do so, the precious horse will circle Jambudvīpa three times in a day.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ལུས་ དག་ ལ་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ ནད་མེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Its body is pure and remains perfectly free of disease.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ལྔ་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the universal monarch’s fifth treasure. $111</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ བློན་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(6) “How is the universal monarch’s precious minister?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་ [103b] འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.103.b] Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བློན་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ འདི་དག་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The precious minister possesses the following qualities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ གང་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ བྱ་བ འི་ རྣམ་པ་ ཡིད་ ལ་ སེམས་པ་ དེ་ཉིད་ མ་ བསྒོས་ ཀྱང་ དེ འི་ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཤེས་ ནས །_ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ལ་ ཡོངས་སུ་ འབུལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Whenever the monarch has the wish for something, the precious minister will understand what the king desires and offer it to him in the fullest measure, even without being asked.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་ རྫོགས་པ་ དང་ །_ དེ་ བསགས་པ་ དང་ །_ མ་ཆགས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་མ་ ཡིན་པ་ རྣམ་པར་ སྤངས་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, he gathers such utterly perfect things without any attachment, and he refrains from non-Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤིན་ཏུ་ རིགས་པ་ བརྩམས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཡུལ་ དང་ །_ དུས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>His acts are extremely appropriate, befitting the place and time.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཉོན་མོངས་ མེད་པ་ དང་ །_ གཞན་ ལ་ གནོད་པ་ མེད་པ་ དང་ །_ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ལ་ རྣམ་པར་ མི་ འཚེ་བ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is free from the afflictions, does not harm others, and does not make the people suffer.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་དག་པ འི་ ཐ་སྙད་ དང་ ལྡན་པ འི་ རང་བཞིན་ ལ་ སྐྱོ་བ་ མེད་པར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, he remains tirelessly committed to the ways of proper business.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ བྱ་བ འི་ རྣམ་པ འམ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ དོན་ གྱི་ བྱ་བ་ འདོད་པ་ དང་ ལྡན་ ཞིང་ མ་འོངས་པ འི་ བྱ་བ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཡོངས་སུ་ འབུལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>His interest is focused on the monarch’s projects and the projects of the Dharma and he devotes himself fully to programs for the future.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ བློན་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the universal monarch’s precious minister.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷག་པ འི་ གནོད་སེམས་ སྤངས་པ འི་ དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ སྤྱོད་པ་ དག་ ནི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ ཕ་མ་ ལྟར་ ཕན་པ ར་ འདོད་པ ར་ གནས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will remain with those who give up ill will and instead follow the path of the ten virtuous actions with the intention of benefiting everyone in the world, as if they were his own parents.$112</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ན་ བདུན་པ་ ཁྱིམ་བདག་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(7) “The seventh treasure is the precious master of the household.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ དུ་ཞིག་ ཡོད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What are his qualities?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས །_ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ་ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ བཀའ་ ཉན་པ འི་ ཁྱིམ་བདག་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ འདི་དག་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ རྡོ་རྗེ་ དང་ །_ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ མཐོན་ཀ་ དང་ །_ མརྒད་ དང་ །_ སྤུག་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ ངམ་གྲོག་ དང་ །_ གཡང་ས་ དང་ །_ རི་ཁྲོད་ དང་ །_ མི་ འཐུན་པ་ གཞན་དག་ ཏུ་ མ་ བསྐོས་ ཀྱང་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ འགེངས་ ལ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱང་ ཟད་པ་ མེད་པར་ འགྱུར་ ན གསེར་ དང་ དངུལ་ ལྟ་ ཞིག་ སྨོས་ ཀྱང་ ཅི་ དགོས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Without having to be told, the precious master of the household, who obeys the monarch’s command, will fill up gorges, ravines, mountainous wildernesses, and other such inaccessible places with an inexhaustible amount of diamonds, sapphires, emeralds, coral, and other such jewels—as well as, needless to mention, gold and silver.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྱིམ་བདག་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ འདི འི་ འབྱོར་པ་ ནི་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ གནས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The wealth provided by the precious master of the household is extremely reliable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཡོ་མེད་པ་ དང་ །_ སྒྱུ་ མེད་པ་ དང་ །_ [104a] གཞན་ ལ་ མི་ གནོད་པ་ དང་ །_ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དགའ་བ་ ནི་ ཁྱིམ་བདག་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is free of deceit and dishonesty, [F.104.a] does not cause anyone harm, and is well liked by the entire populace. Such is the precious master of the household.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ནི །_ མི འི་ གནས་ བཞི་ རྣམས་ ལ་སྒོ་ བར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ ཀླུ་ དང་ །_ ལྷ འི་ རིས་ གཉིས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱལ་ཆེན་ བཞི་ དང་ །_ སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་ གྱི་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ དབང་པོ འི་ སྟན་ ཕྱེད་ འཕྲོག་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$113 “The monarch who possesses these seven treasures wields power over the four human abodes and assumes half of the throne of the ruler of the nāgas, the two classes of gods, the Four Great Kings, and the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the universal monarch who possesses the seven treasures.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ ནི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དེ་དག་ ལས་ ཆུང་ ཟད་ དམན་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$114 “Slightly inferior to these are the seven subsidiary treasures:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ རལ་གྲི་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དང་ །_ པགས་པ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དང་ །_ མལ་ཆ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དང་ །_ ཚལ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དང་ །_ ཁྱིམ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དང་ །_ གོས་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དང་ །_ ལྷམ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>sword, skin, bedding, garden, home, garment, and sandals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ རལ་གྲི་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ ཡུལ་འཁོར་ གང་དག་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཡིད་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་ ལས་ འགལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ འདོད་པ་ དེར་ རལ་གྲི་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ འགྲོ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$115 (1) “The qualities of the subsidiary treasure of the sword are such that the sword will hasten to wherever people of the realm might feel inclined to transgress the monarch’s thought or word.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ བཏབ་པ་ མེད་ ཅིང་ རལ་གྲི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ ས་ སུ་ ལ་ ཡང་ བཏབ་པ་ མེད་ ཀྱིས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nobody will strike the sword and neither does the sword ever strike anyone.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱང་ ཡུལ་འཁོར་ ཀུན་ གྱིས་ མཐོང་ ནས་ འདུད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Yet as they see the sword, all the people will be filled with respect.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཟང་བ །_ མི་བཟད་པ །_ ཆད་པ་ མེད་ ཅིང་ མཚོན་ གྱིས་ བདའ་བ་ མེད་ ཀྱང་ ཡུལ་འཁོར་ དེ་དག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འདུད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, while it never cuts anyone, whether good or evil, and while the sword hence does not function as a weapon, it nevertheless instills reverence in the entire realm.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ རལ་གྲི་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the qualities of the subsidiary treasure of the sword.$116</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>པགས་པ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(2) “What are the qualities of the subsidiary treasure of the skin?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>པགས་པ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ནི་ རྒྱ་མཚོ་ ནས་ འབྱུང་ སྟེ །_ དེ་ བྱུང་བ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ དང་ །_ ཚོང་པ་ དག་ གིས་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ལ་ འབུལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This precious hide comes from the ocean and is offered to the monarch by sea merchants.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ རྒྱ་མཚོ འི་ ཀླུ འི་ པགས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The skin is from an ocean nāga.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཞེང་ དུ་ དཔག་ཚད་ ལྔ་ ལ་ ཆུ ར་ དཔག་ཚད་ བཅུ་ སྟེ །_ དེ་ ཆར་ གྱིས་ མི་ རླན །_ རླུང་ གིས་ མི་ སྐྱོད །_ མེས་ མི་ འཚིག _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Five leagues wide and ten leagues long, it repels water, cannot be stirred by the wind, and is fire resistant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གྲང་ ན་ དྲོ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_ དྲོ་ ན་ བདེ་བ་ བསིལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It brings warmth when one feels cold, and cools in times of heat.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ འཁོར་ དང་ བཅས་པ་ གང་ དུ་ འགྲོ་བ་ དེར་ བློན་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ ས་ དེ་ ཁྱེར་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Wherever the monarch and his court may travel, the precious minister will bring this skin along.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཇི་ [104b] ལྟར་ སོ་སོ་ ནས་ བྱེད་པ་ ལྟར་ དེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ འཁོར་ གྱི་ ཁྱིམ་ གྱི་ བྱ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.104.b] The skin causes everyone to serve the royal household in the same way that they take care of their own.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུད་མེད་ མི་ སྡུག་པ་ དག་ མི་ མཐོང་ ཞིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The skin prevents the sight of repulsive females.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དཀར་བ་ དེ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ་ ཟླ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཉི་མ འི་ འོད་སྣང་བ་ དེ་ དང་ ཡང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is white and shines with the light of the moon and sun. $117</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>!གསུམ་པ་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ མལ་ཆ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ནི་ ཡང་ ཞིང་ འཇམ་ ལ་ མཐོན་ དམན་ ཅན་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ དེ འི་ རྒྱུ་མཚན་ ནི་ བཏེག་ ན་ འཕར་བ་ དང་ མནན་པ་ ནེམ་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(3) “Third, the monarch’s precious bedding is light, smooth, and has upper and lower layers#23 that automatically rearrange themselves in response to the body’s pressure.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ བསམ་གཏན་ སེམས་ ན་ དེ འི་ བསམ་གཏན་ རྣམ་པར་ གྲོལ་ ཞིང་ བློ་གྲོས་ གསལ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If the monarch wishes to concentrate, this bedding will free his concentration and brighten his intelligence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཀྱིས་ ཟིལ་ གྱིས་ ནོན་པ་ ཡིན་ ན་ དེ་ མལ་ཆ འི་ སྟེང་ དུ་ འདུག་ ན །_ དེ འི་ ཚེ་ འདོད་ཆགས་ དང་ བྲལ་ ཞིང་ ཆགས་པ་ མེད་པར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If the monarch should become overcome by desire, sitting on this bedding will make him become detached and free from desire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཞེ་སྡང་ དང་ གཏི་མུག་ དག་ ལ་ ཡང་ དེ་བཞིན་ ཏེ །_ མལ་ཆ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ནི་ བསམ་གཏན་ གྱི་ གནས་ དང་ འདྲ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The bedding has the same effect on anger and delusion, and thus the precious bedding is like a seat of meditation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ མལ་ཆ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ནང་ ན་ འདུག་པ་ བུད་མེད་ ཀྱིས་ མཐོང་ ལ་ དེ འི་ ཚེ་ མཆོག་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ་ སྐྱེས་ ཀྱང་ ཡིད་ ལ་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ འདོད་ཆགས་ པར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When women see the monarch poised on his precious bedding they will feel the most intense joy yet they will not become excessively desirous.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གསུམ་པ་ འདི་ ནི་ མལ་ཆ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the qualities of the bedding that is the third subsidiary treasure. $118</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཞི་པ་ ཚལ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཡོན་ཏན་ དུ་ཡོད་ ཅེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(4) “What are the qualities of the garden, the fourth subsidiary treasure?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ གལ་ཏེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཚལ་ དུ་ བསམ་གཏན་ ལ་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_ དེ་དེ ར་ ཉེ་བ ར་ འགྲོ་ ན་ ཚལ་ དེ འི་ མཐུ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱིས་ གང་ ལྷ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ གྱི་ ཚལ་ གྱི་ དགའ་བ འི་ རྣམ་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Whenever the king approaches his garden, feeling inclined to meditate there, the power of the garden and the monarch’s own virtuous actions cause all the pleasures of the divine parks in the heavenly realms to manifest:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ཏོག་ དང་ །_ འབྲས་བུ་ དང་ །_ བྱ་ དང་ །_ པད་མ་ དང་ །_ ལྟེང་ཀ་ དང་ །_ འབབ་པ འི་ ཆུ་ངོགས་ བདེ་བ་ དང་ །_ ལྷ འི་ བུ་མོ་ དག་ རོལ་མོ་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_ དགོད་ ལ་ མཛེས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>flowers, fruits, birds, lotuses, ponds, streams, and embankments, along with goddesses who play music, smile, and display their beauty.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྩེ་བ་ དེ་དག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལྷ འི་ རིས་ དེ་ནས་ ཚལ་ དེར་ ཉེ་བ ར་ འོང་ སྟེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>All these pleasures descend from the realms of gods and manifest within the garden.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ དེ་ཡང་ ལྷ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ ལྷ འི་ འདོད་པ འི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ལྔ་ དག་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In this way the king may, just like a god, enjoy divine pleasures of the five senses.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚལ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ དེར་ བུད་མེད་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ དགའ་ ཞིང་ དགའ་མགུ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He and the ladies of the garden will find tremendous delight and appreciation in each other’s company.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ དེ་ བཞི་པ་ ཚལ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ མཐོང་ ནས་ གནས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the garden, the fourth subsidiary treasure, as it is seen by the spiritual practitioners of virtuous action.$119</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཁྱིམ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན །_ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ དུ་ཞིག་ དང་ ལྡན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(5) “What is the subsidiary treasure of the universal monarch’s home like, and what are its features?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ གང་ འཁོར་ [105a] ལོས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཁྱིམ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ནང་ དུ་ ཉལ་བ ར་ གྱུར་ ན །_ མཚན་མོ་ ཉལ་བ་ དེ འི་ ཚེ་ ཟླ་བ་ ལྟ་བ ར་ འདོད་ ན་ འོང་ཞིང་ གཟའ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱུ་སྐར་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.105.a] When the monarch sleeps within the subsidiary treasure of the royal home, the moon will draw closer if the monarch so wishes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐར་མདའ་ དག་ ཀྱང་ དེ འི་ ཁྱིམ་ དེར་ ཉེ་བ ར་ འོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ དེ འི་ ནོར་བུ་ ཡང་ མཐོང་ ན་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, all the planets, stars, and other celestial bodies may draw near and display their jewels to everyone’s delight.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་མོ་ དག་ ཀྱང་ ལྷ འི་ རོལ་མོ་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Goddesses will play divine music.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ མྱ་ངན་ མང་པོ་ དང་ བྲལ་བ འི་ མི་ དེ་ བདེ་བ ར་ གཉིད་ལོག་ པར་ འགྱུར །_ གཉིད་ལོག་པ་ ན་ རྨི་ལམ་ དགེ་བ་ མཆོག་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ་ དག་ མཐོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As the people in the house, whose burdens are thus removed, fall happily asleep, they will have auspicious and delightful dreams.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གྲང་བ འི་ དུས་ སུ་ ནི་ རླུང་ དྲོ་བ་ ལྡང་ ཞིང་ །_ དྲོ་བ འི་ དུས་ སུ་ རླུང་ བསིལ་བ་ རེག་ ན་ བདེ་ ཞིང་ འཇམ་པ་ ལྡང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>During cold weather this home is heated by warm breezes, and when the weather is hot it will be fanned by gentle and delightfully cooling winds.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཚན་མོ་ ཐུན་ གསུམ་ ལས་ ཐུན་ གཉིས་ ལ་ ཉལ་ ཞིང་ ཐུན་ གསུམ་པ་ ལས་ གཉིད་ དང་ བྲལ་ ནས་ ལངས་ ཏེ །_ བདེ་བ འི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ གནས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, one will sleep during the night’s first two watches, and wake up pleasantly refreshed in the third.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ནི་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ཁྱིམ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such is the home that is a subsidiary treasure of the universal monarch.$120</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གོས་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ འི་ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་ཡོད་ ཡོན་ཏན་ ནི་ དུ་ཞིག་ དང་ ལྡན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(6) “What are the features and special qualities of the subsidiary treasure of the garment?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ལྟ་སྟེ །_ ཐགས་ བཟང་ ཞིང་མཆོག་ ཏུ་ འཇམ་ ལ་ དྲི་མ ས་ མ་ གོས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ གྱོན་ ནས་ གྲང་བ་ དང་ །_ དྲོ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཀྲེས་པ་ དང་ །_ སྐོམ་པ་ དང་ །_ ཉམ་ཆུང་བ་ དང་ །_ ངལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུབ་པ འི་ གནོད་པ་ མེད་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Excellently woven, perfectly smooth, and unstained, the precious garment makes its bearer impervious to cold, heat, hunger, thirst, weakness, exhaustion, and weariness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ དང་ མཚོན་ དག་ གིས་ བསྲེག་པ་ དང་ །_ གཅད་པ ར་ མི་ ནུས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is also resistant to being burned by fire or cut by sharp weapons. $121</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ འི་ ལྷམ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(7) “What is the subsidiary treasure of the universal monarch’s sandals like?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ བརྟགས་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷམ་ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྐང་པ་ ལ་ གྱོན་ ན་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ སྐམ་ས་ ལ་ རྐང་པ་ མི་ འབྱིང་བ་ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ ཆུ་ ལ་ ཡང་ མི་ འབྱིང་ བར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When the universal monarch wears the subsidiary treasure of the sandals, he may walk on water without sinking in, just as if walking on dry land.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ དལ་ གྱིས་ སྔོན་ དུ་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ འདོད་ ན །_ དཔག་ཚད་ བརྒྱ ར་ ཡང་ འགྲོ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ ལུས་ ལ་ ངལ་བ་ མེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If he wishes to gently walk ahead, the sandals will allow him to proceed for a hundred leagues without any weariness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་དག་ ནི་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ དང་ །_ ཉེ་བ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ བདུན་ དག་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ མི འི་ [105b] གནས་ བཞི་ དང་ །_ ལྷ འི་ རིགས་ གཉིས་ ལ་ཉེ་ བར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$122 “Thus, the universal monarch possesses these seven treasures and seven subsidiary treasures as he rules [F.105.b] the four human abodes and the two classes of gods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ བུ་ དཔའ་ ཞིང་ རྟུལ་ཕོད་ ལ་ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ སྡེ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇོམས་པ་ སྟོང་ ཐམ་པ་ ཡོད་ དེ །_ དེ་དག་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ལ་ ཕྱག་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such a monarch is the father of a thousand sons, each of them bold and heroic, a conqueror of enemy armies, and all of them worship the universal monarch.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གནོད་སེམས་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ ལས་ སྤངས་པ་ ནི །_ དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ གྱི་ རྒྱུ་ འཐུན་པ་ བདེ་བ་ དེ་དག་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such are the pleasures that are experienced as the result of restraint from the negative act of ill will, and the associated ten virtuous actions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འཁོར་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ ས་བོན་ དུ་ གྱུར་པ །_ ཐོག་མ་ མེད་པ འི་ དུས་ ནས་ མུན་པ་ མུན་ནག་ ཏུ་ གྱུར་པ །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ སྦྱོར་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ བག་ ལ་ ཉལ་ དུ་ གྱུར་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$123 “Wrong view is the seed of all cyclic existence, a dense darkness since time without beginning, and the latent tendency underlying all worldly entanglements.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ སྤངས་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན །_ ཡང་དག་པ འི་ ལྟ་བ ས་ འཁོར་བ་ ལས་ གྲོལ་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How is such wrong view abandoned? And how does one reach liberation from cyclic existence by accomplishing the correct view?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see this by means of knowledge derived from hearing or through the divine eye.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ དེས་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ མཐོང་བ་ ནི་ འདི་ ལ་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ སྤངས་ ཤིང་ །_ དེ འི་ ཡང་དག་པ འི་ ལྟ་བ ས་ དོན་མེད་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྤངས་ ལ །_ ཡང་དག་པ འི་ སྦྱོར་བ འི་ བག་ ལ་ ཉལ་ འདོར་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_ དེ་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ འཁོར་བ་ དང་ རིང་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such spiritual practitioners who observe phenomena see that by giving up wrong view and activating the correct view, one will abandon all that is meaningless, give up the latent tendency underlying all worldly entanglements, approach the transcendence of suffering, and leave cyclic existence behind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ ལ་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ རྣམ་པ་ ལྔ་ མཐོང་ ནས་ དབང་པོ་ ལྔ་ བསྒྲུབས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ནི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$124 “Their perception of five types of wrong view will lead such beings to an accomplishment of the five faculties.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་ དམ་པ་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ དེ་ ཐོག་མ་ ནས་ འདི་ལྟར་ སངས་རྒྱས་ ཀྱི་ ཡོན་ཏན་ དེ་དག་ རྣ ར་ ཐོས་ ནས་ དེ འི་ ཚེ་ འདི་ལྟར་ འཁོར་བ འི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ རྣམ་པ་ སྣ་ཚོགས་ ལ་ དམིགས་ ཤིང་ འགྲོ་བ་ ལྔ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ འཇིགས་པ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ལྔ་ དམིགས་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That is to say, from the moment they hear of the qualities of the buddhas, holy beings who delight in the sacred Dharma will begin to notice the many sufferings of cyclic existence, and thus see the five realms of beings as five great horrors.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ བག་མེད་ པས་ འཆི་བ འི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ དང་ །_ མི་ རྣམས་ ལ་ འདོད་པ འི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ དང་ །_ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ གནོད་པ འི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ རྣམས་ ལ་ བཀྲེས་པ་ དང་ སྐོམ་པ འི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ གཅིག་ ལ་ གཅིག་ ཟ་བ འི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will see that due to their carelessness the gods experience the suffering of death, humans suffer due to their desires, hell beings experience the pains of torture, starving spirits suffer from hunger and thirst, and animals suffer as they prey on one another.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ རྣམ་པ་ ལྔ་པོ་ དེ་དག་ རྣམ་པ་ དུ་མ་ ཡོད་ ཅིང་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ གྱི་ ཡན་ལག་ དབྱེ་བ་ དག་ དཔག་ ཏུ་ མེད་པར་ དམིགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Each of these five terrors has numerous distinct features and thus beings undergo innumerable kinds of suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཚེ་ འདི་ལྟར་ ཐོག་མ་ ཉིད་ དུ་ འཁོར་བ་ [106a] ཐམས་ཅད་ ལས་ ངེས་པ ར་ བྱུང་བ ར་ གྱུར་ ཅིང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$125 “When they realize this, holy beings will first of all [F.106.a] develop renunciation toward all of cyclic existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྣང་བར་ གྱུར་ ལ་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ངེས་པ ར་ འབྱེད་པ འི་ ཆ་ལམ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ སེམས་བསྐྱེད་ དེ །_ དེ འི་ སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པ་ གཅིག་ ལས་ དགེ་བ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྒྱུན་ ཉིད་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Illuminated by such renunciation, they will develop the mind that is the path for ascertainment of the sacred Dharma, and from that single event arises a stream of virtuous qualities.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གིས་ དེ འི་ སེམས་བསྐྱེད་པ་ དེ་ དང་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྡན་པ་ ལ་བར་ སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ རབ་ཏུ་ མགུ་ ཞིང་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ དགའ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$126 “The terrestrial yakṣas will notice with great appreciation, fondness, and delight whoever gives rise to and possesses such a mind.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ རངས་པ ར་ གྱུར་ ནས་ ཡིད་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Enraptured, they will think,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ འདི འི་ མིང་ ནི་ འདི་ ཞེས་ བྱ །_ རིགས་ ནི་ འདི་ ཞེས་ བྱ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>‘This is the noble son known as so-and-so, who is of such and such a family.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཐོག་མ་ མེད་པ འི་ དུས་ ནས་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཞེ་སྡང་ གཏི་མུག་ རྣམས་ སྤོང་བ ར་ འདོད་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This individual is intent on relinquishing beginningless desire, anger, and delusion.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདུད་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ གྱི་ དངོས་པོ་ མི་འདོད་པ ར་ ཞུགས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This person has no interest in any of the things that belong to the field of the māras.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀུན་ ནས་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ འི་ ཡུལ་ དག་ གིས་ དགའ་བ འི་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཀྱི་ མོད་ ལས་ སྐྱེས་པ འི་ སྲེད་པ་ དག་ ལ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ མི་ དགའ་བ་ ཡིན་ ནོ་ སྙམ་ མོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This noble son is averse to the craving that accompanies the desire for afflictive objects.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>!གཞན་ ཡང་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ དང་ བྲལ་བ འི་ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ དེ་ ནི་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ རབ་ཏུ་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ སེམས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ བསྟན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ གོམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ལ་ མང་ དུ་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$127 “Furthermore, noble offspring who have given up wrong view will constantly practice,#24 cultivate, and increase that mind of freedom.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ འི་ བཤེས་གཉེན་ ལ་ བསྙེན་བཀུར་ བྱེད །_ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཉན་པ་ ལ་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will serve spiritual teachers and enjoy listening to the sacred Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ ཀྱི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཕྱིར་ཞིང་ སེམས་ གསལ་ ལ་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_ ལུས་ དང་ ངག་གི་ལས་ ཀྱི་ མཐའ་ ཞི་ ཞིང་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ གསལ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With bright minds they will turn toward and prostrate before the Dharma of the buddhas, and their physical and verbal conduct will be peaceful and extremely clear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ དེ འི་ ལུས་ དང་ ངག་ དང་ ཡིད་ ཞི་བས་ ཉིན་ མོ་ མཉམ་པ ར་ གཞག་ པར་ བར་སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ གྱིས་ རིག་ ནས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, when they rest in equipoise with peaceful body, speech, and mind, they are noticed and appreciated by the terrestrial yakṣas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ འདི་ དགེ་བ འི་ བཤེས་གཉེན་ ལ་ སེམས་ རབ་ཏུ་ དང་ ཞིང་ ཁྱིམ་ གྱི་ གནས་ གཟེབ་ ལྟ་བུ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ ལ་ སེམས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ མི་ ཆགས །_ དེས་ བདུད་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ ཐོག་མ་ མེད་པ འི་ དུས་ ནས་ ཞུགས་པ འི་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཞེ་སྡང་ གཏི་མུག་ དག་ གིས་ འདོད་པ འི་ ལྷ་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ ཏུ་ འདུ་ཤེས་ དག་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ་ མེད་ ཅིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These beings will see that there dwells a noble son, someone inspired by a spiritual teacher, someone free from attachment to the web of the household, someone free from attachment to the objects of the māras—an attachment that since beginningless time is created by desire, anger, and delusion, and that accompanies the perceptions of the gods of the desire realm.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདུད་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ གཡུལ་འགྱེད་ པར་ འདོད་ ལ་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ སྤོང་བ ར་ འདོད་པ་ དེ་བར་ སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ གྱིས་ རིག་ ནས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, the terrestrial yakṣas will notice with great delight that this is a person who is intent on battling the māras and giving up the afflictions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ དེ་དེ་ ལྟར་ འཁོར་བ འི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ ལ་ དམིགས་ ནས་ ཆེས་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ རབ་ [106b] ཏུ་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ སེམས་ སྐྱེད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_ དེ་ སྲོག་གཅོད་པ་ དང་ །_ མ་ བྱིན་པ ར་ ལེན་པ་ དང་ །_ འདོད་པ ས་ ལོག་པ ར་ གཡེམ་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆང་ དང་ །_ སྦྱར་བ འི་ ཆང་ དང་ །_ བརྫུན་ དུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ སྤངས་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$128 “Moreover, when such noble offspring observe the sufferings of cyclic existence their strong sense of [F.106.b] renunciation will make them give up killing, stealing, sexual misconduct, the use of intoxicants, and lying.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྡོམ་པ་ ལེན་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will also take vows to that effect.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ གང་ གི་ ཚེ་ དགེ་བསྙེན་ གྱི་ སྡོམ་པ་ རྫོགས་པ ར་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དེ འི་ ཚེ །_ བར་སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When they receive the full vows of a lay practitioner, the terrestrial yakṣas will notice this with joy and proclaim,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ མིང་ ནི་ འདི་ ཞེས་ བྱ །_ རུས་ ནི་ འདི་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ དང་ །_ གྲོང་རྡལ་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ དང་ །_ ཡུལ་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ཏུ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>‘Lo, this is the noble son known as so-and-so, who is of such and such a family, from such and such a town, and such and such an area.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྲ་ དང་ཁ་ སྤུ་ བྲེགས་ ཏེ་ ཆོས་གོས་ ངུར་སྨྲིག་ བགོས་ ནས་ ཡང་དག་པ འི་ དད་པས་ ཁྱིམ་ ནས་ ཁྱིམ་ མེད་པར་ རབ་ཏུ་ བྱུང་ སྟེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Now his hair and beard are being shaved off and, as he dons the saffron-colored robes, he is leaving the household with true faith.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདུད་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ ནི་ དམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ ནི་ མཐོ་བ ར་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is rejecting the side of the māras and acceding to the side of the sacred Dharma.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདུད་ ཀྱི་ འཆིང་བ་ ནི་ རྣམ་པར་ གཅོད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཞེ་སྡང་ གཏི་མུག་ ལས་ གྲོལ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ་ ཞེས་ མངོན་པར་ སྒྲོགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is cutting the chains of the māras and causing liberation from the great afflictions of desire, anger, and delusion.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ ནི་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ སྦྱོར་བ འི་ བག་ ལ་ ཉལ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ གཞི་ ཡིན་ ལ །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྟ་བ་ ནི་ མཐའ་ མྱ་ངན་ ལས་ འདས་པ འི་ གཞི་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$129 “Wrong view is the latent tendency underlying all worldly entanglements, whereas correct view is the basis for the attainment of nirvāṇa.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ པས་ ཆོས་ དེ་ རྗེས་སུ་ མཐོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is seen by spiritual practitioners.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཚེ་ འདི་ལྟར་ ཐོག་མ་ ཉིད་ དུ་ ཡང་དག་པ འི་ ལྟ་བ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ སྟོད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such spiritual practitioners will, therefore, first of all praise right view.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ དགོད་ མི་ སྨོད་ སྐྱོན་ དུ་ མི་ འགྲང་ ལ་ ཕ་རོལ་ དག་ ལ་ སྟོན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ རབ་ཏུ་ འཇོག་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will not laugh at right view, nor will they criticize it or treat it as a flaw. Rather, they will teach right view to others and establish others within that.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ ལ་ སྨོད་ དེ །_ སྟོད་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ལ་ སྨོད་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Wrong view, on the other hand, they will scorn, criticize, and avoid praising.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྟ་བ ས་ ནི་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ ལས་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ དང་ །_ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ མངོན་པར་ སྟོན་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ འཇོག་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$130 “Through right view one may explain the actions, phenomena, and karmic ripenings that are associated with wrong view, and so avoid establishing others in wrong view.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཆིང་བ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ རྩ་བ་ ནི་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Wrong view is the root of all bondage.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྱིས་པ་ སོ་སོ འི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ འཆིང་བ་ ཡིན་ ཞིང་ འབྱུང་པོ་ རྣམས་ དང་ །_ སེམས་ཅན་ དམྱལ་བ་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ ཀྱི་ ཡུལ་ དུ་ གནས་པ འི་ མཐའ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is what binds infantile, ordinary beings and establishes the confines of the realms of ghosts, hell beings, animals, and starving spirits.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུས་ དེ་ སྤངས་ ན་ དགེ་བ་ དུ་མ་ དེ་དག་ ཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A noble son who gives up wrong views will thereby achieve numerous virtues.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ དེ་ འདི་ལྟར་ ཁྱིམ་ གྱི་ གནས་ ནི་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ་ [107a] ཉམ་ང་བ་ འཆིང་བ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ དུ་མ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ རང་དབང་ མེད་པར་ རིག་ ནས་ ཁྱིམ་ ནས་ འབྱུང་ ཞིང་ རབ་ཏུ་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འདོད་ ལ་ བདུད་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ གཡུལ་འགྱེད་ པར་ འདོད་པ འི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$131 “Moreover, when a noble son becomes acutely aware that the household is a place of suffering, [F.107.a] misfortune, and bondage, he will want to go forth from the household, become ordained, and give battle to the māras.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེས་བུ་ དམ་པ་ དེ་ ས་བླ་ དང་ །_ བར་སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ ལྷ་ དག་ གིས་ རིག་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Such a holy person will be noticed and appreciated by the terrestrial and celestial gods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་ སྟེ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི་ རྣམས་ ལ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ འི་ ཡིད་ ཀྱིས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With joy they will convey to the Four Great Kings,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ འདི་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ གྲོང་ ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ དང་ །_ གྲོང་རྡལ་ མང་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ དང་ །_ ཡུལ་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ཏུ་ སྐྲ་ དང་ཁ་ སྤུ་ བྲེགས་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>‘A noble son by the name of so-and-so, who is of such and such a city, such and such a town, and such and such an area, is having his hair and beard shaved off.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གོས་ ངུར་སྨྲིག་ བགོས་ ནས་ ཡང་དག་པ འི་ དད་པ་ ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཁྱིམ་ ནས་ ཁྱིམ་ མེད་པར་ རབ་ཏུ་ བྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is donning the saffron-colored robes and is going forth from the household with true faith.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཁྱིམ་ ནས་ བྱུང་བ ས་ བདུད་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ ནི་ དམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ ནི་ མངོན་པར་ མཐོ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དོ་ ཞེས་ མངོན་པར་ བསྙད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The forces of the māras are waning; the forces of the sacred Dharma are on the rise!’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི་པོ་ དེ་དག་ གིས་ ས་བླ་ དང་ །_ བར་སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ ལྷ་ དག་ དང་ །_ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ དེ་དག་ ལས་ དེ་སྐད་ ཐོས་ ནས་ ཡིད་ དགའ་ ལ་བར་ སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ དག་ རབ་ཏུ་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>As the Four Great Kings hear this from the terrestrial and celestial gods and yakṣas they will rejoice in the same way as the terrestrial yakṣas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ ར་ འཛམ་བུ འི་ གླིང་ གི་ མི་ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ དགེ་བ འི་ གཏམ་ གྱིས་ སྤྲོ་བ་ སྐྱེས་ ནས །_ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ དེ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ རིགས་པ ར་ འཕགས་པ་ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གི་ མཁན་པོ་ ལ་ བསྙེན་བཀུར་ བྱེད་ དོ །_། བསྙེན་བཀུར་ བྱས་ ནས་ ཀྱང་ སྐྲ་ དང་ཁ་ སྤུ་ བྲེགས་ ཤིང་ གོས་ ངུར་སྨྲིག་ བགོས་ ཏེ་ སོ་སོ ར་ ཐར་པ འི་ སྡོམ་པ་ ལེན་ ཏོ །_། སྡོམ་པ་ བླངས་པ ས་ ས་བླ་ དང་ །_ བར་སྣང་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ རྣམས་ ལྷག་པ ར་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$132 “Thus, when a human being in Jambudvīpa becomes inspired by the virtuous words of the sacred Dharma, when such a noble son pays reverence to a noble preceptor of mendicants, and when he shaves off his hair and beard, dons the saffron-colored robes, and takes the prātimokṣa vows, the celestial and terrestrial yakṣas will rejoice deeply in this.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི་ ལ་ འཛམ་བུ་གླིང་ ན་ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ གྲོང་ མང་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ དང་ །_ ཡུལ་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ཏུ་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ སྤངས་ ནས་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྟ་བ འི་ ལས་ དང་ །_ ཆོས་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ བླངས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They will convey to the Four Great Kings, ‘The noble son by such and such a name, and of such and such a town and area, has now given up wrong view and adopted the actions and Dharma of the true view.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བུ་ དང་ ཆུང་མ་ ལ་ སྲེད་པ་ དུག་ ལྟ་བུ་ དོན་མེད་ ཅིང་ ཉམ་ང་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྤངས་ ནས</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He has given up the poison of craving for children and spouse and has relinquished all that is meaningless and miserable.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྲ་ དང་ཁ་ སྤུ་ བྲེགས་ གོས་ ངུར་སྨྲིག་ བགོས་ ཤིང་ སོ་སོ ར་ ཐར་པ་ བླངས་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He has shaved his head, donned the saffron-colored robes, and taken the prātimokṣa vows.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདུད་ དང་ ལྷན་ཅིག་ གཡུལ་འགྱེད་ པར་ འདོད་པ །_ དགའ་བ འི་ འདོད་ཆགས་ ཀྱི་ མོད་ ལས་ སྐྱེས་པ་ སྤོང་བ ར་ འདོད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ་ ཞེས་ མངོན་པར་ བསྙད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is intent on giving battle to the māras and giving up all that involves craving for pleasure.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ [107b] དེ འི་ ཚེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་ ནས་ རྒྱལ་ཆེན་ བཞི འི་ རིས་ ཀྱི་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.107.b] $133 “The Four Great Kings will rejoice deeply, and therefore say to the gods of their realm,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཛམ་བུ འི་ གླིང་ དུ་ རིགས་ ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ལས་ གྲོང་ མང་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ དང་ །_ ཡུལ་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ཏུ་ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ སྤངས་ ནས</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>‘In Jambudvīpa a noble son of such and such a family, town, and area has given up wrong view.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྟ་བ ས་ སྐྲ་ དང་ཁ་ སྤུ་ བྲེགས །_ གོས་ ངུར་སྨྲིག་ བགོས་ ནས་ དད་པ་ ཉིད་ ཀྱིས་ ཁྱིམ་ ནས་ ཁྱིམ་ མེད་པར་ རབ་ཏུ་ བྱུང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Adopting right view, he has shaved off his hair and beard, donned the saffron-colored robes, and with faith gone forth from the household to become a homeless mendicant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་སློང་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ གི་ དྲུང་ དུ་ གནས་ སོ་ ཞེས་ མངོན་པར་ སྒྲོགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is now dwelling before the monk known as so-and-so.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ ཐོས་ ནས་ བདུད་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ དམས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞིང་ །_ དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ ནི་ འཕེལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ་ ཞེས་ ཡིད་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_། དེ་ནས་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི་ ལས་ རྒྱལ་ཆེན་ བཞི འི་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ ཐོས་ ནས་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ ཡིད་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$134 “As the gods in the realm of the Four Great Kings hear this they will rejoice deeply and think, ‘The forces of the māras are waning; the forces of the sacred Dharma are on the rise!’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ དེ་ འདི་ལྟར་ ཁ་ན་མ་ཐོ་བ་ རྡུལ་ ཙམ་ ལ་ ཡང་ འཇིགས་ པར་ ལྟ་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$135 “Moreover, such a noble son will consider even the slightest evil frightening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཟོད་ ཅིང་ དུལ་ ཏེ །_ སེམས་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ སྡོམ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will be accepting and disciplined, and he will guard his mind well.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདུ་འཛི་ ལ་ མི་ དགའ་ ཞིང་ ཉེ་བ ར་ ཁྲོ་བ་ མེད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will have no interest in mundane business and be free of anger.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིགས་ ནས་ རིགས་ སུ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ སྟེན་ ཅིང་ སྡིག་པ འི་ གྲོགས་པོ་ དང་ འགྲོགས་ པར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ལ་ ཡུལ་ གྱི་ རྣམ་པར་ རྟོག་པ་ ལ་ ལྟ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will continuously attend to noble beings, give up negative company, and avoid views that involve thoughts about objects.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཟའ་བ་ ཞིམ་པོ་ མང་ དུ་ མི་ འདོད་ ཅིང་ ཚོགས་ ངན་པ་ དང་ སྤྱོད་པ ར་ མི་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will not crave copious delicious food, nor will he join unwholesome gatherings.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡུལ་ གྱི་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ ནམ་ དུ་ ཡང་ མཛའ་བཤེས་ སུ་ ལྟ་བ འི་ ངང་ཚུལ་ ཅན་ དུ་ མི་ བྱེད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will not be fond of those who are preoccupied with objects, nor will he ever develop friendships with such people.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡུལ་ ལ་ སྤྱོད་པ འི་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ སུ་ མི་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ དྲན་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ གཞག་པ་ ལ་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ བརྩོན་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will not maintain a discipline involving preoccupation with objects but will always endeavor in the application of mindfulness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཞི་བ འི་ ཟས་ ཀྱིས་ གནས་ ཤིང་ བདུད་ ཀྱི་ འཆིང་བ་ གཅོད་པ་ ལ་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ བརྩོན་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He will abide by preserving peace and constantly and persistently cutting through the chains of the māras.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྟ་བ་ ལ་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ བརྩོན་ ཞིང་ སྐྱེས་བུ་ དམ་པ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ ཕན་པ ར་ འདོད་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Always diligently adhering to the right view, such a holy being will be intent on benefiting the entire world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདིར་ ཚིགས་ སུ་ བཅད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$136 “Here follow some verses:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འབྱུང་པོ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ གང་ མི་ འཚེ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Never inflicting harm on others,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྟག་ ཏུ་ བྱམས་ སེམས་ བཟོད་ལྡན་པ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>His love and patience are constant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འབྱུང་པོ་ ཀུན་ གྱི་ ཕ་ ལྟ་བུ ར །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is like a father to all beings</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And is looked up to by the world.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ བྱིན་ལེན་པ་ སྤངས་པ་ ནི །_། རྟག་ ཏུ་ ཤེས་ལྡན་ དབང་པོ་ ཐུལ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$137 “Having given up stealing, He is always aware, and his senses are subdued.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ལས་ མཐའ་ དགེ་བ་ དང་ །_། སྲིད་པ་ དག་ ལས་ དེ་ རྒལ་ ལོ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>His physical conduct is virtuous, And he passes beyond the realms of existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རི་མོ ར་ [108a] བྲིས་པ འི་ བུད་མེད་ ལ །_། མིག་ གིས་ ལྟ་བ ར་ མི་ བྱེད་ དེ །_། འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདོད་པ་ དམ་ བཅོམ་པ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.108.a] $138 “He will not so much as look at A painting of a woman, And so he conquers the world’s tenacious craving.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ལྟ་ བུ་ ནི་ གྲོལ་ ཞེས་ བྱ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is what is known as liberation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དཔའ་ ལ་ བོང་བ་ གསེར་ དུ་ འདྲ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$139 “For such a hero dirt is no different than gold.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མྱ་ངན་ བྲལ་ ཞིང་ མཉམ་པ ར་ གཞག _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Free from suffering, he rests in equipoise.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཉོན་མོངས་ འདོད་ཆགས་ མ་ འདྲེས་པ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Not mixed up with the affliction of desire,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ མཐའ་ ཡ ས་ སྒོ་ ཐོབ་བོ །།_།།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is the attainment of the infinite gateways.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ ལ་དོན་ དང་ དོན་ མིན་ མཉམ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$140 “He for whom something and nothing are the same,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ རྙེད་ དང་ མ་ རྙེད་ དང་ །_། བདེ་ དང་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ སེམས་ མཉམ་པ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Wealth and no wealth are the same, And pleasure and pain are the same,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ དགེ་སློང་ ཞེས་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That person is called a monk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཛའ་བཤེས་ མི་ བཤེས་ གཉི་ག་ སྤངས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$141 “He who has given up the notions of ‘friend’ and ‘not friend,’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ ནི་ མཉམ་ ཞིང་ དབང་པོ་ ཐུལ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Whose mind is in equipoise and whose senses have been tamed,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ ཡུལ་ གྱིས་ ཉོན་ མི་ མོངས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And who is not afflicted by objects—</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ཡང་ བྲམ་ཟེ ར་ ཤེས་པ ར་ བྱ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He should be recognized as a brahmin.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡུལ་ ནི་ གང་ཟག་ དུག་ འདྲ་ ལ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$142 “One who is free from objects that are like poison,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྡང་བ་ དཔའ་བོ་ ཉོན་མོངས་ བྲལ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And from anger that is a hero’s affliction,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྫོགས་ སངས་རྒྱས་ ཀྱིས་ བཤད་པ་ ཡི །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Is said by the perfect Buddha</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཡི་ མྱ་ངན་ འདས་ མི་ རིང་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To be not far from nirvāṇa.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་ དང་ འཇིག་པ འི་ དེ་ཉིད་ ཤེས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$143 “Knowing the nature of arising and cessation</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཡང་དག་ ལྟ་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ་ མེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Is the correct view, and there is no attachment.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གངས་རི་ ལྟ་བུ ར་ བློ་ མི་ གཡོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, the mind, as immovable as a snow mountain,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ འཁོར་བ་ ལས་ གྲོལ་ ལོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Has been liberated from cyclic existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཙན་དན་ དང་ ནི་ རལ་གྲི ར་ མཉམ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$144 “When sandalwood and swords are the same,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟས་ ནི་ ཞིམ་ དང་ མི་ ཞིམ་ མཉམ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When tasty and unappealing food are the same,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟབ་ དར་ སྣམ་བུ་ མཉམ་པ་ ནི །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And when silk and raw wool are the same,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲེད་པ ས་ གནོད་པ ར་ མི་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One will not be harmed by craving.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྙེད་ དང་ བཀུར་སྟི་ མི་ དགའ་ ཞིང་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$145 “One who has no concern for wealth and adulation</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྩྭ་ སྟན་ ཙམ་ གྱིས་ ཆོག་ཤེས་ ལ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Is content with merely a straw mat.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྙེད་ དང་ བཀུར་སྟི་ མེ་ ལྟ་བུ ར །_། གང་ གིས་ མཐོང་བ་ དེ་ མཐོང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is perceived by One who sees wealth and adulation to be like fire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ ཡུལ་ གྱི་ དབང་ མི་ འགྱུར །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$146 “The one who will not be swayed by objects,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྲེད་པ འི་ ཆུ་བོ ར་ མི་ འཇུག་ ལ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Who will not enter the river of craving,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རང་ གི་ ལས་འབྲས་ དེ་ཉིད་ ཤེས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>But understands his own acts and their effects,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ དགེ་སློང་ སངས་རྒྱས་ གསུངས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He is a monk, according to the Buddha.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ འདས་པ འི་ དུས་ མི་ འདོད །_། མ་འོངས་པ་ ལ་ བློ་ མི་ དགའ །_། རྣལ་འབྱོར་པ་ ནི་ ད་ལྟ ར་ ལ །_། མི་ དགའ་ དེ་ ཡི་ བློ་གྲོས་ མེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$147 “When he does not hanker for the past, Does not speculate about the future, And is not infatuated with the present, The practitioner is devoid of thought.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གི་ བློ་གྲོས་ ཕྱིར་ལོག་པ །_། ཆོས་ ལ་ རྟག་ ཏུ་ གནས་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_། དཀར་པོ་ ཆོས་ ལ་ མཉམ་ གཞག་པ །_། དེ་ ནི་ འཁོར་བ ར་ མི་ འཇུག་ གོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$148 “When one withdraws one’s thoughts, Letting the mind rest constantly in the Dharma, One achieves equipoise in the qualities of virtue And will thus not enter into cyclic existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གིས་ སེམས་ ལ་ རྙོག་ མི་ བྱེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$149 “Those who do not make their minds turbid</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རིག་པ་ མེ་ ལྟ་བུ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Achieve an awareness that is like fire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ ལ་ ཡུལ་ ནི་ བྲན་ ལྟ་བུ །_། དེ་ ལ་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ མེད་པ་ ཡིན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Those for whom objects are servants Will not encounter any suffering.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གིས་ དབང་པོ་ དབང་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_། དབང་པོ འི་ དབང་ དུ་ མི་ [108b] འགྲོ་ ལ །_། གང་དག་ གཟུགས་ སོགས་ མི་ འཕྲོགས་ ཤིང་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$150 “Those who master their senses, And are not swayed by their senses, [F.108.b] Will not be ruined by forms and so on.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཉོན་མོངས་ མེད་པ་ ཐུབ་ དང་ འདྲ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Like the Able One, they will be free from the afflictions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གིས་ བསམས་པ་ དགེ་བ་ དག _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$151 “One whose wishes are virtuous,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཟོད་ལྡན་ མཐོང་ ན་ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_། སེམས་ ནི་ རབ་ཏུ་ དགའ་བྱེད་པ །_། མི་ དེ་ ཟླ་ འདྲ་ ཐུབ་པ་ ཡིན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Who is patient, delightful to behold, And whose mind is joyous— That person is a moon-like able one.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་དག་ དགོན་པ ར་ མངོན་དགའ་བ །_། ཁང་ བཟངས་ མཆོག་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ་ མེད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$152 “One who delights in the wilderness, Who has no attachment to fine mansions,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐང་ གི་ ཤིང་ ལ་ མངོན་དགའ་ ཞིང་ །_། ཟས་ སློང་ དགེ་སློང་ ཞེས་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Who is fond of trees on the plains and who begs for his food, Is one who should be recognized as a monk.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དཔའ་བོ་ ཞི་དུལ་ བློ་བཟང་བ །_། བདེ་ དང་ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ དེ་ཉིད་ རིག _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$153 “The gentle hero of excellent intellect, Who knows the true nature of pleasure and pain,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ནི་ བླ་མེད་ གནས་ འགྲོ་ ཞིང་ །_། གང་ དུ་ སོང་བ ར་ ཉོན་ མི་ མོངས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Will go to the unexcelled realm And be free from afflictions wherever he is.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྙིང་བརྩེ་ ལྡན་ ཞིང་ བློ་གྲོས་ དྲང་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$154 “With a loving heart and honest mind</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྟག་ ཏུ་ བསམ་གཏན་ ཕ་རོལ་ འགྲོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He constantly perfects concentration.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕལ་པ་ རྣམས་ དང་ མཉམ་ མི་ འགྲོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Not keeping company with the ordinary,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ དེ་ ནི་ བདེན་ཚིག་ ལྡན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This practitioner possesses the power of true words.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ འི་ ཆོས་ དེ་དག _། སྤངས་པ ས་ དེ་དག་ འཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$155 “When giving up wrong view, These are the attainments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞན་ ཡང་ ལོག་པ ར་ ལྟ་བ་ སྤངས་པ ས་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ ལྟ་བ་ སྔོན་ དུ་ འགྲོ་བ འི་ ཡིད་ རྣམ་པར་ རྟོག་པ་ སྤངས་པ འི་ རིམ་གྱིས་ ཟག་པ་ མེད་པ འི་ བསམ་གཏན་ ལ་ མངོན་པར་ དགའ་བ་ ལས་ བླ་ དང་བ ར་ སྣང་ ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$156 “By giving up wrong view one relinquishes thoughts in a way that brings the mind toward right view. Thus, one will gradually achieve the joy of undefiled concentration.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྤྱོད་པ འི་ ལྷ་ དང་ །_ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ དང་ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི་ རྣམས་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེ་ན</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How, you may wonder, do the terrestrial and celestial gods and yakṣas, as well as the Four Great Kings, rejoice in this?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྣལ་འབྱོར་ སྤྱོད་པ་ ནང་ གི་ ཆོས་ ལ་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ རྗེས་སུ་ ལྟ་ ཞིང་ གནས་པ་ དེས་ ཐོས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ འི་ ཤེས་པ འམ །_ ལྷ འི་ མིག་ གིས་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི་པོ་ དེ་དག་ གིས་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བཞི འི་ ལྷ་ དེ་དག་ དང་ །_ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ དབང་པོ་ བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ ལ་ སྒྲོགས་ པར་ བྱེད་པ་ ནི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Spiritual practitioners who carefully observe inner phenomena see by means of knowledge derived from hearing, or through the divine eye, that when the Four Great Kings have passed their message to the gods of their realm those gods will, in turn, pass it to Śakra, lord of the gods.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ འདི་ལྟར་ འཛམ་བུ འི་ གླིང་ ན་ རིགས་ ཆེ་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ལས །_ གྲོང་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ དང་ །_ གྲོང་རྡལ་ ག་གེ་མོ་ ཞིག་ ཏུ་ རིགས་ ཀྱི་ བུ་ མིང་ འདི་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ སྐྲ་ དང་ཁ་ སྤུ་ བྲེགས་ ཏེ གོས་ ངུར་སྨྲིག་ བགོས་ ནས་ དད་པས་ ཁྱིམ་ ནས་ ཁྱིམ་ མེད་པར་ རབ་ཏུ་ བྱུང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus, they will convey to him, ‘In Jambudvīpa, the noble son known as so-and-so, who is of such and such a family, village, and town, has shaved off his hair and beard, donned the saffron-colored robes, and with faith gone forth from the household to become a homeless mendicant.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ དང་ །_ ཡང་དག་ པར་ སྡོམ་པ་ སྤྱོད་པ །_ སྤོབས་པ་ རིགས་པ་ དང་ གྲོལ་བ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Observing discipline and vows, he possesses eloquence, reasoning, and liberation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དྲན་པ་ ཉེ་བ ར་ གཞག་པ །_ ཁ་ན་མ་ཐོ་བ་ རྡུལ་ ཙམ་ ལ་ ཡང་ འཇིགས་ པར་ ལྟ་བ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He remains mindful and regards even a speck of evil with fear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདུད་ [109a] ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ དམས་པ ར་ བྱེད་ ཅིང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[F.109.a] The forces of the māras are waning;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དམ་པ འི་ ཆོས་ ཀྱི་ ཕྱོགས་ ནི་ མངོན་པར་ མ་ ཐོ་བ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>the forces of the sacred Dharma are on the rise!</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ བདག་ཅག་ གིས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ལ་ གསོལ་བ་ ལགས་སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This is our message to the gods.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཐོས་ ནས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ དབང་པོ་ བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ ཤིན་ཏུ་ ཡིད་ དགའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བརྒྱ་བྱིན་ གྱི་ མདུན་ན་འདོན་ དེ་ དང་ སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ་ གྱི་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ དགའ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$157 “Śakra, lord of the gods, will be most delighted when he hears this, and so will the gods who are his close servants, and the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ་ བཅུ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱི་ ལམ་ ལེའུ ར་ བཅད་པ འོ །།_།།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$158 This was the chapter on the ten virtuous courses of action.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>
