<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra The Fourfold Accomplishment</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">The Translation</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">$1 [61.a] Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">$2 Thus did I hear at one time.</s>
    <s id="4:2">The Blessed One was in the Jeta Grove, in Anāthapiṇḍada’s park at Śrāvastī.</s>
    <s id="4:3">He was residing there with a great saṅgha of five hundred monks, one hundred thousand bodhisattvas who had all donned the great armor, and the gods who inhabit the desire and form realms.</s>
    <s id="4:4">There, the Blessed One, surrounded and revered by this retinue of hundreds of thousands of beings, taught the Dharma.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$3 Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta raised a jeweled parasol measuring ten leagues in diameter as an offering to the Blessed One and</s>
    <s id="5:2">held it above the Blessed One’s head.</s>
    <s id="5:3">Within the retinue was a god from the Heaven of Joy named Śrībhadra whose progress toward unsurpassed and perfect awakening had become irreversible.</s>
    <s id="5:4">Together with his attendants, he had joined the retinue and taken his seat.</s>
    <s id="5:5">Now he rose from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</s>
    <s id="5:6">Joining his palms, he bowed toward Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta and</s>
    <s id="5:7">inquired of him, [61.b]</s>
    <s id="5:8">“Mañjuśrī, have you still not had enough of making offerings to the Thus-Gone One?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">$4 “Divine being, tell me,” Mañjuśrī asked in return,</s>
    <s id="6:2">“is the ocean ever satiated by all of the water that it receives?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">“No, Mañjuśrī, it is not,” replied the god.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">$5 Mañjuśrī then said, “Divine being, bodhisattvas seek boundless and immeasurable omniscient wisdom that is as difficult to fathom as the depths of the great ocean,#4</s>
    <s id="8:2">so they can never have enough of making offerings to the Thus-Gone One.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">$6 “Mañjuśrī, what should bodhisattvas focus on when they make offerings to the Thus-Gone One?” asked the god.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">$7 Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, there are four things that bodhisattvas should focus on when they make offerings to the Thus-Gone One.</s>
    <s id="10:2">These four are omniscience,</s>
    <s id="10:3">liberating all beings,</s>
    <s id="10:4">ensuring that the lineage of the Three Jewels is not broken,</s>
    <s id="10:5">and attaining the array of qualities of the buddhafield.</s>
    <s id="10:6">Divine being, bodhisattvas should make offerings to the Thus-Gone One while focusing on those four things.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">$8 “Mañjuśrī,” said the god, “when you were among the Brahmā realm gods you gave a Dharma teaching to Brahmā Śikhin called The Fourfold Accomplishment of the Bodhisattva Path.</s>
    <s id="11:2">Mañjuśrī, would you please teach that?</s>
    <s id="11:3">I and everyone in this assembly would like to hear it.</s>
    <s id="11:4">Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas are not stingy with the Dharma,</s>
    <s id="11:5">nor are they tight-fisted with the Dharma as teachers.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">$9 “Divine being,” Mañjuśrī replied, “in that case listen well, pay attention, and</s>
    <s id="12:2">I will explain the Dharma teaching called The Fourfold Accomplishment to you.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">$10 “Divine being, these are the four altruistic intentions that bodhisattvas generate: [62.a]</s>
    <s id="13:2">bodhisattvas generate the intention to gather together immeasurable beings,</s>
    <s id="13:3">they generate the intention to ripen immeasurable beings,</s>
    <s id="13:4">they generate the intention to accumulate immeasurable roots of virtue, and</s>
    <s id="13:5">they generate the intention to perfectly realize the boundless buddha qualities.</s>
    <s id="13:6">Divine being, those are the four altruistic intentions that bodhisattvas generate.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">$11 “Divine being, these are the four attitudes bodhisattvas generate that are like a rock:</s>
    <s id="14:2">an attitude that has no hostility toward those who make requests,</s>
    <s id="14:3">an attitude of compassion toward those who have gone astray,</s>
    <s id="14:4">an attitude of not losing insight, and an attitude of bringing all undertakings to completion.</s>
    <s id="14:5">Divine being, those are the four attitudes bodhisattvas generate that are like a rock.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">$12 “Divine being, these are the four attitudes bodhisattvas generate that are superior:</s>
    <s id="15:2">superior discipline, superior learning, superior great love, and superior great compassion.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">$13 “Divine being, these are the four attitudes bodhisattvas generate that are stable, substantial, inseparable, and like a vajra:</s>
    <s id="16:2">not being separated from the intention,</s>
    <s id="16:3">not being separated from spiritual companions,</s>
    <s id="16:4">not being separated from striving, and</s>
    <s id="16:5">not being separated from the Great Vehicle.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">$14 “Divine being, these are the four attitudes bodhisattvas generate that are difficult to accomplish:</s>
    <s id="17:2">not being involved with the afflictions;</s>
    <s id="17:3">not being involved with gain, honor, and praise;</s>
    <s id="17:4">not being involved with a lesser vehicle;</s>
    <s id="17:5">and not being involved with crude people. [62.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">$15 “Divine being, these are the four attitudes bodhisattvas generate that are unsurpassed:</s>
    <s id="18:2">the wish to relinquish all manner of pleasing things,#5</s>
    <s id="18:3">having no regret after giving them away,</s>
    <s id="18:4">not wishing for any result, and</s>
    <s id="18:5">the attitude of dedication to awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">$16 “Divine being, these are the four qualities that crown bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="19:2">the perfection of wisdom,</s>
    <s id="19:3">skill in methods,</s>
    <s id="19:4">understanding the true Dharma, and</s>
    <s id="19:5">bringing beings to fruition.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">$17 “Divine being, these are the four that demonstrate the bodhisattvas’ path to awakening:</s>
    <s id="20:2">exerting oneself in the perfections,</s>
    <s id="20:3">acting in accord with the means for drawing beings to the path,</s>
    <s id="20:4">accomplishing the abodes of Brahmā, and</s>
    <s id="20:5">demonstrating playful mastery of the supernatural perceptions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">$18 “Divine being, these four are excellent, holy, and supreme among the qualities of the bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="21:2">having no hostility toward anyone,</s>
    <s id="21:3">generating the wish to liberate those who oppose oneself,</s>
    <s id="21:4">being conscientious regardless of one’s wealth or the vastness of one’s domain, and</s>
    <s id="21:5">acting in accord with the Dharma, no matter how destitute and poor one may be.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">$19 “Divine being, these are the four inclinations of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="22:2">being satisfied with one’s own wealth as a householder,</s>
    <s id="22:3">harboring no desire for another’s wealth,</s>
    <s id="22:4">being satisfied with the family of the noble ones after one has gone forth, and</s>
    <s id="22:5">adopting ascetic practices and reducing one’s material possessions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">$20 “Divine being, these are the four gifts of bodhisattvas: the gift of Dharma;</s>
    <s id="23:2">the gift of material wealth;</s>
    <s id="23:3">the gift of paper, ink, pens, and books; [63.a] and</s>
    <s id="23:4">the gift of wholeheartedly exclaiming ‘Well done!’ to those who teach the Dharma.#6</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">$21 “Divine being, these are the four essentials of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="24:2">essential perseverance rather than studying,</s>
    <s id="24:3">essential relinquishment rather than having possessions,</s>
    <s id="24:4">essential service to the teacher#7 rather than to the body, and</s>
    <s id="24:5">the essential development of roots of virtue rather than a livelihood.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">$22 “Divine being, these are the four things that bodhisattvas should not forsake:</s>
    <s id="25:2">they should not forsake the thought of awakening,</s>
    <s id="25:3">they should not forsake the holy Dharma,</s>
    <s id="25:4">they should not forsake beings, and</s>
    <s id="25:5">they should not forsake pursuing any qualities that are roots of virtue.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">$23 “Divine being, these are the four motives of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="26:2">dwelling in the deep forest,</s>
    <s id="26:3">delighting in solitude,</s>
    <s id="26:4">yearning for virtuous qualities, and</s>
    <s id="26:5">skillfully ripening beings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">$24 “Divine being, these are the four mansions of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="27:2">the abodes of Brahmā,</s>
    <s id="27:3">being delighted when hearing the Dharma expounded,</s>
    <s id="27:4">reflecting on emptiness, and</s>
    <s id="27:5">gathering with beings of the same spiritual lineage.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">$25 “Divine being, these four are the bodhisattvas’ inexhaustible wealth:</s>
    <s id="28:2">the wealth of learning,</s>
    <s id="28:3">the wealth of teaching the Dharma,</s>
    <s id="28:4">the wealth of assembling beings in need, and</s>
    <s id="28:5">the wealth of dedication to awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">$26 “Divine being, these are the four treasures of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="29:2">the treasure of retention,</s>
    <s id="29:3">the treasure of eloquence,</s>
    <s id="29:4">the treasure of the Dharma, and</s>
    <s id="29:5">the treasure of dedication to inexhaustible enjoyment.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">$27 “Divine being, these are the bodhisattvas’ four types of departure: [63.b]</s>
    <s id="30:2">departure from society,</s>
    <s id="30:3">departure from all inhabited lands,</s>
    <s id="30:4">departure from ignoble intentions, and</s>
    <s id="30:5">departure from all the three realms.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="31">
    <s id="31:1">$28 “Divine being, these are the bodhisattvas’ four types of happiness:</s>
    <s id="31:2">the happiness of being free from possessiveness and grasping due to a disregard for all material things,</s>
    <s id="31:3">the happiness of solitude due to abandoning one’s homeland,</s>
    <s id="31:4">the happiness of quiescence due to relinquishing the afflictions, and</s>
    <s id="31:5">the happiness of attaining nirvāṇa by not forsaking beings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="32">
    <s id="32:1">$29 “Divine being, these are the bodhisattvas’ four supreme joys:</s>
    <s id="32:2">supreme joy due to seeing the Thus-Gone One,</s>
    <s id="32:3">supreme joy due to hearing the Dharma,</s>
    <s id="32:4">supreme joy due to giving without regret, and</s>
    <s id="32:5">supreme joy due to engendering happiness in all beings.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="33">
    <s id="33:1">$30 “Divine being, these are the bodhisattvas’ four truths:</s>
    <s id="33:2">not forsaking the thought of awakening,</s>
    <s id="33:3">not breaking one’s commitments,</s>
    <s id="33:4">not forsaking those who have taken refuge, and</s>
    <s id="33:5">restraining one’s speech so that one always speaks the truth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="34">
    <s id="34:1">$31 “Divine being, these are the bodhisattvas’ four virtuous qualities:</s>
    <s id="34:2">applying oneself with good intentions to all virtuous qualities,</s>
    <s id="34:3">not harboring contempt toward anyone who is untrained,</s>
    <s id="34:4">becoming a friend to all beings without being asked, and</s>
    <s id="34:5">not hoping for any reward because one has already accomplished all manner of good qualities and because one does not wish to be compensated.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="35">
    <s id="35:1">$32 “Divine being, these four are the pure practices of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="35:2">pure discipline because of the lack of self,</s>
    <s id="35:3">pure absorption because of the non-existence of beings,</s>
    <s id="35:4">pure insight because of the non-existence of the soul, and [64.a]</s>
    <s id="35:5">pure liberation because of the non-existence of persons.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="36">
    <s id="36:1">$33 “Divine being, these are the four feet of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="36:2">the foot of the Dharma, the foot of purpose, the foot of engaging in the ascetic practices and having few possessions, and the foot of gathering#8 the accumulations of the path of awakening.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="37">
    <s id="37:1">$34 “Divine being, these are the four hands of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="37:2">the hand of faith, the hand of discipline, the hand of learning, and the hand of insight.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="38">
    <s id="38:1">$35 “Divine being, these are the four eyes of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="38:2">the physical eye due to correct karmic action,</s>
    <s id="38:3">the divine eye due to undiminished supernatural perception,</s>
    <s id="38:4">the eye of insight due to possessing the power of extensive learning, and</s>
    <s id="38:5">the Dharma eye due to reflection on all phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="39">
    <s id="39:1">$36 “Divine being, these are the four things that bodhisattvas never tire of:</s>
    <s id="39:2">they never tire of generosity,</s>
    <s id="39:3">they never tire of living in the deep forest,</s>
    <s id="39:4">they never tire of hearing the Dharma, and</s>
    <s id="39:5">they never tire of the entire collection of virtuous qualities.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="40">
    <s id="40:1">$37 “Divine being, these are the four hardships of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="40:2">the hardship of being patient and tolerant toward beings who are weak;</s>
    <s id="40:3">the hardship of wanting to give all one’s possessions to the poor;</s>
    <s id="40:4">the hardship of not being angry at those who ask for one’s head—that most important body part—but instead generating the thought that they are one’s spiritual teacher; and</s>
    <s id="40:5">the hardship of taking birth at will due to not conceptualizing birth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="41">
    <s id="41:1">$38 “Divine being, these are the bodhisattvas’ four types of good health:</s>
    <s id="41:2">being healthy because the elements are in balance,</s>
    <s id="41:3">being healthy because one is not tormented by the afflictions, [64.b]</s>
    <s id="41:4">being healthy because one will establish all beings in happiness, and</s>
    <s id="41:5">being healthy because one harbors no doubts regarding any phenomena.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="42">
    <s id="42:1">$39 “Divine being, these are the four personal perspectives of bodhisattvas:</s>
    <s id="42:2">the perspective of the perfections,</s>
    <s id="42:3">the perspective of the factors of awakening,</s>
    <s id="42:4">the perspective of the authentic spiritual teacher, and</s>
    <s id="42:5">the perspective of not committing any misdeeds.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="43">
    <s id="43:1">$40 “Divine being, these are the four unshakable qualities that bodhisattvas possess:</s>
    <s id="43:2">the unshakable mind of awakening,</s>
    <s id="43:3">unshakable commitments,</s>
    <s id="43:4">the unshakable practice of what one preaches, and</s>
    <s id="43:5">unshakable correct exertion.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="44">
    <s id="44:1">$41 “Divine being, these are the bodhisattvas’ four accumulations:</s>
    <s id="44:2">the accumulation of tranquility,</s>
    <s id="44:3">the accumulation of special insight,</s>
    <s id="44:4">the accumulation of learning, and</s>
    <s id="44:5">the accumulation of all roots of virtue.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="45">
    <s id="45:1">$42 “Divine being, these are the four ways that bodhisattvas integrate the teachings:</s>
    <s id="45:2">integrating intention with application,</s>
    <s id="45:3">integrating giving away with dedication,</s>
    <s id="45:4">integrating love with compassion, and</s>
    <s id="45:5">integrating method with wisdom.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="46">
    <s id="46:1">$43 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ Dharma#9 obscurations:</s>
    <s id="46:2">seeing a dirty well yet still seeing the moon at the bottom;</s>
    <s id="46:3">seeing a muddy pond, pool, or well yet still seeing the moon at the bottom;</s>
    <s id="46:4">seeing the moon although the sky is cloudy; and</s>
    <s id="46:5">seeing the moon although the sky appears shrouded in wind, dust, and smoke.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="47">
    <s id="47:1">$44 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ karmic obscurations: [65.a]</s>
    <s id="47:2">seeing oneself fall from a high cliff into an abyss;</s>
    <s id="47:3">seeing a road with highs and lows;</s>
    <s id="47:4">seeing oneself set out on a narrow roadway;</s>
    <s id="47:5">being lost in the dream and seeing many terrifying things.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="48">
    <s id="48:1">$45 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ afflictive obscurations:</s>
    <s id="48:2">seeing someone convulsing due to a strong poison,</s>
    <s id="48:3">hearing the call of a large pack of vicious predators,</s>
    <s id="48:4">seeing oneself living among rogues, and</s>
    <s id="48:5">seeing one’s body and clothing covered with filth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="49">
    <s id="49:1">$46 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ attaining dhāraṇī:</s>
    <s id="49:2">seeing a great treasure chest filled with many jewels,</s>
    <s id="49:3">seeing a pool filled with blooming lotus flowers,</s>
    <s id="49:4">seeing oneself finding a bundle of white cloth, and</s>
    <s id="49:5">seeing a god with a parasol being held over his head.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="50">
    <s id="50:1">$47 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ attaining absorption:</s>
    <s id="50:2">seeing an attractive girl with beautiful jewelry who offers worship by scattering flowers,</s>
    <s id="50:3">seeing a flock of pure white swans flying in the sky and calling out,</s>
    <s id="50:4">seeing the hand of the luminous Thus-Gone One being placed on the top of one’s head, and</s>
    <s id="50:5">seeing the Thus-Gone One seated on a lotus and engaged in concentration.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="51">
    <s id="51:1">$48 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ seeing the Thus-Gone One:</s>
    <s id="51:2">seeing a moonrise,</s>
    <s id="51:3">seeing a sunrise,</s>
    <s id="51:4">seeing a lotus flower opening, and</s>
    <s id="51:5">seeing the lord of the Brahmā realms in the posture of utter quiescence.</s>
    <s id="51:6">Divine being, those four [65.b] dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ seeing the Thus-Gone One.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="52">
    <s id="52:1">$49 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ particular characteristics:</s>
    <s id="52:2">seeing a great sāla tree that is full of brilliantly colored leaves, flowers, and fruits;</s>
    <s id="52:3">seeing a metal bowl filled with gold;</s>
    <s id="52:4">seeing the sky filled with parasols, banners, and standards; and</s>
    <s id="52:5">seeing a great universal emperor.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="53">
    <s id="53:1">$50 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ taming Māra:</s>
    <s id="53:2">seeing a great champion overcome all of the enemy’s champions, raise a standard, and advance;</s>
    <s id="53:3">seeing a great hero defeat an army and then advance;</s>
    <s id="53:4">seeing a king being consecrated; and</s>
    <s id="53:5">seeing oneself sitting at the seat of awakening and taming Māra.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="54">
    <s id="54:1">$51 “Divine being, these are the four corresponding dreams that are signs of the bodhisattvas’ non-regression:</s>
    <s id="54:2">seeing a white diadem affixed on one’s head,</s>
    <s id="54:3">seeing oneself making unstinting offerings,</s>
    <s id="54:4">seeing oneself seated on a great Dharma seat, and</s>
    <s id="54:5">seeing the Thus-Gone One sitting at the seat of awakening and teaching the Dharma.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="55">
    <s id="55:1">$52 “Divine being, these four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ attainment of the seat of awakening:</s>
    <s id="55:2">seeing a vase;</s>
    <s id="55:3">seeing oneself surrounded by blue roller birds;</s>
    <s id="55:4">seeing that wherever one goes, all of the trees first reach upward, then bow and pay homage; and</s>
    <s id="55:5">seeing a bright golden light.</s>
    <s id="55:6">Divine being, those four dreams are consequences of the bodhisattvas’ attainment of the seat of awakening.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="56">
    <s id="56:1">$53 When Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta gave this Dharma teaching on The Fourfold Accomplishment, [66.a]</s>
    <s id="56:2">the god Śrībhadra was happy and rejoiced.</s>
    <s id="56:3">Since he had become exceedingly happy, delighted, and joyful,</s>
    <s id="56:4">he and his retinue showered the entire retinue with divine mandārava flowers as well as blue, pink, red, and white lotus flowers as an offering to Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta.</s>
    <s id="56:5">As soon as they had scattered the flowers, through the power of the Buddha, beautiful, fragrant, and delightful lotus flowers the size of chariot wheels appeared in the sky above them.</s>
    <s id="56:6">In the center of each of the flowers were bodhisattvas ornamented with the thirty-two marks of a great being.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="57">
    <s id="57:1">$54 Then the god Śrībhadra asked Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta,</s>
    <s id="57:2">“Mañjuśrī, where did these bodhisattvas come from?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="58">
    <s id="58:1">“Divine being, where did these flowers of yours come from?” Mañjuśrī asked in return.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="59">
    <s id="59:1">$55 “Mañjuśrī,” replied the god, “these flowers are emanations—</s>
    <s id="59:2">I scattered them to make an offering to you.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="60">
    <s id="60:1">$56 Mañjuśrī then said,</s>
    <s id="60:2">“Divine being, you should view the bodies of those bodhisattvas just as you view these flowers—as emanations.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="61">
    <s id="61:1">$57 At that moment the Blessed One smiled.</s>
    <s id="61:2">As happens when the blessed buddhas smile, a multitude of light rays of various colors—</s>
    <s id="61:3">blue, yellow, red, white, violet, and crystalline—emanated from the mouth of the Blessed One.</s>
    <s id="61:4">These light rays pervaded infinite and limitless world systems and</s>
    <s id="61:5">reached all the way up to the realm of Brahmā above.</s>
    <s id="61:6">Their splendor outshone the radiance of the sun and the moon.</s>
    <s id="61:7">Then the light rays returned and dissolved into the Blessed One’s crown. [66.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="62">
    <s id="62:1">$58 At that point the god Śrībhadra rose from his seat,</s>
    <s id="62:2">arranged his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee.</s>
    <s id="62:3">Joining his palms, he bowed toward the Blessed One and</s>
    <s id="62:4">praised the Blessed One with these verses:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="63">
    <s id="63:1">$59 “You shine with light rays of the purest gold,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="64">
    <s id="64:1">You possess the thirty-two supreme marks of a great being,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="65">
    <s id="65:1">You are resplendent with innumerable billions of good qualities—</s>
  </p>
  <p id="66">
    <s id="66:1">Protector, please explain why you are smiling.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="67">
    <s id="67:1">$60 “Your voice is pleasant, and your speech exalted;</s>
  </p>
  <p id="68">
    <s id="68:1">You speak with the voice of Brahmā, using tender words.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="69">
    <s id="69:1">Wise Sugata, you shine brightly with the seven riches</s>
  </p>
  <p id="70">
    <s id="70:1">And your voice is like a cuckoo—please explain why you are smiling.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="71">
    <s id="71:1">$61 “Supreme human, holy being who subdued the one with a wicked horde,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="72">
    <s id="72:1">You have permanently and decisively eradicated Māra’s power.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="73">
    <s id="73:1">The gods, asuras, and garuḍas continually worship you—</s>
  </p>
  <p id="74">
    <s id="74:1">Wielder of the ten powers, please explain why you are smiling.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="75">
    <s id="75:1">$62 “Stainless, uncontaminated, and free from the three defilements,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="76">
    <s id="76:1">Your broad face is like the full moon.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="77">
    <s id="77:1">You cut through faults that, like dust, shroud our vision in darkness,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="78">
    <s id="78:1">And you bring joy and happiness—please explain why you are smiling.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="79">
    <s id="79:1">$63 “Blissful one, supreme benefactor of the earth and the god realms</s>
  </p>
  <p id="80">
    <s id="80:1">Who brings joy and happiness, whose qualities are limitless,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="81">
    <s id="81:1">Whose clear speech perfectly teaches in a way that is appropriate and relevant—</s>
  </p>
  <p id="82">
    <s id="82:1">Please make us understand the reason that you smile.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="83">
    <s id="83:1">$64 “You remove the thick film that shrouds our eyes in darkness,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="84">
    <s id="84:1">You wield the brilliant radiance of the torch of insight,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="85">
    <s id="85:1">You have the power of the leader of a herd of elephants and the majestic gait of a lion,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="86">
    <s id="86:1">And you benefit beings—please explain why you are smiling.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="87">
    <s id="87:1">$65 “Supreme human, you tame hordes of wicked people.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="88">
    <s id="88:1">Incomparable one, you dry up the waters of existence,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="89">
    <s id="89:1">Which are so deep, hard to fathom, and difficult to measure.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="90">
    <s id="90:1">You are undeceiving and possess the ten powers—please explain why you are smiling.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="91">
    <s id="91:1">$66 “You grant the goal of immortality that pacifies old age and death. [67.a]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="92">
    <s id="92:1">Your feet are supple, webbed, and marked with wheels.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="93">
    <s id="93:1">You dispel stupidity and are unequaled in the threefold world.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="94">
    <s id="94:1">Master of sublime gnosis, please explain why you are smiling.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="95">
    <s id="95:1">$67 “Divine being,” the Blessed One replied to Śrībhadra,</s>
    <s id="95:2">“do you see these bodhisattvas in the sky above who are seated in the center of lotuses on lion thrones?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="96">
    <s id="96:1">“Yes, Blessed One, I see them.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="97">
    <s id="97:1">$68 “Divine being,” the Blessed One then explained,</s>
    <s id="97:2">“all these bodhisattvas have gathered from the ten directions to hear the Dharma in the presence of Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta.</s>
    <s id="97:3">They have come to hear this Dharma teaching on The Fourfold Accomplishment.</s>
    <s id="97:4">Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta ripened all these bodhisattvas.</s>
    <s id="97:5">All these bodhisattvas are now only one birth away from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</s>
    <s id="97:6">They will fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood in one buddhafield or another, each with their various names, throughout the worlds in the ten directions.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="98">
    <s id="98:1">$69 “Blessed One,” the god replied, “I cannot comprehend the number of bodhisattvas here—how many are there?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="99">
    <s id="99:1">$70 The Blessed One then asked Venerable Śāriputra,</s>
    <s id="99:2">“Śāriputra, can you comprehend how many bodhisattvas there are here?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="100">
    <s id="100:1">$71 “Blessed One,” said Śāriputra, “in one instant, one moment, or one second, I can count all the stars in an entire three-thousandfold universe.</s>
    <s id="100:2">However, Blessed One, I would be unable to count these bodhisattvas even in a hundred years.” [67.b]</s>
  </p>
  <p id="101">
    <s id="101:1">$72 “Śāriputra,” the Blessed One replied, “even if this continent of Jambūdvīpa were filled with minute particles,</s>
    <s id="101:2">it would be possible to determine their number by counting them. However, it would be impossible to determine the number of these bodhisattvas by counting them,</s>
    <s id="101:3">because the bodhisattvas that have gathered here are that innumerable.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="102">
    <s id="102:1">$73 “Blessed One, how can there be that many buddhafields in which these bodhisattvas will fully awaken to buddhahood?” asked Śāriputra.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="103">
    <s id="103:1">$74 “Silence, Śāriputra, do not say that,” replied the Blessed One.</s>
    <s id="103:2">“Śāriputra, the thus-gone ones empty countless buddhafields.</s>
    <s id="103:3">Consider this, Śāriputra:</s>
    <s id="103:4">The lifespan of the thus-gone ones lasts for as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</s>
    <s id="103:5">Each and every day each one delivers as many Dharma teachings as there are grains of sand in the Ganges,</s>
    <s id="103:6">and in all of those Dharma teachings he prophesies as many bodhisattvas as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</s>
    <s id="103:7">Even if one were to identify a single bodhisattva to the east, beyond as many buddhafields as there are grains of sand in the Ganges,</s>
    <s id="103:8">the thus-gone one will empty that many buddhafields.#10</s>
    <s id="103:9">Therefore, it goes without saying that the thus-gone ones, who know the minds of all beings born into the buddhafields of the ten directions, whom they perceive with the ordinary, corporeal eye of a thus-gone one, will empty all those buddhafields.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="104">
    <s id="104:1">$75 At that point the great hearers and the entire retinue were amazed and exclaimed,</s>
    <s id="104:2">“Our teachers have such vast magical powers, are so mighty, and have such great supreme knowledge!</s>
    <s id="104:3">We are so fortunate!”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="105">
    <s id="105:1">$76 The bodhisattvas who had assembled from the worlds in the ten directions [68.a] and hovered in the air now descended from the sky and</s>
    <s id="105:2">bowed their heads at the feet of the Blessed One and Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta, circumambulated them, and</s>
    <s id="105:3">then departed into the ten directions.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="106">
    <s id="106:1">$77 At that point the god Śrībhadra said to Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta,</s>
    <s id="106:2">“Mañjuśrī, you performed these deeds and ripened countless beings for awakening—well done!</s>
    <s id="106:3">Mañjuśrī, please grace us with your eloquence, beginning with the teachings that ripen the awakening of bodhisattvas.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="107">
    <s id="107:1">$78 “Divine being,” replied Mañjuśrī, “there are thirty-five teachings that ripen the awakening of bodhisattvas.</s>
    <s id="107:2">The thirty-five teachings are these:</s>
    <s id="107:3">urging them toward timeliness;</s>
    <s id="107:4">urging them toward moderation;</s>
    <s id="107:5">urging them toward proportion;</s>
    <s id="107:6">urging them toward capacity;</s>
    <s id="107:7">urging them toward stability;</s>
    <s id="107:8">urging them toward the perfections;</s>
    <s id="107:9">urging them toward method;</s>
    <s id="107:10">urging them toward the altruistic intention;</s>
    <s id="107:11">urging them toward great love;</s>
    <s id="107:12">urging them toward great compassion;</s>
    <s id="107:13">urging them toward the Great Vehicle;</s>
    <s id="107:14">urging them toward the Lesser Vehicle;</s>
    <s id="107:15">urging them toward the truth;</s>
    <s id="107:16">urging them to act on it;</s>
    <s id="107:17">urging them to protect the Dharma;</s>
    <s id="107:18">urging them to teach what they have studied;</s>
    <s id="107:19">urging them to not discriminate among various types of beings;</s>
    <s id="107:20">urging them to be equally generous to those who have faulty discipline and those who observe discipline;</s>
    <s id="107:21">urging them to declare the work of Māra;</s>
    <s id="107:22">urging them to fulfill their promises;</s>
    <s id="107:23">urging them to not grow weary of cyclic existence;</s>
    <s id="107:24">urging them to subdue Māra;</s>
    <s id="107:25">urging them to be grateful and appreciative;</s>
    <s id="107:26">urging them to eliminate the cause;</s>
    <s id="107:27">urging them to not be afraid of the gateways to liberation;</s>
    <s id="107:28">urging them to worship and serve the Thus-Gone One;</s>
    <s id="107:29">urging them to joyfully consider ways to help beings;</s>
    <s id="107:30">[68.b] urging them to not mix that with worldly Dharma;</s>
    <s id="107:31">urging them to delight in the deep forest;</s>
    <s id="107:32">urging them to have few desires and be content;</s>
    <s id="107:33">urging them toward the past as well as the future;#11 urging them to liberate those who are not liberated;</s>
    <s id="107:34">urging them to comfort those who are not comforted;</s>
    <s id="107:35">urging those who have not passed into parinirvāṇa to pass into parinirvāṇa;#12</s>
    <s id="107:36">urging them to not interrupt the lineage of the Three Jewels;</s>
    <s id="107:37">and urging them to accept the array of good qualities of the buddhafield as completely pure.</s>
    <s id="107:38">Divine being, those are the thirty-five teachings that ripen the awakening of bodhisattvas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="108">
    <s id="108:1">$79 “Divine being, bodhisattvas who have been ripened do not waver from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</s>
    <s id="108:2">No opponent whatsoever can overpower them.</s>
    <s id="108:3">From then on, they no longer fear#13 a bodhisattva’s ten types of pride.</s>
    <s id="108:4">The ten types of pride are these:</s>
    <s id="108:5">pride due to being disciplined;</s>
    <s id="108:6">pride due to being learned;</s>
    <s id="108:7">pride due to being eloquent;</s>
    <s id="108:8">pride due to being successful, revered, and praised;</s>
    <s id="108:9">pride due to living in the deep forest;</s>
    <s id="108:10">pride due to one’s ascetic practices and having few belongings;</s>
    <s id="108:11">pride due to being attractive, wealthy, powerful, and having attendants;</s>
    <s id="108:12">pride due to Śakra, Brahmā, and the world protectors offering service;</s>
    <s id="108:13">pride due to one’s absorption and supernatural perception;</s>
    <s id="108:14">and being free from any arrogance due to the fact that the gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kiṃnaras, and mahoragas who have faith in the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha</s>
    <s id="108:15">are fond of, praise, and glorify them.</s>
    <s id="108:16">Divine being, they are not at all arrogant due to those ten types of a bodhisattva’s pride.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="109">
    <s id="109:1">$80 The god Śrībhadra then said to Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta,</s>
    <s id="109:2">“Mañjuśrī, [69.a] wherever you are and</s>
    <s id="109:3">wherever this Dharma teaching is practiced, the Buddha will be seen there,</s>
    <s id="109:4">turning the wheel of Dharma.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="110">
    <s id="110:1">$81 The Blessed One replied,</s>
    <s id="110:2">“Yes, divine being, that is correct.</s>
    <s id="110:3">What you say is true.</s>
    <s id="110:4">Wherever Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta is, that place will not seem empty.#14</s>
    <s id="110:5">Wherever this Dharma teaching is performed, that is the endeavor of the Thus-Gone One, the lord of Dharma.</s>
    <s id="110:6">Those beings who hear this Dharma teaching and</s>
    <s id="110:7">develop interest in it become my followers.</s>
    <s id="110:8">The beings who hear this Dharma teaching and develop interest in it should be regarded as having been trained by the Thus-Gone One.</s>
    <s id="110:9">Those who understand this Dharma teaching and persist in their pursuit of suchness will not regress from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="111">
    <s id="111:1">$82 The Blessed One then said to the bodhisattva Maitreya, the elder Mahā­kāśyapa, and Venerable Ānanda,</s>
    <s id="111:2">“Holy beings, I entrust this Dharma teaching to you so that you may adopt, uphold, teach, and master it.</s>
    <s id="111:3">Soon I will pass into parinirvāṇa, so rely on this Dharma teaching that carries out the buddhas’ work for all beings.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="112">
    <s id="112:1">$83 Then Maitreya inquired, “Blessed One,</s>
    <s id="112:2">since we will uphold this Dharma teaching, what is its name?</s>
    <s id="112:3">How should it be remembered?”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="113">
    <s id="113:1">$84 “Maitreya,” the Blessed One replied, “you should remember this Dharma teaching as The Fourfold Accomplishment,</s>
    <s id="113:2">The Path of the Bodhisattvas, or Ripening the Bodhisattvas.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="114">
    <s id="114:1">$85 After the Blessed One had said this,</s>
    <s id="114:2">the bodhisattva Maitreya, [69.b] Venerable Mahā­kāśyapa, Venerable Ānanda, and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and</s>
    <s id="114:3">praised the Blessed One’s words.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="115">
    <s id="115:1">$86 This concludes The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Fourfold Accomplishment.”</s>
  </p>
</text>
