<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">$1 [274.a] One who wishes to take up the ringing staff [274.b] should kneel before an honorable one and</s>
    <s id="1:2">The Rite for the Protocols Associated with Carrying the Ringing Staff</s>
    <s id="1:3">say three times,</s>
    <s id="1:4">“Honorable one, I request your attention.</s>
    <s id="1:5">Today, I, named so-and-so, request you, honorable one, to be my teacher for carrying the ringing staff.”</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">$2 The honorable one then says, “Pay attention.</s>
    <s id="2:2">Venerable one , after generating the mind aspiring for unsurpassed awakening,</s>
    <s id="2:3">will you take up the ringing staff and utilize it properly?</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">$3 “Do not hold it with dirty hands.</s>
    <s id="3:2">When entering a dwelling of the saṅgha, do not rest it with its head and lower tip removed.#14</s>
    <s id="3:3">When entering the homes of householders, point the lower tip behind you.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">$4 “In the morning, when conditions are right for you to go to the home of a householder to beg for alms,</s>
    <s id="4:2">rattle the staff three times at their door.</s>
    <s id="4:3">If no one responds when you rattle it three times, you should rattle it five times.</s>
    <s id="4:4">If no one responds when you rattle it five times, you should rattle it seven times.</s>
    <s id="4:5">If no one responds when you rattle it seven times, you should proceed to another household and rattle it seven times.</s>
    <s id="4:6">If you are satisfied after having gone to seven households,</s>
    <s id="4:7">then in that case say three times, ‘I shall eat.’</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$5 “There are twenty-five rules associated with carrying the rattling staff:</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">1. “Carry it to guard against snakes on the ground.</s>
    <s id="6:2">2. “Carry it because you are elderly.#15</s>
    <s id="6:3">3.</s>
    <s id="6:4">“Carry it to collect alms.</s>
    <s id="6:5">4.</s>
    <s id="6:6">“Should you see a buddha image when entering or exiting, make some sound with it.#16</s>
    <s id="6:7">5.</s>
    <s id="6:8">“Do not go among the saṅgha while carrying a rattling staff.</s>
    <s id="6:9">6.</s>
    <s id="6:10">“Do not walk about carrying a ringing staff after noon.</s>
    <s id="6:11">7.</s>
    <s id="6:12">“Do not rest it on your shoulders hanging on to its two ends.</s>
    <s id="6:13">8.</s>
    <s id="6:14">“Do not carry it on your shoulders.#17</s>
    <s id="6:15">9.</s>
    <s id="6:16">“Do not turn it around with your hands.#18</s>
    <s id="6:17">10.</s>
    <s id="6:18">“Do not go into toilets carrying a rattling staff.</s>
    <s id="6:19">11.</s>
    <s id="6:20">“Do not follow the preceptor or other ordination masters when they are carrying ringing staffs.#19</s>
    <s id="6:21">12.</s>
    <s id="6:22">“Do not take up a ringing staff and then follow a group of four or more persons carrying ringing staffs.#20 [275.a]</s>
    <s id="6:23">13.</s>
    <s id="6:24">“Do not let your ringing staff be away from your body when visiting the home of a patron.</s>
    <s id="6:25">14.</s>
    <s id="6:26">“Go to the door of a patron and rattle the staff three times.</s>
    <s id="6:27">If no one responds, you should rattle it five times.</s>
    <s id="6:28">If no one responds when you rattle it five times, you should rattle it seven times.</s>
    <s id="6:29">If no one responds when you rattle it seven times, you should proceed to another household and rattle the staff there.#21</s>
    <s id="6:30">15.</s>
    <s id="6:31">“When the patron answers the door, lean the rattling staff against your right arm and rest it there.#22</s>
    <s id="6:32">16.</s>
    <s id="6:33">“Do not let it touch the ground when put in a dwelling.</s>
    <s id="6:34">17.</s>
    <s id="6:35">“Always put it by your bed.</s>
    <s id="6:36">18.</s>
    <s id="6:37">“Clean it from time to time.</s>
    <s id="6:38">19.</s>
    <s id="6:39">“Keep the head of the ringing staff straight.</s>
    <s id="6:40">20.</s>
    <s id="6:41">“During alms rounds, do not allow it to be taken away from you by novice monks or householders.#23</s>
    <s id="6:42">21.</s>
    <s id="6:43">“Take the ringing staff with you when spending the night in a place of sick people.</s>
    <s id="6:44">22.</s>
    <s id="6:45">“Take the ringing staff with you when you go to see someone off on a long journey.</s>
    <s id="6:46">23.</s>
    <s id="6:47">“Take the ringing staff with you when you go off to welcome someone from a long journey and</s>
    <s id="6:48">you might need to go and stay there with them.#24</s>
    <s id="6:49">24.</s>
    <s id="6:50">“Take the ringing staff with you when you need to go to places unknown.</s>
    <s id="6:51">25.</s>
    <s id="6:52">“In order to draw another person close to you, touch that person with it and</s>
    <s id="6:53">make designs on the ground.”#25</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">$6 This completes “The Rite for the Protocols Associated with Carrying the Ringing Staff.”</s>
  </p>
</text>
