<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<text>
  <p id="1">
    <s id="1:1">Praise to Tārā with Twenty-One Verses of Homage</s>
  </p>
  <p id="2">
    <s id="2:1">$1 [42.b] Homage to the honored, noble lady Tārā!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="3">
    <s id="3:1">$2 Homage to Tārā, swift and gallant, Whose glance is instantaneous like lightning.</s>
    <s id="3:2">You arose from the heart of the blossoming lotus That is the face of the lord of the three worlds.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="4">
    <s id="4:1">$3 Homage to you whose face resembles One hundred autumn full moons gathered;</s>
    <s id="4:2">Your brilliant radiance blazes,#10 Like a thousand clusters of stars.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="5">
    <s id="5:1">$4 Homage to you, whose hand is graced By a golden-blue lotus flower.#11</s>
    <s id="5:2">You embody generosity, diligence, endurance, Serenity, patience, and concentration.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="6">
    <s id="6:1">$5 Homage to you, whose triumphs are endless, Jewel on the Tathāgata’s crown.</s>
    <s id="6:2">You are well attended to by the heirs of the victors, Who have mastered all the perfections.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="7">
    <s id="7:1">$6 Homage to Tuttārā,#12 who with hūṁ Fulfills all wishes to the bounds of space.#13</s>
    <s id="7:2">You trample the seven worlds underfoot,#14 And possess the strength to summon all.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="8">
    <s id="8:1">$7 Homage to you, praised by Śakra, Agni, Brahmā, maruts, and Śiva.</s>
    <s id="8:2">The hosts#15 of bhūtas, vetālas, gandharvas, And yakṣas pay tribute to you.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="9">
    <s id="9:1">$8 Homage to you, who with traṭ#16 and phaṭ [43.a] Crush the magical devices of other traditions.</s>
    <s id="9:2">With your right leg bent and your left leg extended, You shine amid flames blazing wildly.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="10">
    <s id="10:1">$9 Homage to Turā, the fearsome lady, Destroyer of the most powerful demons.#17</s>
    <s id="10:2">With your lotus face and stern frown, You are the slayer of each and every foe!</s>
  </p>
  <p id="11">
    <s id="11:1">$10 Homage to you, whose fingers grace your heart, Displaying the mudrā of the Three Jewels.</s>
    <s id="11:2">Graced by wheels in all directions, Your natural radiance overwhelms all.#18</s>
  </p>
  <p id="12">
    <s id="12:1">$11 Homage to you, supremely joyous, Your splendorous crown spreading garlands of light.</s>
    <s id="12:2">Tuttārā, smiling and laughing, You bring demons and worlds within your control.#19</s>
  </p>
  <p id="13">
    <s id="13:1">$12 Homage to you, who can summon The hosts of earthly guardians.</s>
    <s id="13:2">Knitting your quivering brows, with the syllable hūṁ You deliver from every misfortune.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="14">
    <s id="14:1">$13 Homage to you, so brightly adorned, With a sliver of moon as your crown,#20</s>
    <s id="14:2">Your locks always graced by Amitābha, Whose bright light streams forever forth.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="15">
    <s id="15:1">$14 Homage to you, seated amid blazing flames That resemble the fire that ends an eon.</s>
    <s id="15:2">Immersed in joy, your right leg extends, and the left is bent.</s>
    <s id="15:3">Thus, you crush legions of foes.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="16">
    <s id="16:1">$15 Homage to you, who on the earth’s surface Strike your palms and stamp your feet;</s>
    <s id="16:2">The hūṁ that is formed by your frown Smashes the seven netherworlds to nothing but dust.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="17">
    <s id="17:1">$16 Homage to you, blissful, gracious, and tranquil, Whose domain is the peace of nirvāṇa.</s>
    <s id="17:2">In perfect union with svāhā and oṁ, You lay to waste every terrible evil.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="18">
    <s id="18:1">$17 Homage to you, who, immersed in rapture, Shatter the bodies of all foes.</s>
    <s id="18:2">You shine with the knowledge-syllable hūṁ, As your mantra’s ten syllables are set forth.#21</s>
  </p>
  <p id="19">
    <s id="19:1">$18 Homage to Turā, your feet stomping, Formed from the seed of the syllable hūṁ.</s>
    <s id="19:2">The mountains of Meru, Mandara, and Vindhya,#22 And all the three worlds—you cause them to quake.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="20">
    <s id="20:1">$19 Homage to you, who hold in your hand A deer-marked moon like a divine lake.</s>
    <s id="20:2">With tāra uttered twice and then with phaṭ, [43.b] You eliminate all poisons.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="21">
    <s id="21:1">$20 Homage to you, sovereign of divine hosts, Served by gods and kiṃnaras.</s>
    <s id="21:2">Your resplendence, an armor of joy, Pacifies strife and clears away nightmares.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="22">
    <s id="22:1">$21 Homage to you, whose two eyes shine brightly Like the sun and the moon when it’s full.</s>
    <s id="22:2">Tuttārā, with twice-uttered hara, You pacify the most intractable ills.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="23">
    <s id="23:1">$22 Homage to you, who have the power to pacify,#23 You display the three true natures.#24</s>
    <s id="23:2">Turā, supreme lady, you destroy The hordes of grahas, vetālas, and yakṣas.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="24">
    <s id="24:1">$23 This praise by means of the root mantra— The twenty-one verses of homage Should be recited in earnest by the wise,#25 Who are filled with devotion for the goddess.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="25">
    <s id="25:1">$24 Recalling it at dusk and also when rising at dawn Will grant them freedom from every fear.</s>
    <s id="25:2">It will pacify all misdeeds, And destroy all evil destinies.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="26">
    <s id="26:1">$25 Soon they will receive empowerment From seven million conquerors.</s>
    <s id="26:2">Beyond this, they shall attain greatness, And proceed to the ultimate state of buddhahood.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="27">
    <s id="27:1">$26 If they recall this praise all dreadful poisons, Whether natural or manufactured, Whether eaten or imbibed, Will be utterly neutralized.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="28">
    <s id="28:1">$27 This will dispel the heap of suffering Inflicted by grahas, infectious diseases, and poisons, Even in other beings.</s>
    <s id="28:2">If chanted twice, thrice, or seven times,</s>
  </p>
  <p id="29">
    <s id="29:1">$28 Those who want children will come to have them,</s>
    <s id="29:2">Those who seek wealth will come to have that,</s>
    <s id="29:3">Each and every wish will be fulfilled,</s>
    <s id="29:4">And obstacles, entirely vanquished, will be no more.</s>
  </p>
  <p id="30">
    <s id="30:1">$29 This completes the praise to the Blessed Tārā as spoken by the completely perfect Buddha.</s>
  </p>
</text>
