<tmx version="1.4b">
	<header creationtool="InterText" creationtoolversion="1.0" datatype="PlainText" segtype="block" adminlang="en-us" srclang="bo" o-tmf="XML aligned text"></header>
<body>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་འཕོ་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ ཞུས་པ འི་ མདོ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The Sūtra |#| Questions Regarding Death and Transmigration</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ བྱང་ཆུབ་ སེམས་དཔའ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་ ལོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$1 [145.b]  Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་སྐད་ བདག་ གིས་ ཐོས་པ་ དུས་ གཅིག་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$2 Thus did I hear at one time.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ན་ གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ ཆེན་པོ་ སེར་སྐྱ ར་ ཁྱིམ་བདག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འདུལ་བ འི་ དུས་ ལ་ བབ་པ ར་ གཟིགས་ ནས་ |#| དེ་དག་ དད་པ་ བསྐྱེད་པ ར་ བྱ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར །_ འཁོར་ ལྔ་ བརྒྱ་ དང་ བཅས་པ ར་ གཤེགས་པ་ ལས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The Blessed One, seeing that the time had come to train all the various householders of the great city of Kapilavastu, went there with a retinue of five hundred to cause them to generate faith.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཚེ་ ཤཱཀྱ་ དགའ་ སྐྱེས་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ དར་ལ་ བབ་པ །_ གཉེན་ གྱི་ སྐྱེ་བོ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ རབ་ཏུ་ གཅེས་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$3 At that time, a man in the prime of his life called Śākya Nandaja, who was cherished by all his relatives and praised by all, had died.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱིས་ བཀུར་བ འི་ གནས་ སུ་ གྱུར་པ་ ཞིག་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ ཕུང་པོ འི་ དྲུང་ ན་ དེ འི་ བུ་ དང་ །_ ཆུང་མ་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ དང་ །_ གཡོག་འཁོར་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ རྟ འི་ ཚོགས་ དང་ །_ གླང་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཚོགས་ དང་ །_ གོས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་ ཡང་ བསགས །_ |#| གསེར་ དངུལ་ དང་ །_ མུ་ཏིག་ དང་ །_ ཤེལ་ ལ་སོགས་པ འི་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ སྣ་ཚོགས་པ་ ཡང་ བསགས །_ |#| བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཏུང་བ་ རོ་ ཞིམ་པོ་ མངར་བ་ སྣ་ཚོགས་ པ་ ཡང་ བསགས་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In front of his body his children, wife, relatives, and dependents had gathered together his horses, elephants, clothes, and a variety of ornaments, gold and silver, pearls, crystals, and other jewels, as well as a variety of delicious and sweet food and drink.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྨྲེ་སྔགས་ འདོན་ ཅིང་ དགའ་ སྐྱེས་ ལ་ གསོལ་ ལོ་ ཞེས་ མཆོད་པ་ བྱེད་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They offered them, wailing, “We give these to Nandaja!”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཟས་གཙང་ མས་ བསམས་ [146a]  པ །_ འདི་ལྟར་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ལ་ མཆོད་ ཅིང་ གསོལ་པ་ དང་ །_ རྗེད་པ་ ནི་ བྲམ་ཟེ་ དག་ གི་ སྨྲང་ ལས་ ཟེར་ ན་ |#| འདི་དག་ ལ་སྨན་པ་ དང་ བདེ་བ་ ཅི་ ཡོད་པ་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ དྲི འོ་ སྙམ་ ནས</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$4 This made King Śuddhodana wish [146.a] to ask the Blessed One what benefit#16 and good would ensue if, in such a fashion, offerings, food,#17 and honors to the deceased were presented according to the brahmins’ formulae.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱི་ དྲུང་ དུ་ སོང་ ནས་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་ ཏེ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He approached the Blessed One, prostrated, and asked,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ སེམས་ཅན་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ དོན་ ཞུ་བ ར་ འཚལ་ ན་ |#| སྐབས་ དབྱེ་བ ར་ ཅི་ གནང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One, would you allow me to ask some questions about what it is like for sentient beings to die?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ བཀའ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$5 The Blessed One replied,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཅི་ དང་ ཅི་ བཞེད་པ་ ཞུས་ ཤིག་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“O Great King, ask whatever you wish.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ འི་ སེམས་ རངས་པ ར་ བཤད་པ ར་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It will be explained to the Great King’s satisfaction.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཟས་གཙང་ མས་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$6 The Great King Śuddhodana then asked the Blessed One,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདི་ ནས་ ཚེ་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ སེམས་ཅན་ རྣམས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ དེ་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱང་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ འམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One, regarding the rebirths of beings who pass from this world to the next, are gods reborn as gods?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ མི་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ དང་ །_ དམྱལ་བ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱང་ མི་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ དང་ །_ དམྱལ་བ་ རྣམས་ སུ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ ར་ རིགས་ མ་ འདྲེས་པ ར་ སོ་སོ ར་ སྐྱེ འམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, are humans, animals, hungry ghosts, and hell-beings also reborn consistently as their own kind, respectively, as humans, animals, hungry ghosts, and hell-beings?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ནས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ པ་ མི་ལ་ སོགས་པ་ གཞན་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ འམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Or is it the case, Blessed One, that when gods pass from this life, they are reborn as humans and other kinds of beings?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ མི་ དང་ །_ དུད་འགྲོ་ དང་ །_ ཡི་དགས་ དང་ །_ དམྱལ་བ་ རྣམས་ ནས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ན་ |#| ཡང་ ལྷ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ གཞན་ རྣམས་ སུ་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, are humans, animals, hungry ghosts, and hell-beings reborn as other kinds of beings, such as gods and so forth, as well?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ སེམས་ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འདི་ ནས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ ཡེ་ མེད་པར་ གྱུར་ ཏེ །_ |#| མེ་ ཤི་བ འི་ ཐལ་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ གྱུར་ ནས་ |#| སྐྱེ་བ ར་ ཡེ་ མ་ མཆིས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$7 “Or, Blessed One, when they pass from this life do sentient beings become utterly nonexistent, becoming like the ashes of a fire that has died out, and not taking any rebirth at all?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ སེམས་ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འདི་ ནས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཕ་ དང་ །_ མེས་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་མེས་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཐོག་མ་ མེད་པ་ ནས་ བཟུང་བ འི་ བར་ དུ་ བརྒྱུད་ པ འི་ རིས་ འཐུན་པ་ རྣམས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ མི་ ལེན་པ ར་ འདིར་ ཅི་ སྤྱད་པ་ བཞིན་ འགྲོགས་ ཏེ་ གནས་ སོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆིས་ ན་ |#| དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལགས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$8 “Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? |#| Do all sentient beings live on after their deaths, befriending their kin#18 in a beginningless lineage including fathers, grand­fathers, great-grandfathers, and more, not taking rebirth in a future life but living just as they do in this life?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འདི་ ན་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་པ་ རྣམས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ ཡང་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་ [146b]  པར་ འགྱུར་ རམ །_ འདི་ ན་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་ ཉམ་ཆུང་བ་ རྣམས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ ཡང་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་ ཉམ་ཆུང་ བར་ འགྱུར་ རམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$9 “Blessed One, do those who are wealthy and proud in this life go on to be wealthy and proud in the hereafter too, [146.b] and do those who are poor and humble in this life go on to be poor and humble in the next?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འོན་ཏེ་ དེ་ གཉིས་ མི་ འདྲ་བ ར་ ཕན་ཚུན་ བསྣོལ་ མར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Or do people simply switch back and forth between the two?#19</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འདི་ ན་ རྟ་ དང་ །_ གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཞོན་པ་ དང་ །_ འདི་ ན་ གོས་ གྱོན་པ་ དང་ རྒྱན་ ཐོགས་པ་ དང་ །_ འདི་ ན་ ཟས་ བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཏུང་བ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ རྣམས་ ཤི་འཕོས་ ནས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ ཡང་ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ ཞོན་པ་ དང་ །_ གྱོན་པ་ དང་ །_ ཟ་ ཞིང་ འཐུང་ ངོ་ ཞེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆི་ ན་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལགས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$10 “Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? |#| Those who, in this life, ride horses and elephants, wear fine clothes and ornaments, eat food and drink, do they continue in their future lives to ride, dress, and eat in the same way?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འདི་ ནས་ ཤི་འཕོས་པ་ ལ་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ ནམ །_ བུ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཉེ་ རིས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཏུང་བ་ ཉུང་ངུ་ ཉུང་ངུར་ གཏང་བ འམ །_ བསྔོས་པ་ ཡང་ བསྐལ་པ་ མང་པོ འི་ བར་ དུ་ ཟད་པ ར་ མི་འགྱུར་བ ར་ ཟ་ ཞིང་ འཐུང་ ངོ་ ཞེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆི་ ན་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལགས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$11 “Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? |#| When their parents, siblings and cousins, children, and so forth give or dedicate small portions of food or drink to someone who has passed from this world, is the deceased then able to eat and drink inexhaustibly for many eons?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་ འདས་ གཞན་ ཡང་ སེམས་ཅན་ འདི་ ནས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ན་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ ནམ །_ བུ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ་ གཏམ་ བྱས་ ཏེ་ |#| ཚིག་ ཅི་ སྨྲས་པ་ དང་ །_ |#| གཟུགས་བྱད་ ཅི་འདྲ་བ་ དག་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཕྱིས་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ ནམ །_ བུ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ་ སྔོན་ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ དུས་ ན་ གཏམ་ བྱས་པ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ སྨྲ་བ་ དང་ །_ གཟུགས་བྱད་ དག་ སྟོན་ ཏེ |#| མཐོང་བ་ དང་ ཐོས་པ་ ཡོད་ ཅེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆི་ ན་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལགས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$12 “Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? |#| When sentient beings pass on from this world, do they later, after death, tell their parents, siblings, children, and so forth the same things, such as stories and so forth, that they had told them earlier before they died? |#| And do they later exhibit the same physical features to them as they had earlier before death? |#| Are they seen and heard to do this?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་པ་ དང་ །_ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཟས་གཙང་ མ་ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$13 After these queries, the Blessed One replied to the king Śuddhodana,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་ པོ་ འདི་ ནས་ ཤི་འཕོས་ ནས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ འདྲི་བ་ ལྟར་ མ་ ལགས་ ཏེ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“O Great King, with regard to your question as to whether gods are reborn as gods and so forth, the answer is ‘no.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཡང་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེས་ ནས་ |#| འགྲོ་བ་ རིས་ གཞན་ རྣམས་ སུ་ མི་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལགས་པ་ ནས་ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ མི་ལ་ སོགས་པ་ འགྲོ་བ་ གཞན་ རྣམས་ ཀྱང་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| འགྲོ་བ་ གཞན་ དང་ གཞན་ རྣམས་ སུ་ མི་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ རང་རང་ གི་ སྔ་མ འི་ རིས་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལགས་ ན་ ནི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Suppose that when gods died they were reborn only as gods and not reborn as other types of beings, and the same for humans and so forth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ མི་ རྣམས་ དང་པོ་ ལྷ་ ལས་ གྱུར་པ་ ལགས་ ལ །_ ངན་སོང་ གསུམ་པོ་ རྣམས་ ནི་ མི་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ མི་དགེ་བ་ སྤྱད་པ་ ལས་ གྱུར་པ་ ལགས་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ གང་ ལྷ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ དེ་ འགྲོ་ [147a]  བ་ རིས་ གཞན་ དང་ གཞན་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལགས་སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, initially humans come from gods, and the three lower realms come from humans’ engagement in nonvirtue. |#| Therefore, those gods and so forth who die [147.a] are reborn in various other types of migrations.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ གསུངས་པ་ ལྟར་ ལགས་ ན་ ནི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$14 “O Great King, suppose, moreover, that the answer to this question of yours were to be ‘yes.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ འགྲོ་བ་ རིས་ དྲུག་པོ་ རྣམས་ མང་བ་ དང་ ཉུང་བ་ རྣམས་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ ཡོད་པ་ བཞིན་ དུ་དུ ས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དུ་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ རིགས་ ན</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Then it would be logical that the quantities of the six types of beings would always be the same as they are now.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ རྣམས་ ལས་མི་ དགེ་བ་ སྤྱད་པ་ མང་བ འི་ རྒྱུས་ ངན་སོང་ གསུམ་པོ་ རྣམས་ ཕྱིར་ཞིང་ མང་བ་ ལ་ གཟིགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>But notice how the three lower realms are more numerously repopulated#20 due to the preponderance#21 of humans’ engagement in nonvirtue!</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ་ འདི་དག་ ནི་ མི་ལས་ གྱུར་པ་ ལགས་ ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Moreover, O Great King, if the arhats of today come from the ranks of humans,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འགྲོ་བ་ རིས་ སོ་སོ ར་ མ་ འདྲེས་པ ར་ ཡང་ རིས་ སོ་སོ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ནི་ མི་རིགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>then it cannot be right that beings are consistently reborn in their own types.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ ཐོབ་པ ར་ ཡང་ མི་རིགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What is more, it would be impossible for anyone to obtain the fruit of being an arhat.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དེ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ན་ ལས་ དགེ་བ་ དང་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ དབང་ གིས་ མཐོ་རིས་ དང་ ངན་སོང་ ལ་སོགས་ པར་རིས་ ཐ་དད་ པར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Therefore, O Great King, through virtuous and nonvirtuous actions beings are reborn as different types, such as those in the heavens and those in the lower realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ ལྷ་ རྣམས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ མི་ལ་ སོགས་པ་ གཞན་ རྣམས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ འམ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ དྲིས་པ་ ནི་ དེ་དེ་ བཞིན་ ལགས་ ཏེ །_ |#| དེ་དེ་ ལྟར་ ལགས་སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$15 “O Great King, regarding your question as to whether gods that die are reborn as other types of beings, such as humans and the like, the answer is ‘yes.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཡེ་ མེད་པར་ གྱུར་ ཏེ་ |#| མེ་ ཤི་བ འི་ ཐལ་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ཡེ་ མ་ མཆིས་ སམ་ ཞེས་ གསུངས་པ་ ནི་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ མ་ ལགས་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$16 “O Great King, regarding your question as to whether sentient beings die and become utterly nonexistent, like the ashes of a fire that has died out, and as to whether rebirth is utterly nonexistent, the answer is ‘no.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དཔེར་ན་ ས་བོན་ ཡོད་ ན་ འབྲས་བུ་འབྱུང་ སྟེ །_ |#| ཚེ་ འདི་ ས་བོན་ ལྟ་བུ་ ལས་ ཚེ་ ཕྱི་མ་ འབྲས་བུ་ ལྟ་བུ་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, just as when you have a seed, a fruit will come forth, so from the seed of this life the fruit of the next life comes about.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཉི་མ་ ཤར་ ནས་ ཁད་ ཀྱིས་ ནུབ་ སྟེ་ སྨག་ ཏུ་ གྱུར་པ་ ལས་ ཡང་ ནང་པ ར་ འཆར་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ ཚེ་ འདི་ འཕོས་ ནས་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བ་ཕྱི་མ་ ལེན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, just as the sun rises, slowly sets, becomes obscured, and then rises again the following morning, so too one passes from this life and takes rebirth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ ཕྱི་མ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ཡེ་ མ་ མཆིས་ ན་ འགྲོ་བ་ རྣམས་ ཟད་པ འི་ རིགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, sentient beings would become extinct species if they died without any subsequent rebirth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཕྱི་རོལ་ གྱི་ རྩྭ་ དང་ ཤིང་ རྣམས་ ཀྱང་ དུས་ ཀྱི་ དབང་ གིས་ བསྐམས་པ་ དེ་ཡང་ ཕྱིར་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, if we take the grass and trees outside too, those that have withered will grow again through the changing of the seasons.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ སེམས་ཅན་ རྣམས་ ལས་ དང་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ དུས་འགྱུར་ བ་ དང་ འདྲ་བ འི་ དབང་ གིས་ སྐྱེ་བ་ དང་ འཆི་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, sentient beings will be reborn and die through actions and afflicted emotions, which are like the changing of the seasons.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ན་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཚེ་ ཕྱི་མ་ ངེས་པ ར་ ཡོད་པར་ མཁྱེན་པ ར་ མཛོད་ ཅིག _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>So, O Great King, know that there are future lives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ འདི་ ནས་ [147b]  ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཕ་ དང་ །_ མེས་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་མེས་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཐོག་མ་ མེད་པ་ ནས་ བཟུང་བ འི་ བར་ དུ་ གཅིག་ ནས་ གཅིག་ ཏུ་ བརྒྱུད་པ འི་ རིས་ འཐུན་པ་ རྣམས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཕ་རོལ་ ན་ སྐྱེ་བ་ མི་ ལེན་པ ར་ འདི་ ན་ ཅི་ སྤྱོད་པ་ བཞིན་ འགྲོགས་ ཏེ་ གནས་ སོ་ ཞེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆི་ ན །_ |#| དེ་དེ་ ལྟར་ ལགས་ སམ །_ ཞེས་ གསུང་བ་ ནི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$17 “O Great King, you asked whether [147.b] it is as the worldly say it is. |#| You asked whether all sentient beings after their deaths live on, befriending their kin in a beginningless lineage, including parents, grandparents, great-grandparents, and so forth, and not taking rebirth in a future life but living just as they did in this life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འདི་ ན་ ཕ་ དང་ བུ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ གཅིག་ ལ་ གཅིག་ སྣང་བ་ ནི་ གཟུགས་ དངོས་པོ་ ཅན་ གཅིག་ ལ་ གཅིག་ སྣང་ གི །_། སེམས་ གཅིག་ གིས་ གཅིག་ མཐོང་བ་ ནི་ མ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, in this life, when a parent or a child and the like see each other, it is one embodied being seeing another, not one mind seeing another.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཟུགས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུང་པོ་ འདིར་ ཞིག་ སྟེ་ མེད་ ན །_ |#| ཕ་རོལ་ ན་ སེམས་ གཅིག་ ལ་ གཅིག་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ སྣང་ སྟེ་ |#| འགྲོགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If, in this life, the body perishes and is gone, then in the hereafter how would one mind see another and befriend it?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ ཕ་ དང་ །_ མེས་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་མེས་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ད་ལྟ ར་ ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ བུ་ཚ་ གཟུགས་ ཡོད་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ མི་ མཐོང་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Children, nephews, and nieces who are alive and have physical forms cannot even see their deceased parents, grandparents, and great-grandparents.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ ལུས་མེད་ པས་ ཕ་ དང་ །_ མེས་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་མེས་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ གཟུགས་ མེད་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ མཐོང་ ནས་ |#| འགྲོགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Then how would disembodied deceased people see and befriend their formless parents, grandparents, and great-grandparents?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ འདི་ ན་ ཕ་ དང་ །_ བུ་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ མང་པོ་ འགྲོགས་པ འི་ དུས་ ན་ ཡང་ གཟུགས་ སོ་སོ ར་ སྣང་བ་ ལས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$18 “What is more, O Great King, in this life, when the many parents, children, and other relatives get together, even then, it is only their respective physical forms that appear.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མ་ གཏོགས་པ་ རང་ གི་ སེམས་ ཀྱང་ རང་ གིས་ མི་ མཐོང་ ན་ |#| སྤད་ དང་ སྤུན་ གྱི་ སེམས་ གཅིག་ གིས་ གཅིག་ ལྟ་ ག་ལ་ མཐོང་ ན</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Unable to see even their own minds,#22 how could children and other relatives ever see each other’s minds?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ མཐོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How would they see them after death?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕ་རོལ་ ན་ སྤད་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ དང་ །_ མེས་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་མེས་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ སྣང་ ནས་ |#| འགྲོགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How would they, in an afterlife, first see the children, relatives, grandparents, and great-grandparents and then befriend them?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཐོག་མ་ མེད་པ འི་ དུས་ ན་ དེ་བ ས་ སྔ་བ་ མེད་པ འི་ མེས་པོ་ དང་ །_ ད་ལྟ འི་ བུ་ ཚ་ རྣམས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ན་ འགྲོགས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$19 “O Great King, let us suppose that an ancestor, one who had no one before him at any point in beginningless time, and his presently existing descendants were to befriend each other in a future life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ད་ལྟ་ མི འི་ རུས་ དང་ །_ རིགས་ དང་ །_ ཕྱོགས་ དང་ །_ རིས་ མི་ གཅིག་པ་ ཐ་དད་པ་ མང་པོ་ ཇི་སྙེད་པ་ རྣམས་ སོ་སོ ར་ དགྲ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ རྣམས་ དང་ །_ གནས་ གང་ ན་ འདུག་པ་ དང་ །_ རུས་རིགས་ གཅིག་པ་ དང་ །_ སྐད་ དང་ ཆ་ལུགས་ མ་ ཐོས་པ་ དང་ མ་ མཐོང་བ་ དག་ ཀྱང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Now, there are at present many different clans, castes, factions, and parties, some of which have become enemies of each other and whose places of residence, associates of clan and caste, language, and style of dress are neither heard of nor seen.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐོག་མ་ མེས་པོ་ གཅིག་ ལས་ གྱེས་པ་ ཡིན་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Suppose that they too issued from the same original ancestor.#23</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ད་ལྟ ར་ སྤད་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ དང་ མེས་པོ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ འགྲོགས་ མི་ འགྲོགས་ ཀྱི་ མཚམས་ སྤུན་ དང་ སྤད་ གང་ ལ་ གཟུང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>How would you delineate which children and relatives do or do not befriend present children, relatives, grandfathers, and so forth?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དང་པོ་ མེས་པོ་ ནས་ བཟུང་ སྟེ་ ད་ལྟ ར་ སྤུན་ དང་ སྤད་ ཀྱི་ བར་ དུ་ བརྒྱུད་པ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱང་ ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ སྤད་ [148a]  དང་ སྤུན་ འདྲ་བ ར་ སོ་སོ་ ན་ བརྩེ་ ཞིང་ གདུང་བ ར་ འདྲ་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The offspring from this first ancestor, up to and including the presently existing relatives and children, [148.a] would be alike in their respective affections [and antagonisms] for one another, just like the presently existing children and relatives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གང་ གང་ ནི་ འགྲོགས །_ གང་ གང་ ནི་ མི་ འགྲོགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If this is so, who befriends whom and who fails to befriend whom?#24</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ མི་ རྣམས་ སོ་སོ་ ནས་ བདག་ཅག་ གི་ མེས་པོ་ འདི་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ ཕྱོགས་ དང་ རིས་ བཟུང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$20 “People who are now living each apprehend their own factions and parties, saying, ‘So-and-so is our ancestor.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདག་ཅག་ འདི་ དང་ ཕ་ གཅིག་ གི་ བུ འོ་ ཞེས་ ཕྱོགས་ དང་ རིས་ སུ་ བཅད་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And they determine the factions and parties, saying, ‘We are children of the same father as so-and-so.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ གིས་ མེས་པོ་ ཞེས་ སོ་སོ ར་ བཟུང་བ་ དེ་ ཀུན་ གྱི་ ཡང་ ཕ་ དང་ །_ མེས་པོ་ དང་ །_ ཡང་མེས་ དང་ །_ ཞེ་ མེས་ ནས་ དང་པོ འི་ མེས་པོ་ ལ་ ཐུག་ གི་ བར་ དུ་ བརྒྱུད་པ་ ནི་ ད་ལྟ ར་ སོ་སོ ར་ ན་ བདག་ཅག་ གི་ མེས་པོ་ ཞེས་ བཟུང་བ་ ཡིན་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Suppose, too, that they now each grasped as ‘our ancestors’ the lineage of all the fathers, grandfathers, great-grandfathers, and great-great-grandfathers all the way down to the first ancestor—that is, the lineage of all those who respectively apprehend each other as ‘ancestors.’</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ སྨྲ་བ་ ལྟར་ འདི་ ནས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| སྐྱེ་བ་ མི་ ལེན་པ ར་ ཕ་རོལ་ ན་ སྤད་ དང་ སྤུན་ འགྲོགས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And suppose, following what the worldly say, these ancestors did not take rebirth after passing from this world, but instead befriended children and relatives in an afterlife.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ད་ལྟ ར་ རུས་རིགས་ དང་ །_ ཕྱོགས་ མི་ གཅིག་པ་ དང་ །_ དགྲ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ ཀུན་ ཀྱང་ ཕྱོགས་ གཅིག་ ནས་ འགྲོགས་ དགོས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Then they would have to befriend as one unified faction#25 the presently different clans, castes, and factions, as well as all those people that have become enemies, too.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ ཚེ་ འདི་ གཟུགས་ཅན་ དངོས་པོ ར་ སྣང་བ་ ཡང་ མུན་པ་ དང་ །_ ཕག་ ན་ འདུག་པ་ དག་ གཅིག་ གིས་ གཅིག་ མི་ མཐོང་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$21 “O Great King, in this life, although people appear as embodied entities, nonetheless when they are in the dark or hidden they do not see one another.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ སེམས་ཅན་ གཟུགས་ མེད་པ ས་ གཅིག་ གིས་ གཅིག་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ མཐོང་ ནས་ |#| འགྲོགས་ པར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Then, given that deceased beings do not have any bodies, how could they see and thus befriend one another?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ སེམས་ཅན་ གཟུགས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ མི་ མཐོང་བ འི་ གནས་ཡུལ་ མི་ གཅིག་པ་ དང་ །_ གནས་ ཐ་དད་པ་ དག་ ལ་ རང་ གི་ གཟུགས་ སྣང་བར་ སྟོན་ མི་ ནུས་ ན་ |#| ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཇི་ལྟ ར་ གཟུགས་ སྣང་བར་ སྟོན་ ནུས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, if embodied sentient beings who are alive now cannot even make their bodies visible to people in some other country or in the different places that they do not see, then how could they ever make their bodies visible after death?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ ཁ་ཅིག་ གིས་ གྲགས་པ་ དང་ རྙེད་པ་ དག་ བཙལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ བཟླས་པ འི་ གཏམ་ གྱིས་ གཞན་ སླུ་བ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ ལ་ གསན་པ ར་ མི་རིགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, you should not listen to worldly individuals who seek fame and gain#26 and thus deceive others with the tales they tell.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ འདི་ ན་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་པ་ རྣམས་ ཕ་རོལ་ དུ་ ཡང་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རམ །_ འདི་ ན་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་ ཉམ་ཆུང་བ་ རྣམས་ ཕ་རོལ་ དུ་ ཡང་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་ ཉམ་ཆུང་ བར་ འགྱུར་ རམ །_ འོན་ཏེ་ དེ་ གཉིས་ མི་ འདྲ་བ ར་ ཕན་ཚུན་ སྣོལ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེས་ གསུངས་པ་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་ ནི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$22 “O Great King, you asked whether those who are wealthy and proud in this life are also wealthy and proud in the hereafter, whether the poor and humble in this life go on to be poor and humble in the next, or whether people switch between the two.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སེམས་ཅན་ རྣམས་ ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ སྐྱེ་བ་ འདི་ ལ་ ཡང་ ལ་ལ་ སྐྱེས་མ་ ཐག་ ཏུ་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་པ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ ལས་ ལོ་ ལྔ་ བཅུ་ དང་ དྲུག་ཅུ་ ནས་ འཁོགས་པ འི་ བར་ དུ་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་ ཉམ་ [148b]  ཆུང་བ་ ཡང་ ཡོད །_ |#| ལ་ལ་ སྐྱེས་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, just take sentient beings in this life who have not yet died: some are wealthy and proud from the moment of birth, but are then poor and humble from the age of fifty or sixty onward into their old age;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཞོན་ དར་བ འི་ ཚེ་ ལ་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་པ་ ལས་ ལོ་ ལྔ་ བཅུ་ དང་ དྲུག་ཅུ་ ནས་ འཁོགས་པ འི་ བར་ དུ་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་པ་ དག་ ཡོད་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[148.b] others are poor and humble from birth and throughout their youth, but then, from the age of fifty or sixty up until their old age, they are wealthy and proud. |#| If that is so,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཕྱུག་དབུལ་ མི་རྟག་པ་ ལྟ་ཅི་ སྨོས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>then it is all the more obvious that people’s riches and poverty are impermanent when they are dead!</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དཔེར་ན་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ན་ རྩྭ་ དང་ ཤིང་ ལ་སོགས་ པ་ དྲོ་བ་ དང་ བརླན་པ འི་ རྐྱེན་ ཚོགས་པ འི་ ཚེ་ ནི་ ལོ་མ་ དང་ འདབ་མ་ རྒྱས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_ གྲང་ ཞིང་ རླན་ མེད་པ འི་ རྐྱེན་ གྱིས་ སྐམས་ པར་ འགྱུར་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, to use an analogy, in this world when conditions like warmth and moisture are present, grass, trees, and other plants grow leaves, but when it is cold and dry they wither.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཞིན་ དུ་ སྦྱིན་པ་ ལ་སོགས་པ འི་ རྐྱེན་ གྱིས་ ནི་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་པ ར་ འགྱུར་ ལ །_ རྐུ་འཕྲོག་ དང་ །_ སེར་སྣ འི་ དབང་ གིས་ ནི་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་ པ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Similarly, one becomes wealthy and proud due to conditions such as generosity, but poor and humble from theft and miserliness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སྦྱིན་པ་ རྒྱུན་ མ་ ཆད་པ ས་ ཚེ་རབས་ ནས་ ཚེ་རབས་ སུ་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་ རྒྱགས་པ་ ཡང་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$23 “O Great King, some people are wealthy and proud from life to life because they have always been generous.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྱོགས་ཆ་ དང་ སྦྱིན་པ་ ལ་ འགྱོད་པ་ བྱས་པ ས་ ཚེ་ འགའ་ དང་ །_ ཚེ་སྟོད་ སྨད་ ལ་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་པ་ ཡང་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Others are poor and humble in some lives, or at the beginning or end of certain lives, because they were partial or had regrets about giving.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དུས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དུ་ རྐུ་འཕྲོག་ དང་ སེར་ སྣ་ དག་ ལ་ གནས་པ ས་ ཚེ་རབས་ ནས་ ཚེ་རབས་ སུ་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་པ་ ཡང་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Some are poor and humble life after life because they always stole or were miserly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྐུ་འཕྲོག་ དང་ སེར་སྣ་ ལ་ འགྱོད་པ་ བྱས་པ ས་ ཚེ་ འགའ་ འམ །_ ཚེ་སྟོད་ སྨད་ ལ་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་པ་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Yet others are wealthy and proud in some lives, or at the beginning or end of certain lives, because they regretted their theft and miserliness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སྦྱིན་པ འི་ རྐྱེན་ གྱིས་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་པ་ ཡང་ མི་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, being poor and humble does not come about through generosity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེར་སྣ འི་ དབང་ གིས་ ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་པ་ ཡང་ མི་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Being wealthy and proud does not come about through miserliness.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྱུག་ དྲེགས་པ་ དང་ དབུལ་ རྒུད་པ་ འདི་ གཉིས་ ཚེ་ སྔ་ཕྱི་ ལ་ རྗེ་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ལགས་སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One does not simply [arbitrarily] switch between riches and poverty from one life to the next.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ འདི་ ན་ རྟ་ དང་ །_ གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཞོན་པ་ དང་ །_ འདི་ ན་ གོས་ གྱོན་པ་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ ཐོགས་པ་ དང་ །_ འདི་ ན་ ཟས་ བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཏུང་བ་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ རྣམས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ ཡང་ དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ ཞོན་པ་ དང་ །_ གྱོན་པ་ དང་ །_ ཟ་ ཞིང་ འཐུང་ ངོ་ ཞེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆི་ ན་ དེ་དེ་ ལྟར་ ལགས་ སམ་ ཞེས་ གསུངས་པ་ ནི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$24 “O Great King, you asked whether what the worldly say is really true. |#| You asked whether those who, in this life, ride horses and elephants and so forth, wear fine clothes and ornaments, and eat food and drink, continue in future lives after their deaths to ride, dress, eat, and drink in the same ways.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ མི་ རྣམས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ ཚེ་ ལས་ དགེ་ སྡིག་ གང་ སྤྱད་པ་ བཞིན་ མཐོ་རིས་ དང་ ངན་སོང་ དག་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, when humans die, they take rebirth in the heavens or in the lower realms in line with how they had practiced virtuous or nonvirtuous actions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆི་བ་ ལྟར་ མ་ ལགས་སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, it is not as the worldly say it is.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ འདི འི་ ཆ་ལུགས་ ལྟར་ སྣང་བ་ ནི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$25 “What about an apparition of a deceased individual’s style of dress?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བར་སྣང་ གི་ ཁམས་ འདི་ ན་ དྲི་ཟ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ གྱི་ ཁམས་ དཔག་ ཏུ་ མེད་པ་ བསམ་ གྱིས་ མི་ ཁྱབ་པ་ [149a]  མཐར་ཐུག་པ་ མེད་པ་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In the heavenly realm there exists an unfathomable, unimaginable, limitless [149.a] world of gandharvas.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དྲི་ཟ་ འཆི་ཀ་ མ འི་ སེམས་ ལ་ཉེ་ བར་ འཇུག་པ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ འི་ རིགས་ ཡོད་ དེ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One type there is called the gandharva who preys upon the minds of those on the verge of death.#27</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ དྲི་ཟ འི་ ཟས་ བཙལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ཚེ་རབས་ སྔ་མ འི་ ལུས་ དང་ །_ གོས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ དང་ །_ ཆ་ལུགས་ ལྟ་བུ་ དག་ སྤྲུལ་པ ར་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In search of the food that gandharvas eat, they create an illusion of the body, clothes, ornaments, and style of dress of someone who lived previously.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ དེ འི་ ཆ་ལུགས་ དང་ གཏམ་ དག་བྱེད་ ཅིང་ སྤྲུལ་པ་ སྟོན་པ་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They thus create and display illusions of the style of dress and the speech of a deceased person.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འདི་ ལ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ དེ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>But there is more here, O Great King.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དྲི་ཟ་ ལས་མ་ གཏོགས་པ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ དང་ །_ ཤ་ཟ་ དང་ །_ འབྱུང་པོ་ ལ་སོགས་ པས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ ཕ འམ །_ བུ འམ །_ སྤུན་ ལ་ སོགས་པ་ བསླུ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ མི་མ་ཡིན་པ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Not only gandharvas, but other spirits, such as yakṣas, piśācas, and bhūtas, also seek to trick the deceased person’s father, sons, relatives, and so forth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ འི་ རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་ གྱིས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ གཏན་ཚིགས་ དང་ །_ ས་མལ་ དང་ །_ ལོ་རྒྱུས་ དག་ ཤེས་པ ར་ བྱས་ ནས་ |#| མི་མ་ཡིན་པ་ དེ འི་ བྱིན་ གྱིས་ ཕ་མ་ ལ་སོགས་ པས་ མཐོང་བ་ དང་ །_ རྨི་ལམ་ དུ་ འབྱུང་བ་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thus these demons use their worldly magical powers to know the distinctive signs, final resting place, and the history of the deceased individual, and then they use their demonic influence so that parents and others see and dream of that individual.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་ པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འདི་ ལ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ དེ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$26 “Furthermore, O Great King, consider the following.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྤད་ དང་ སྤུན་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཡུན་རིང་ པོ ར་ ལྷན་ཅིག་པ འི་ བག་ཆགས་ རྟས་པ ས་ མཐོང་བ་ དང་ རྨི་ལམ་ དུ་ སྣང་བ་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is due also to the maturation of habitual tendencies stemming from longstanding association that one sees children and relatives and that they appear in dreams.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དཔེར་ན་ མི་ ཞིག་ གིས་ ད་ལྟ ར་ ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ རང་ གི་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ཟླ འམ །_ བྲན་ ཁོལ་ ལམ །_ གཞན་ སུ་ ཡང་ རུང་བ་ དག་ དང་ འགྲོགས་པ་ དང་ །_ ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ ཀྱི་ བདེ་བ འམ །_ དགྲ་ རྐུན་ དང་ །_ འཐབ་རྩོད་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ བདེ་བ་ དང་ །_ སྡུག་བསྔལ་ གང་ཡང་ རུང་ བདག་ རྨིས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Suppose, for example, that a person dreamed of their own presently undeceased#28 parents, relatives, servants, or any others who might befriend them, and as well dreamed of their pleasures coming from various enjoyments, or their pleasures and pains from grappling with enemies or thieves.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ དེས་ རྨིས་པ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ གང་ རྨིས་པ འི་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ཟླ འམ །_ བྲན་ ཁོལ་ ལམ་ གཞན་ སུ་ ཡང་ རུང་བ་ རྨི་ལམ་ ན་ སྣང་བ་ དེས་ ཚོར་བ་ ཡོད་ ན་ |#| ནི་ རྨིས་པ་ དེ་ བདེན་པ་ ཡིན་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If the parents, relatives, and servants they dreamed of, or any others appearing in their dream, actually were to have the feelings in question, just as that person dreamed they did, then that of which they dreamed would have been real.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེས་ རྨིས་པ འི་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ཟླ འམ །_ བྲན་ ཁོལ་ ལམ །_ གཞན་ སུ་ ཡང་ རུང་བ་ རྨི་ལམ་ ན་ སྣང་བ་ དེ་ བདེན་པ ར་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ བཟུང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>But how could the parents, relatives, and servants they dreamed of, or any others appearing in their dream, ever be thought to be real?#29</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཡང་ གཅིག་ གིས་ རྨིས་ པ་ གཅིག་ གིས་ མི་ ཚོར་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, even among living people, that which one person dreams is never felt by another.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ རྨིས་པ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ དེ་ ཡིན་པ ར་ ག་ལ་ འགྱུར་ ཏེ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Then how could what is dreamed concerning a deceased person ever be that deceased person?#30</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བག་ཆགས་ རྟས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What is involved is the maturation of habitual tendencies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ བག་ཆགས་ ལགས་པ འི་ དཔེ་ ནི་ གཞན་ ཡང་ མཆིས་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$27 “O Great King, there is yet another analogy for this being a matter of habitual tendencies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་ ཞིག་ སྔོན་ཚེ་ སྟོད་ ལ་ མཆིས་པ འི་ མཁར་ དང་ །_ ཁང་པ་ དང་ །_ གྲོང་ གང་ཡིན་པ་ ཞིག་ [149b]  བོར་ ཏེ །_ |#| ཡུལ་ གཞན་ ཞིག་ ཏུ་ ཚེ་སྨད་ ལ་ འདུག་པ་ ན་ སྔོན་ གྱི་ གྲོང་ དེ་ཡང་ ཞིག་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Suppose that a person left whatever castles, houses, and cities they had been in during an earlier part of their life, and that in the later part of their life, [149.b] when they lived elsewhere, the city they knew previously was destroyed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>!སྔོན་ མི་ འདྲ་བ་ ལས་མི་ དེས་ སྔོན་ གྱི་ ཁང་པ འི་ དབྱིབས་ དང་ རྒྱ་ ཅི་འདྲ་ བ་མ་ ཞིག་པ །_ མ་ འདྲ་མ ས་པ་ རྨིས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>This person dreams of the shape and size of their house as they were when it was neither destroyed nor scattered about,#31 no different from before.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གྲོང་ དང་ ཁང་པ་ དེ་ ལ་ སེམས་ ཡོད་ ན་ |#| ནི་ ཁང་པ་ དེ འི་ སེམས་ སྣང་ དུ་ རུང་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If the city and the house were to have mental natures,#32 then the mental nature of that house might have actually appeared to them.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁང་ པ་ དང་ གྲོང་ དེས་ རྡོ་ བེམས་པོ་ ཡིན་ ན་ |#| མི་ དེས་ རྨིས་པ་ དེ་ ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ བག་ཆགས་ རྟས་པ་ མ་ ཡིན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>But since their house and city are earth and stone,#33 then why would what that person dreamed not be a maturation of their habitual tendencies?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ དན་རྟགས་ དང་ བཅས་པ་ ཡང་ ཁང་པ་ མ་ ཞིག་པ་ རྨིས་པ་ དང་ འདྲ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, that which has the distinctive signs of a now deceased person is comparable to the undestroyed house of one’s dreams.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ སེམས་ ཀྱང་ ལས་ གར་ འཐུན་ པར་ སྐྱེ་བ་ བླངས་ ཟིན་ ན་ |#| དེ་ སྣད་ དུ་ བཏུབ་ བམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And if the deceased individual’s mind too had already taken rebirth in accordance with their previous actions, then could they actually appear#34 to anyone?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དེ འི་ ཕྱིར་ བག་ཆགས་ མཐུ་ རྟས་པ འི་ དབང་ གིས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ གཏན་ཚིགས་ དང་ །_ ཆ་ལུགས་ མཐོང་བ་ དང་ རྨིས་པ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>We conclude, O Great King, that it is through the maturation of habitual tendencies that people see and dream of distinctive signs and styles of dress of now deceased individuals.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་ རལ་གྲི་ ལ་སོགས་པ འི་ གོ་མཚོན་ ཐོགས་པ་ དང་ །_ གོས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ གྱོན་པ་ དང་ །_ རྟ་ དང་ །_ གླང་པོ་ཆེ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཞོན་པ ར་ སྣང་བ་ དང་ རྨི་ལམ་ དུ་ འབྱུང་བ་ ཡང་ བག་ཆགས་ སྣང་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, the appearances and occurrences in dreams of the deceased holding swords and other weapons, wearing clothes and other ornaments, and riding their horses and elephants, and so forth are also just appearances due to habitual tendencies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁང་པ འི་ དཔེ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ རིག་པ ར་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>You should understand them along the lines of the analogy of the house.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ འདི་ ནས་ ཤི་འཕོས་པ་ ལ་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ ནམ །_ བུ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཉེ་ རིས་ རྣམས་ ཀྱིས་ བཟའ་བ་ དང་ །_ བཏུང་བ་ ཉུང་ངུ་ ཉུང་ངུར་ གཏད་པ་ དང་ །_ བསྔོས་པ་ ཡང་ བསྐུལ་པ་ མང་པོ འི་ བར་ དུ་ ཟད་པ ར་ མི་འགྱུར་བ ར་ ཟ་ ཞིང་ འཐུང་ ངོ་ ཞེས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆིས་ ན་ |#| དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལགས་ སམ །_ ཞེས་ གསུངས་པ་ ནི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$28 “O Great King, you asked whether it is as the worldly say it is. |#| You asked whether those who have passed on from this world can eat and drink inexhaustibly for many eons the small portions of food and drink given and dedicated to them by their parents, siblings and cousins, children, and other relatives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ གླིང་བཞི་པ་ ནས་ སྟོང་ གི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ གྱི་ ཁམས་ དང་ །_ སྟོང་ གཉིས་པ་ དང་ །_ སྟོང་གསུམ་ གྱི་ སྟོང་ ཆེན་པོ འི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ གྱི་ ཁམས་ དང་ །_ འཇིག་རྟེན་ གྱི་ ཁམས་ མཐའ་ཡས་པ་ དཔག་ ཏུ་ མེད་པ་ བསམ་ གྱིས་ མི་ ཁྱབ་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ན་བཟའ་བ་ དང་ བཏུང་བ་ ཉུང་ངུ་ ཉུང་ངུ ས་ དུས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དང་ །_ བསྐལ་པ་ མང་པོ ར་ ཟ་བ འི་ སེམས་ཅན་ གཟིགས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, anywhere, be it on the four continents, in the chiliocosms, the dichiliocosms, the trichiliocosms, or in the limitless, unfathomable, unimaginable world systems, have you ever seen a sentient being who consumes one small portion of food and drink all the time and over many eons?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གསན་ ནམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Have you ever heard of such a sentient being?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཡིད་བཞིན་ གྱི་ ནོར་བུ་ རིན་པོ་ཆེ་ ལ་ ཅི་ བསམས་པ འི་ འདོད་པ་ འབྱུང་བ་ འཁོར་ལོ ས་ སྒྱུར་བ འི་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ལ་ ཡོད་པ་ ཡང་ སྔོན་ བསྐལ་པ་ མང་པོ ར་ བསོད་ནམས་ ཀྱི་ ཚོགས་ ཚད་ མེད་པ ས་ [150a]  བསགས་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ |#| གནམ་ ནས་ བབས་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, though the Cakravartin king has a wish-fulfilling gem that gives whatever he might wish, it came to exist because of immeasurable [150.a] collections of merit collected earlier over numerous eons—it did not fall from the sky or emerge accidentally.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གློ་བུར་ དུ་ བྱུང་བ་ ནི་ མ་ ཡིན་ ན་བཟའ་བ་ དང་ བཏུང་བ་ ཉུང་ངུ་ དེ་ བསྐལ་པ་ མཐ འི་ བར་ དུ་ མི་ཟད་པ་ དེ་ རིགས་ ལགས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Is it then reasonable that this small portion of food and drink would remain unexpended until the end of the eon?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ ཕ་སྤད་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ གཅིག་ ལ་ གཅིག་ འབྲེལ་ པར་ འཛིན་པ་ ཕན་པ ར་ འདོད་པ་ རྣམས་ ད་ལྟ ར་ མ་ ཤི་བ་ ལུས་ དང་ ལྡན་པ་ ཡང་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$29 “O Great King, suppose that some living parents, children, siblings, and cousins, who have a mutual relationship and wish to be of benefit to one another, have not yet died and are still physically embodied.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཅིག་ ཡུལ་ གཞན་ དུ་ སོང་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And suppose one of them went off to another country.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ལ་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ བུ འམ །_ སྤུན་ གང་ཡང་ རུང་བ ས་ ཟས་སྐོམ་ མང་པོ ར་ སྦྱིན་ ནོ་ གསོལ་ ལོ་ ཞེས་ བསྔོས་པ་ ཡང་ ཡུལ་ གཞན་ དུ་ སོང་བ འི་ རྨི་ལམ་ དུ་ ཡང་ མི་ འབྱུང་ ན་ |#| དངོས་པོ ར་ ཟ་ ཞིང་ འཐུང་བ་ ལྟ་ ག་ལ་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Although any of the parents, children, siblings, or cousins might resolve to give and offer a lot of food and drink to that person, none of that would appear to the person who had gone off to the other country, even in their dreams—let alone food and drink in reality.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ ལ་ བསྔོས་ ཞིང་ གཏད་པ་ ཟ་ ཞིང་ འཐུང་བ་ ལྟ་ ག་ལ་ ཡོད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>So why even mention food and drink dedicated to people who have died and have no body?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| སེམས་ ལུས་ དང་ བྲལ་བ་ དེས་ བུ་ དང་ སྤུན་ ལ་སོགས་ པས་ གཏད་པ འི་ ཟས་ དང་ །_ སྐོམ་ དངོས་པོ་ ཅན་ འདི་དག་ སེམས་ དངོས་པོ་ མེད་པ་ གཟུགས་ མེད་པ ས་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ བདག་པོ་ བྱེད་པ ར་ འགྱུར །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, how would those people, whose minds have separated from their bodies after death, use their immaterial and formless minds to take possession of the real items of food and drink provided to them by their children, siblings, and the like?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Why would this be a problem?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཟའ་བ་ དང་ བཅའ་བ་ ནི་ ལུས་ ཡོད་པ འི་ ཡན་ལག་ གི་ རྩོལ་བ་ ལ་ རག་ ལུས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The answer is that eating and chewing depend on the workings of body parts.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ ལ་ ལུས་ ཀྱི་ ཡན་ལག་ དེ འི་ རྩོལ་བ་ ཡོད་ དམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In that case, are the workings of the parts of the body to be found present in the mind?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ གསོལ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$30 The Great King then asked,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལགས་ ན་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ལ་ འདི་ ན་ ཕན་ འདོགས་པ འི་ བཟའ་བཏུང་ དང་ །_ བཞོན་པ་ དང་ །_ གོས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ གཏོང་བ་ འདི་དག་ ལ་དོན་ མ་ མཆིས་པ་ ལགས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One, if that is the case, then is it useless to offer deceased individuals the food, drink, mounts, clothes, and ornaments that were beneficial to them in the present world?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$31 The Blessed One replied,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་ པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ དེས་ ལས་ གང་ སྤྱད་པ འི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ ས་ འགྲོ་བ་ རིས་ ཐ་དད་པ་ གང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་པ་ དེ་ |#| ལ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“O Great King, take the case where a deceased person is being reborn in one of various different states of being because actions he had done are ripening.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་དགེ་བ་ དང་ མ་ འབྲེལ་པ འི་ བསོད་ནམས་ ཀྱི་ ཚོགས་ སུ་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ ལས་ དགེ་བ་ སྣ་ཚོགས་ པས་ བསྟངས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And suppose people help#35 that person by [dedicating to him] all sorts of virtuous actions that will constitute a collection of merit without any nonvirtue.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཐོ་རིས་ དང་ ཐར་པ ར་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་ ལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In that case, the person will be reborn in higher states, or attain liberation.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གལ་ཏེ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ བླངས་པ་ ཞིག་ ལ་ བསོད་ནམས་ སུ་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ ལས་ དགེ་བ་ ཞིག་ གིས་ བསྟངས་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>On the other hand, when someone has already taken rebirth, then if one aids#36 him through [the dedication of] a virtuous action that constitutes merit,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བ་ བླངས་པ་ དེས་ ནོར་ རྙེད་པ་ དང་ །_ ལོ་ལེགས་པ་ དང་ །_ འདོད་པ འི་ ལོངས་སྤྱོད་ འཕེལ་བ་ དང་ །_ འགྲོ་བ་ གཞན་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱིས་ མཆོད་ ཅིང་ བཀུར་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ ཕན་པ་ ཡོད་ ཀྱི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>that will aid the already reborn person to gain wealth, have good crops, more and more of the pleasures he wishes, as well as honor and respect from all his other fellow beings.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ [150b]  མི་ ལེན་པ ར་ གཤིན་ གྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཡོད་ ནས་ |#| བཟའ་བཏུང་ དང་ །_ བཞོན་པ་ དང་ །_ གོས་ དང་ །_ རྒྱན་ དག་ བདག་པོ ར་ བྱེད་པ་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>However, it is not so that the deceased individual stays on in the ‘world of Death,’#37 without rebirth, [150.b] and taking on food and drink, mounts, clothing, and ornaments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ གང་ གིས་ མཐོང་བ་ དང་ །_ ཕ་མ་ ལ་སོགས་ པས་ རྨི་ལམ་ དུ་ རྨིས་ ཏེ །_ |#| ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ལས་ བསྔོས་ པ ས་ གཤིན་ དེ་ བཟའ་བཏུང་ གིས་ མགུ འོ །_། |#| བཞོན་པ་ ཞོན་ ནོ །_། |#| གོས་ གྱོན་ ནོ །_། |#| རྒྱན་ ཐོགས་ སོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$32 “O Great King, suppose people say that things seen by the worldly and dreamed of by parents and others are dedicated to the deceased,#38 and that consequently the dead person is satisfied with the food and drink, rides the mounts, and wears the clothes and ornaments.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>!ཞེས་ སྨྲ་ ཞིང་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ སྣང་བ་ དེ་ཡང་ བཟའ་བཏུང་ གིས་ མི་ མགུ འོ །_། |#| བཞོན་པ་ མེད་ དོ །_། |#| གོས་ མི་ གྱོན་ ནོ །_། |#| རྒྱན་ མི་ ཐོགས་ སོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ སྨྲ་ ཞིང་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ སྣང་བ་ དག་ དྲི་ཟ་ འཆི་ཀ འི་ སེམས་ ལ་ཉེ་ བར་ འཇུག་པ་ དང་ །_ མི་མ་ཡིན་པ་ དག་ གིས་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ སྣང་བར་ བྱེད་པ་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>While this might appear to be so,#39 there are demons and gandharvas who prey upon the minds of those on the verge of death, and who make such apparitions manifest in that way and [make them seem to be] saying they are unsatisfied with the food and drink, do not have the mounts, and do not wear the clothes and ornaments.#40</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ སེམས་ཅན་ དག་ འདི་ ནས་ ཚེ་ འཕོ་ ཁ་ ན་ ཕ་མ འམ །_ སྤུན་ ནམ །_ བུ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ་ གཏམ་ བྱས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཚིག་ ཅི་ སྨྲས་པ་ དང་ །_ གཟུགས་ ཅི་འདྲ་བ་ དག་ དེ་ |#| ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཕྱིས་ ཕ་མ་ དང་ །_ སྤུན་ ནམ །_ བུ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ་ དེ་ སྔོན་ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ དུས་ ན་ གཏམ་ བྱས་པ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ སྨྲ་བ་ དང་ གཟུགས་བྱད་ སྟོན་ ཏེ |#| དེ་ལྟ་ བུ་ མཐོང་བ་ དང་ སྟོན་པ་ ཡོད་ ཅེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$33 “O Great King, the worldly say the following: whatever words sentient beings say and stories they tell, and whatever physical features they exhibit to their parents, siblings, and so forth when on the verge of death, later, after death, they will tell the same stories and so forth to their parents, siblings, and children that they had told earlier before they died, and they will exhibit the same physical features to them later as they had earlier before their death—such visions and exhibitions supposedly exist.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ མཆི་ ན །_ |#| དེ་ལྟ ར་ ལགས་ སམ་ མ་ ལགས་ ཞེས་ གསུངས་པ་ ནི །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The Great King has asked whether what the worldly say is true or not.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སྨྲ་བ་ ནི་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$34 “O Great King, take the case of speech.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལུས་ ཡོད་པ འི་ ཁ་ ལྕེ་ ལ་ བརྟེན་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Speech depends upon the vocal tract of an embodied person.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྨྲ་བ་ ལགས་ ན་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ ལུས་ ནི་ འདིར་ བཞག་ ན་ |#| སེམས་ གཟུགས་ མེད་པ་ དེ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ སྨྲ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>So then, if the body of the dead person is left behind in this world, how could their incorporeal mind ever speak?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་སྟེ་ ཤི་བ་ དེ་ ལ་ ལུས་ ཡོད་ དོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ ནི་ སྐྱེ་བ་ བླངས་པ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ |#| དེ་ ལ་ ཕ་མ་ དགོས་པ ས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Now, when we say that a dead person has a body, we mean that they have taken rebirth, for which parents were required.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཤིན་ གྱི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཡང་ མེད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>So there is no ‘world of Death’ either.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དེ་ལྟ་ བུ འི་ ཚེ་ མ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ མཚན་མ་ དང་ དན་རྟགས་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ གང་དག་ སྨྲ་བ་ ནི་ དྲི་ཟ་ ཁྱབ་བྱེད་ ཅེས་བྱ་བ འི་ རིགས་ ཡོད་པ ས་ བྱེད་ དེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$35 “O Great King, what the worldly call characteristics and distinctive signs of the living#41 are things fabricated by a type of gandharva called the pervader .</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དཔེར་ན་ རླུང་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ ཐང་ དང་ ཀླུང་ ཡངས་ པ་ དག་ ཏུ་ དུས་ གཅིག་ ཏུ་ རླུང་ལྡང་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ འཆི་ འཕོ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཀྱི་ སེམས་ ལ་ ཁྱབ་པ ར་ བྱེད་པ འི་ རིགས་ དྲི་ཟ་ བི་ ཙ་ན་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ དང་ །_ གནོད་སྦྱིན་ སྨྲ་ འདོད་ ཀྱི་ རིགས་ དང་ །_ འབྱུང་པོ་ བར་ ཧི་ ནི་ ཏ་ ཀུན་ ཏུ་ རྟོགས་ འདོད་ ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ དག་ གིས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The so-called vicana sorts of gandharvas, the talkative sorts of yakṣas, and the inquisitive bar hi ni ta sorts of bhūtas pervade the minds of all the dying, just like a strong wind that instantly blows over the wide plains and waters.#42</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསྒྲུབས་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They conjure up#43 such things.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མི་མ་ཡིན་པ་ དེ་དག་ [151a]  གིས་ ཤི་བ་ དེས་ སྔོན་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ གཏམ་ བྱས་པ་ དང་ །_ ཆ་ལུགས་ ཀྱི་ དན་རྟགས་ དག་ འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ དག་ བསླུ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ སྟོན་ ཅིང་ སྨྲ་བ་ དག་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And then, [151.a] in order to trick the worldly, these demons tell stories in the same way the deceased people used to do earlier, and exhibit their characteristic styles of dress.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཚེ་ ལྷ་ སྦྱིན་ དེ་ ན་ འདུག་པ ས་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ དེ་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསུངས་པ་ དེ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ མ་ ཆེས་ ནས །_ |#| བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$36 At that time Devadatta was present and, not believing what the Blessed One had said, he questioned him:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གཽ་ ཏ་ མ་ སེམས་ཅན་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ |#| ཅིར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ དན་རྟགས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ན་ ཡོད་པ་ དང་ མེད་པ་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Gautama, you have explained whatever distinctive signs there are, or are not, in the afterlife that follows death.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མས་ ཐོག་མ་ སུ་ ལ་ གསན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>From whom did you first hear about them, Gautama?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དུས་ ནམ་ གྱི་ ཚེ་ མཁྱེན་པ ར་ མཛད །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When did you come to know about them?</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གསན་པ་ དང་ མཁྱེན་པ ར་ མཛད་པ འི་ གྲོགས་པོ་ ནི་ སུ་ ལགས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Who heard and knew about them along with you?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$37 The Blessed One replied,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ སྦྱིན་ ངས་ ནི་ རང་ གི་ ལུས་ བཏང་བ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ དཀའ་བ་ མང་པོ་ དག་ བསྐལ་པ་ གྲངས་མེད་ པར་ སྤྱད་ དེ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Devadatta, for countless eons I practiced numerous sorts of austerities, such as sacrificing my body;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྒྲིབ་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ནི་ སྦྱངས །_ |#| ཚོགས་ཆེན་ པོ་ ཡང་དག་ པར་ བསགས་པ ས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མཁྱེན་པ འི་ ཡེ་ཤེས་ ཐོབ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>I purified all obstructions, perfectly accumulated a great collection of merit, and thus attained omniscient wisdom.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདས་པ འི་ དུས་ ན་ སྔོན་བྱུང་བ་ དང་ །_ ད་ལྟ ར་ གྱི་ དུས་ ན་ ཕྱོགས་ བཅུ་ མཐའ་ཡས་པ་ ན་ ཤེས་བྱ་ གང་དག་ ཅི་ ཡོད་པ་ དང་ །_ མ་འོངས་པ འི་ དུས་ ན་ འབྱུང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ འི་ ཤེས་བྱ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ མི་ མཁྱེན་པ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ གང་ཡང་ མེད་ དེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>There is nothing I do not know concerning any knowable matter before me in the past or in the limitless ten directions in the present, or concerning all knowable matters that will occur in the future.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དཔེར་ན་ འཛམ་བུ འི་ གླིང་ འདིར་ ཉི་མ་ ཤར་བ་ དེ་ ཁད་ དང་ རིམ་གྱིས་ ཤར་བ་ མ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ |#| དུས་ གཅིག་ ཏུ་ གསལ་བ ར་ ཤར་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ ཤེས་བྱ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ སྐད་ཅིག་མ་ གཅིག་ ལ་ མཁྱེན་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$38 “Just as when the sun shines here in Jambudvīpa, it does not shine over things gradually or in stages, but shines clearly all at once, so too I know, in one instant, everything that can be known.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ང་ ནི་ རྣམ་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མཁྱེན་ པ འི་ ཡེ་ཤེས་ མངའ་བ་ ཞེས་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And thus it is said that I possess the exalted wisdom that knows all aspects.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་སྐད་ ཅེས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ་ ལ་ ཡང་ ལྷ་ སྦྱིན་ ཡིད་ མ་ ཆེས་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$39 Devadatta did not believe in these sorts of statements either.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐམས་ཅད་ མཁྱེན་པ་ མངའ་བ་ དེ་ ཉམས་སད་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ འཛམ་བུ་གླིང་ འདི་ ན་ ཤིང་ གི་ རིགས་ ཙན་དན་ དང་ །_ བླག་ ཤ་ དང་ །_ སེང་ལྡེང་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཤིང་ ཐ་དད་པ་ བརྒྱ་ སྟོང་ བྱེ་བ་ དག་ བཅད་ དེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>In order to test whether the Blessed One actually did possess omniscience, he cut samples of a vast number#44 of different sorts of wood, that is, of all the types of trees here on Jambudvīpa, including sandalwood, waved-leaf fig trees, catechu, and so forth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སོ་སོ ར་ བསྲེགས་ ནས་ ཐལ་བ འི་ ཕུར་མ་ བྱས་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He burnt them and made small bags for the ashes of each one.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རང་ གིས་ མི་ ནོར་བ ར་ བྱ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ཐལ་བ་ ལ་ ཤིང་ གང་དང་གང་ གི་ མིང་ ཡི་གེར་ བཏགས་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>So as not to be mistaken about which type of wood each bag of ash came from, he labelled each bag of ash with the appropriate name.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱི་ དྲུང་ དུ་ སོང་ ནས་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He then went to the Blessed One and asked,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ [151b]  ཁྱོད་ ལ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མཁྱེན་པ འི་ ཡེ་ཤེས་ མངའ་ ན །_ |#| འདི་ ཤིང་ གང་ གི་ ཐལ་བ་ འདི་ ཤིང་ གང་ གི་ ཐལ་བ་ ལགས་ ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One [151.b] , if you possess omniscient wisdom, then which bag of ash belongs to which tree?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མཐར་ཆགས་ སུ་ ཐལ་བ འི་ ཕུར་མ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ བསྟན་པ་ ལས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And he showed him the small bags of ashes one by one.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ ཤིང་ གང་ གི་ ཐལ་བ་ ཡིན་པ་ མ་ ནོར་བ ར་ འདི་ ནི་ ཙན་དན་ གྱི་ ཐལ་བ འོ །_། |#| འདི་ ནི་ བླག་ ཤ འི་ ཐལ་བ འོ །_། |#| འདི་ ནི་ སེང་ལྡེང་ གི་ ཐལ་བ འོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ ཐལ་བ འི་ ཕུར་མ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མ་ ནོར་བ ར་ བཤད་པ་ ལས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>For each small bag, the Blessed One explained unmistakenly which tree the ash had come from, saying, “This one is sandalwood ash. |#| This one is waved-leaf fig tree ash. |#| This one is catechu ash,” and so forth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ སྦྱིན་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ རྣམ་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ མཁྱེན་པ འི་ ཡེ་ཤེས་ མངའ་བ ར་ ཡིད་ཆེས་ པར་ གྱུར་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Devadatta thus came to believe that the Blessed One really did have omniscient wisdom.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཅིར་ འགྱུར་བ ར་ གསུངས་པ་ བདེན་པ ར་ བསམས་ ནས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Thinking that the Blessed One’s pronouncements on death were all true,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ བསྟོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>he praised him in the following terms:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ནི་ ཀུན་མཁྱེན་ ལགས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$40 “The Blessed One is omniscient;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤིང་ མང་ ཐལ་བ འི་ བྱེ་བྲག་ རྣམས །_། མ་ གཟིགས་ མ་ གསན་ ངེས་པ ར་ མཁྱེན །_། |#| ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ཅི་ འགྱུར་ གསུངས་པ་ ངེས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>What he has said about death must be true. |#| Without previously seeing them or hearing of them, He recognizes these different varieties of ashes of wood.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཞེས་ བསྟོད་ ནས་ སྤོབས་པ་ མེད་པར་ གྱུར་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He thus praised him and was left at a loss for words.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཚེ་ ཤཱཀྱ་ མིང་ ཆེན་ དེ་ ན་ འདུག་པ ས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$41 At that time the Śākya Mahānāman was present, too.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཅིར་ འགྱུར་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ མ་ ཆེས་ ནས་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Not believing what the Blessed One had said about death, he asked,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ འི་ སེམས་ཅན་ རྣམས་ ཅིར་ འགྱུར་བ་ གསུངས་པ་ དེ་ མངོན་སུམ་ དུ་ གཟིགས་ སམ་ འོན་ཏེ་ གཞན་ ཞིག་ ལ་ གསན་པ་ ལགས །_ དེ་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་པ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One, did you directly perceive what you have explained about the death of beings, or did you hear it from someone else?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$42 The Blessed One replied,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མིང་ ཆེན་ ང འི་ སངས་རྒྱས་ ཀྱི་ སྤྱན་ གྱིས་ མི་ གཟིགས་པ་ ནི་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ ན་ མེད་ དེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Mahānāman, there is nothing in the world that my buddha-eye does not see.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱུ་རུ་ར་ རློན་པ་ ལག་མཐིལ་ དུ་ བཞག་ ན་ ལག་ པ འི་ བྱེ་བྲག་ ཐམས་ཅད་ གསལ་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When a fresh gooseberry is placed in the palm of the hand, all the features of the hand are conspicuous in it.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བཞིན་ དུ་དུ ས་ གསུམ་ གྱི་ ཤེས་བྱ་ ལ་ ངས་ མ་ གཟིགས་པ་ ཅི་ཡང་ མི་ མངའ་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Likewise, there is no knowable thing whatsoever in the three times that I do not see.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐོས་པ་ ལ་ བརྟེན་པ་ ནི་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>I do not base myself on hearsay.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤཱཀྱ་ མིང་ ཆེན་ གྱིས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ གཟིགས་པ་ དེ་ བདེན་ བརྫུན་ ཉམས་སད་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ སེར་ སྐྱ འི་ གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ ཆེན་པོ ར་ སོང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$43 In order to test whether the Buddha was truly omniscient or not, Śākya Mahānāman then went to the great city of Kapilavastu.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁྱིམ་ ཇི་སྙེད་ ཡོད་པ་ ལ་ འབྲས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུར་མ་ རེ་རེ་ བླངས་ ཏེ །_ |#| རང་ གིས་ འབྲས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུར་མ་ མི་གང་ ལ་ བླངས་པ་ མི་ ནོར་བ ར་ བྱ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ཤཱཀྱ་ གང་ ལ་ བླངས་པ འི་ མིང་ རྣམས་ བྲིས་ ཏེ །_ |#| འབྲས་ ཕུར་མ འི་ ནང་ དུ་ བཅུག་ ནས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>From each household, he took a small bag of rice, and so that he would not mistake whose rice was whose, he wrote down the name of every Śākya he took them from and put these names inside the small bags.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འབྲས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུར་མ་ གླང་པོ་ཆེ འི་ [152a]  ཁལ་ ལོངས་པ་ ཅིག་ དང་ །_ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱི་ སྤྱན་སྔ ར་ སོང་ སྟེ་ |#| ཕྱིན་པ་ དང་ །_ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When the rice bags came to be a full load for an elephant, [152.a] he went to the Blessed One and requested of him,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ སངས་རྒྱས་ ཀྱི་ སྤྱན་ གྱིས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ གཟིགས་ ན་ |#| འབྲས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུར་མ་ འདི་དག་ མི་ དབྱེ་བ ར་ ཤཱཀྱ་ གང་ གང་ གི་ འབྲས་ གང་ གང་ ལགས་པ་ མཁྱེན་པ ར་ མཛོད་ ཅིག་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ནས</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One, if your buddha-eye sees all, then please recognize, without opening them, which Śākyas’ small bags of rice are which.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གླང་པོ་ཆེ འི་ ཁལ་ གྱི་ འབྲས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུར་མ་ རྣམས་ དྲུང་ དུ་ བཞག་པ་ ལས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And he put down the elephant’s load of small bags in front of the Buddha.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ འབྲས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུར་མ་ རེ་རེ་ བླངས་ ཤིང་ འདི་ ཤཱཀྱ་ དགའ་བྱེད་ ཀྱིའོ །_། འདི་ ཤཱཀྱ་ ཀ་ ཡ འི་ འོ །_། |#| འདི་ ཤཱཀྱ་ འདོད་སྲེད་ ཀྱིའོ །_། ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ འབྲས་ ཕུར་མ་ རེ་རེ་ ལ་ ཤཱཀྱ་ འདི་ ཡི འོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ མིང་ མ་ ནོར་བ ར་ རིམ་པ ར་ རྫོགས་པ ར་ གསུངས་པ་ ལས །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$44 The Blessed One held up each small bag in turn and said, “This one belongs to Śākya Nandaka, this one belongs to Śākya Kaya, this one belongs to Śākya Desire,”#45 and so forth, assigning the appropriate Śākya to each bag of rice and thus unmistakenly, step by step, stating the names till they were finished.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ སངས་རྒྱས་ ཀྱི་ སྤྱན་ གྱིས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ གཟིགས་ པ་ ལ་ ཤཱཀྱ་ མིང་ ཆེན་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཡིད་ཆེས་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>With this, Śākya Mahānāman and the others were all convinced that the Blessed One’s buddha-eye saw all things.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཅིར་ འགྱུར་བ་ བཤད་པ་ ནི་ ངེས་ སོ་ སྙམ་ ནས །_ |#| བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ལ་ བསྟོད་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They thought that the Blessed One’s explanation about death was surely right and commended him as follows:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སངས་རྒྱས་ སྤྱན་ གྱིས་ ཐམས་ཅད་ གཟིགས །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$45 “With his buddha-eye, he sees all.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་པ་ ལྟར་ བརྫུན་ མི་ མངའ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Unlike the worldly, he does not lie.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤཱ་ ཀྱའི་ གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ ཇི་སྙེད་པ འི །_། འབྲས་ ཀྱི་ ཕུར་མ་ མ་ ནོར་ མཁྱེན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>He unmistakenly knows the small bags of rice Of everyone in Kapilavastu.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སེམས་ཅན་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ན །_། |#| ཇི་ལྟ ར་ སྣང་བ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ བརྫུན །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$46 “The world lies about beings’ deaths And how they appear in the beyond.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ གསུངས་པ་ མད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The Blessed One has spoken truly.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀུན་གཟིགས་ ཁྱོད་ ལ་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་ བསྟོད །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Praise and homage to you who sees all.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཅེས་ བསྟོད་ ནས་ སྤོབས་པ་ མེད་ དེ་ མི་སྨྲ་ བར་ འདུག་ གོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>They were at a loss for words after offering such praises, and thus remained silent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་ནས་ ཡབ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ འདི་སྐད་ ཅེས་ གསོལ་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$47 The father, the Great King, then spoke.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ སེམས་ཅན་ གང་དག་ གིས་ མཚམས་མེད་པ་ ལ་སོགས་ པ འི་ ལས་མི་ དགེ་བ་ དག་ བགྱིས་པ ས་ དེ འི་ རྣམ་པར་ སྨིན་པ་ མི་བཟད་པ་ མྱོང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One, there are sentient beings who have committed nonvirtues, such as the actions that bring immediate retribution, on account of which they come to experience the unbearable ripening of such actions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དག་ གིས་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ བགྱིས་ ན་ |#| བདེ་བ་ ཐོབ་པ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ བཤད་ དུ་ གསོལ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Please explain what sorts of things they should do to attain happiness.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ །_ ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སེམས་ཅན་ གང་དག་ གིས་ མཚམས་མེད་པ་ ལ་སོགས་ པ འི་ ལས་མི་ དགེ་བ་ བྱས་པ་ དག་ གིས་ སྒྱུ་ མེད་པ འི་ སེམས་ དང་བ ས་ རྣམ་ [152b]  པར་ སྨིན་པ་ ལ་ ཡིད་ཆེས་ པར་ བྱས་ ཏེ |#| སེམས་ཐག་པ་ ནས་ བཤགས་ ན་ འབྱང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$48 The Blessed One replied, “O Great King, those sentient beings who have committed nonvirtuous actions, like those actions that bring immediate retribution, will become pure if they sincerely believe in the [152.b] ripening of the actions and confess them deeply.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཆི་བ འི་ ཚེ་ མི་དགེ་བ་ སྔར་ བྱས་པ་ དག་ ལ་ འགྱོད་པ་ བསྐྱེད་ དེ །_ |#| སངས་རྒྱས་ དང་ །_ བྱང་ཆུབ་ སེམས་དཔའ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ ཕྱག་ འཚལ་ ཞིང་ སྐྱབས་ སུ་ གསོལ་ ན་ སྡིག་ པ་ འབྱང་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_། |#| མཐོ་རིས་ སུ་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>If, at death, they regret the negative actions they committed earlier, pay homage, and go for refuge to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas, their negativities will become pure; |#| such beings will also be reborn in high states.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ ཕྱི་མ་ མེད་པ འི་ འདུ་ཤེས་ བསྐྱེད་པ ར་ མི་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Do not think that there are no future lives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་པ་ ནི་ དབང་ཕྱུག་ དང་ །_ འདོད་རྒྱལ་ དང་ །_ གྱི་ ན་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ དག་ གིས་ བྱེད་པ ར་ མི་ བལྟ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nor should you think that rebirth is caused by God, arbitrarily, or through mere caprice and the like.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཇིག་རྟེན་པ འི་ བདེ་བ་ དང་ འཁོར་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ལ་ ཆགས་པ ར་ མི་ བྱ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Have no attachment to any worldly happiness or cyclic existence.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འཇིག་རྟེན་ འདི་ ནས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ འཕོ་ སྟེ །_ |#| སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་པ་ ན་ རྟག་པ་ འཕོ་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_། |#| ཆད་པ་ འགགས་ ཏེ་ མེད་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$49 “O Great King, when you pass from this world to the next and take rebirth, it is not something permanent that transmigrates in this way,#46 nor something that is extinguished, halted, and hence nonexistent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱུ་ མེད་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_། |#| རྒྱུ་ མེད་པ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_། |#| བྱེད་ པ་པོ ས་ བྱས་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is neither uncaused, nor arisen from something without a cause, nor made by an external agent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལས་ དང་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ འི་ རྒྱུ་རྐྱེན་པ་ ལས་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ བལྟ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Understand it to be produced by an aggregate of causes and conditions, that is, actions and afflictive emotions.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ ས་ གསོལ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$50 The Great King then asked,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ སེམས་ཅན་ རྣམས་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་པ་ དེ་དེ་ ལྟར་ རྟག་པ་ ཡང་ མི་ འཕོ །_། |#| ཆད་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ལགས །_ རྒྱུ་ མེད་ པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ལགས །_ བྱེད་པ་པོ ས་ ཀྱང་ མ་ བྱས །_ |#| འཇིག་རྟེན་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ཡང་ འགྲུབ་པ་ དེ་ རྟོགས་པ ར་ དཀའ་ ན་ |#| འདི་ ལ་ འཐུན་པ འི་ དཔེ་ འདི་ མཆིས་ སམ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“Blessed One, if the transmigration and rebirth of sentient beings is not the transmigration of something permanent, nor of something extinguished, nor without a cause, nor made by an external agent, and if, moreover, the established fact of rebirth in the world beyond is difficult to understand, are there any analogies for it?”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$51 The Blessed One replied,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ འདི་ ལ་ འཐུན་པ འི་ དཔེ་ བརྒྱད་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>“O Great King, there are eight analogies for rebirth:</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བླ་མ ས་ ཁ་ ཏོན་ བརྗོད་པ་ སློབ་མ ས་ ཤེས་པ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(1) the analogy of students learning that which is recited by the teacher,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མར་མེ་ ལས་མ ར་ མེ་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(2) a lamp being lit from another lamp,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ལོང་ ལས་ གཟུགས་བརྙན་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(3) a reflection occurring because of a mirror,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱ་ལ ས་ རྒྱ འི་ འབུར་ དང་ རི་མོ་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(4) an impression and image coming from a stamp,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ཤེལ་ ལས་ མེ་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(5) fire coming from a magnifying glass,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ས་བོན་ ལས་ མྱུ་གུ་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(6) a sprout arising from a seed,</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱུར་ ཞེས་ བརྗོད་པ ས་ འགྲམ་ཆུ་ ལྡང་བ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(7) the production of saliva when someone says the word ‘sour,’ and</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྲག་ཅ འི་ སྒྲ་ རྣམས་ ཀྱི་ དཔེ ས་ རྟོགས་པ ར་ བྱ་ སྟེ</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>(8) the sound of an echo.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དཔེ་ བརྒྱད་པོ་ འདི་དག་ གིས་ སྔ་མ་ སྔ་མ ས་ ནི་ ཕྱི་མ་ ཕྱི་མ་ རྣམས་ འབྱུང་བ་ ཡང་ ཡོད་པ་ ནི་ རྟག་པ་ འཕོ་བ་ མ་ཡིན་པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>O Great King, in these eight analogies, the fact that earlier things give rise to the later ones illustrates how nothing permanent transmigrates.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྱི་མ་ ཕྱི་མ་ ནི་ སྔ་མ་ སྔ་མ་ [153a]  རྣམས་ ལས་ འབྱུང་བ ས་ རྒྱུ་ མེད་པ་ ལས་ འབྱུང་བ་ མ་ཡིན་པ འི་ དཔེ་ དང་ །_ ཆད་པ་ འགག་པ་ མ་ཡིན་པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The fact that later things arise from [153.a] earlier ones illustrates how transmigration and rebirth do not occur without a cause and that they are not of something extinguished and halted.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ དཔེ་ འདི་དག་ ནི་ རྐྱེན་ གསུམ་ གསུམ་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་ འབྱུང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$52 “Furthermore, O Great King, all of these analogies are things that come about when three conditions are gathered together.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བླ་མ་ དང་ སློབ་མ་ དེ་ གཉིས་ དབང་པོ་ རྣམས་ ཚང་བ་ ལས་ ཁ་ཏོན་ འབྱུང་ ཞིང་ སྨྲ་ ཤེས་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When there are teachers, students, and sense faculties, we have recitation and language learning.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མར་ དང་ སྡོང་བུ་ དང་ སྣོད་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་མ ར་ མེ་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When there exist butter, wicks, and vessels, we have lamps.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ནམ་མཁའ་ དང་བ་ དང་ །_ གདོང་ དང་ མེ་ལོང་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་ གཟུགས་བརྙན་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When there are bright skies, faces, and mirrors, we have reflections.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱ་ དང་ འཇིམ་པ འི་ གོང་བུ་ དང་ སྐྱེས་བུ འི་ ལག་པ འི་ རྩོལ་བ་ རྣམས་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་ འབུར་ དང་ རི་མོ་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When there are signets, lumps of clay, and human manual effort, we have impressions and images from stamps.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤེལ་ དང་ ཉི་མ འི་ འོད་ དང་ རྩྭ་ཤིང་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་ མེ་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When there are crystals, sunlight, grass, and wood, we get fire.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ས་བོན་ དང་ ས་གཞི་ དང་ རླན་པ་ རྣམས་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་ མྱུ་གུ་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When there are seeds, earth, and moisture, we get sprouts.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚྭ་ དང་ ཚྭ་ ཆུ་ འཐུང་ མྱོང་བ་ དང་ །_ སྐྱུར་ ཞེས་ བརྗོད་པ་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་ འགྲམ་ ཆུ་ ལྡང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When there is salt, a previous experience of drinking salty water, and when the word ‘sour’ is pronounced, people then begin to salivate.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མིས་ བརྗོད་པ འི་ སྒྲ་ དང་ སྒྲ་ དྲག་པོ་ གཞན་ མེད་པ་ དང་ །_ རི་བྲག་ རྣམས་ ཚོགས་པ་ ལས་ བྲག་ཅ་ འབྱུང་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>When someone speaks, when there is no other loud sound, and when there is a nearby mountain, then an echo will occur.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ ནི་ སེམས་ཅན་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ནི་ བྱེད་པ་པོ ས་ མ་ བྱས་ ཏེ །_ |#| ལས་ དང་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ འི་ རྒྱུ་རྐྱེན་ གྱིས་ བསྐྱེད་པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>These are all analogies showing how sentient beings’ rebirths are not made by external agents, but are produced through the causal conditions of actions and afflictive emotions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ གཞན་ ཡང་ བླ་མ་ ནི་ ཚེ་ འདི འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$53 “Furthermore, O Great King, the teacher illustrates this life;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སློབ་མ་ ནི་ ཚེ་ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>the student illustrates future lives;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁ་ཏོན་ ནི་ རྣམ་པར་ ཤེས་པ་ ཉིང་མཚམས་ སྦྱོར་བ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>recitation illustrates how consciousness bridges the gap between lives.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མར་མེ་ སྔ་མ་ ནི་ ཚེ་ འདི འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The earlier lamp illustrates this present life;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྱི་མ་ ནི་ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>the later lamp illustrates future lives;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མར་མེ་ སྔ་མ་ ལས་ ཕྱི་མ་ བྱུང་བ་ ཡང་ སྔ་མ་ ཡོད་པ་ ནི་ རྟག་པ་ འཕོ་བ་ མ་ཡིན་ པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>though the later lamp arose from the earlier lamp, the fact that the one existed before the other illustrates how nothing permanent transmigrates.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕྱི་མ་ དེ་ སྔ་མ་ ལས་ བྱུང་བ་ རྒྱུ་ མེད་པ་ ལས་མ་ བྱུང་བ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>That the later one arose from the earlier one illustrates how things do not occur without causes.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ལོང་ ནི་ ཚེ་ འདི་ ཡོད་པ འི་ སྒོ་ ནས་ ཕྱི་མ་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ ལ །_ དངོས་པོ་ ཡང་ མི་ འཕོ་ ཞིང་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཡང་ ཡོད་ ངེས་པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The mirror illustrates how future lives exist because present lives exist, how nothing real transmigrates, and how future lives definitely do exist.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱ་ ནི་ འདིར་ ལས་ ཅི་ སྤྱད་པ་ འཐུན་ པར་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ ཡང་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་ པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The stamp illustrates how one takes rebirth in a future life in accordance with actions one has done in this life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ཤེལ་ ནི་ འགྲོ་བ་ རིས་ མི་ འདྲ་བ་ ནས་ མི་ འདྲ་བ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The magnifying glass illustrates how one exists as one type of being and is then reborn as another.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ས་བོན་ ནི་ འགགས་ ནས་ མེད་པར་ མི་འགྱུར་བ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The seed illustrates how one does not cease and become nonexistent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱུར་ ནི་ མྱོང་བ འི་ ལས་ ཀྱིས་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The sour taste illustrates how one takes rebirth due to actions one has experienced.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྒྲ་ ནི་ རྒྱུ་རྐྱེན་ ཚོགས་ ནས་ གནོད་པ འི་ རྐྱེན་ གཞན་ མེད་ ན་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The echoing sound illustrates how one takes a rebirth when causes and conditions are present without other annulling conditions;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>[153b]  གཅིག་པ་ དང་ ཐ་དད་པ་ མ་ཡིན་པ འི་ དཔེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>[153.b] it illustrates how a [reborn individual] is not the same as or different [from that of the earlier life].</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ དཔེ་ བརྒྱད་པོ་ འདི་ ཚང་བ ར་ མ་ སྨོས་ ཏེ །_ |#| འགའ་ཞིག་ བསྟན་ ན་ |#| དབང་ཕྱུག་ དང་ །_ འདོད་རྒྱལ་ དང་ །_ གྱི་ ན་ དང་ །_ རྒྱུ་ མེད་པར་ སྨྲ་བ་ དག་ གིས་ དགེ་སྦྱོང་ གཽ་ ཏ་ མ འི་ དཔེ་ འདི་དག་ ཁ་ཏོན་ གྱི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ འདི འི་ ཕུང་པོ་ དང་ །_ རྣམ་པར་ ཤེས་པ་ གཉིས་ མ་ བྲལ་བ ར་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ རྣམ་པར་ ཤེས་པ་ འཕོ་བ ར་ འགྱུར་ ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$54 “O Great King, if I had not explained all eight analogies but had taught only some of them, then those who maintain that rebirth is due to God, arbitrary, due to mere caprice, or without any causes would use the Śramaṇa Gautama’s analogy of recitation to say that consciousness will transmigrate to the next life without losing the aggregates and consciousness of this life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྨྲ་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute those who might say this, I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མར་མེ འི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ འདི་ དང་ ཕ་རོལ་ གཉི་ག ར་ ཕུང་པོ་ དུས་ གཅིག་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$55 “Some might use the analogy of the lamp to say that the aggregates in both this life and the next exist at one and the same time.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute them I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ལོང་ གི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ འདྲ་བ འི་ དཔེ་ ཡིན་པ ས་ གྲུམ་པོ་ ལས་ གྲུམ་པོ ར་ སྐྱེ །_ |#| དཀར་པོ་ ལས་ དཀར་པོ ར་ སྐྱེ འོ་ ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$56 “Some others might use the mirror analogy to say that the lame are reborn lame and the fair are reborn fair because the mirror illustrates similarity.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟེར་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute them I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱ འི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ ལྷ་ འཕོས་པ་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ །_ |#| མི་ འཕོས་པ་ མིར་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ངེས་པ འོ་ ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$57 “Others might use the analogy of the stamp to say that gods who have died are reborn as gods and that humans who have died are reborn as humans.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟེར་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute them I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ཤེལ་ གྱི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ མི་ འདྲ་བ འི་ དཔེ་ ཡིན་པ ས་ དགེ་བ ས་ ངན་སོང་ དང་ མི་དགེ་བ ས་ མཐོ་རིས་ འགྲུབ་བོ་ ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$58 “Yet others might use the analogy of the magnifying glass to say that from virtue come the lower realms and from nonvirtue comes high status because a magnifying glass illustrates dissimilarity.#47</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟེར་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute them I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ས་བོན་ གྱི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ ཤེས་པ་ གཅིག་ ལས་ མང་པོ ར་ འཕེལ་ ལོ་ ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$59 “Some might use the analogy of the seed to say that one consciousness grows to be many.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟེར་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute them I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱུར་ གྱི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ མྱོང་བ འི་ དཔེ་ ཡིན་པ ས་ ལྷ འི་ ལོ་རྒྱུས་ ཡོད་པ་ དག་ དགེ་བ འི་ བསོད་ནམས་ མ་ བྱས་ ཀྱང་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ འོ །_། |#| ངན་སོང་ གི་ ལོ་རྒྱུས་ ཡོད་པ་ དག་ མི་དགེ་བ་ མ་ བྱས་ ཀྱང་ ངན་སོང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_། |#| ཞེས་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$60 “Some too might use the analogy of a sour taste, because it illustrates experience, to say that those who have a history of rebirth as gods will be reborn as gods even though they have not done virtuous deeds, and that those who have a history of rebirth in the lower realms will be reborn in the lower realms even though they have done no nonvirtuous deeds.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟེར་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute them I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྒྲ འི་ དཔེ ས་ ནི་ བྱེད་པ་པོ འི་ དཔེ་ ཡིན་པ ས་ རྒྱུ་རྐྱེན་ ལས་མ་ བྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$61 “Yet some others might use the analogy of the echoing sound to say that rebirth does not come from causes and conditions, as they would maintain that such an analogy illustrates agency.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཟེར་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ ལྷག་མ་ རྣམས་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute them I taught the remaining analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ འི་ ཕྱིར་ དཔེ་ བརྒྱད་ བསྟན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is for these reasons that I taught all eight analogies.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ ཚེ་ ཞིག་ སྟེ་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ མེད་ དེ །_ |#| ཆད་པ་ དང་ འགག་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$62 “O Great King, it is not the case that life ceases, with no rebirth in the hereafter, and that it is extinguished and halted.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འདི་ དངོས་པོ་ རྟག་པ་ མ་ ཉམས་པ ར་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ འཕོ་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Neither is this life a permanent entity that transmigrates to the hereafter intact.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འདི་ ལ་མ་ བསྟེན་པ ར་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>People cannot take rebirth in the hereafter without any dependence upon this life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདག་ གིས་ [154a]  སྐྱེ་བ་ འདི་ བླང་ ངོ་ ཞེས་ བསམས་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ སྐྱེ་བ་ མི་ ལེན་ ཏོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nor do they have a rebirth by simply thinking that they [154.a] will take such and such a rebirth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདག་ གིས་ དབང་ཕྱུག་ ཆེན་པོ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ལ་ བརྟེན་ ཏེ་ མཐོ་རིས་ སུ་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ བྱ འོ་ སྙམ་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Rebirth does not occur because people think that they rely on God and the like, and that they will thus be reborn in the heavens.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བདག་ མཐོ་རིས་ དང་ ངན་སོང་ གར་ འདོད་པ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ ར་ བྱ འོ་ སྙམ་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nor do people take rebirth thinking that they will be reborn wherever they wish, whether in the heavens or in the lower realms.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཅི་ཡང་ མ་ བྱས་ ཏེ་ རྒྱུ་རྐྱེན་ ལ་ བརྟེན་ མི་ དགོས་པ ར་ སྐྱེ འོ་ སྙམ་པ ས་ ཀྱང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And rebirth does not occur because people think that they will in any case be reborn, even without doing anything and irrespective of causes and conditions.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཕུང་པོ་ འདི་ ཞིག་ སྟེ་ ཤི་ ནས་ ཅི་ཡང་ མེད་ དོ་ ཞེས་ སྨྲ་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$63 “Nor can one say that one’s aggregates perish, one dies, and that afterward there is nothing at all.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདིར་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་ ནས་ ཕ་རོལ་ ན་ གཤིན་ གྱི་ ཁམས་ སུ་ མུ་ ཆགས་ སུ་ མཆིས་པ ས་ འདི་ ན་ ཅི་ སྤྱོད་པ་ བྱེད་ དེ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ མི་ ལེན་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One cannot say either that after death in this world, people in the afterlife abide continuously#48 in the ‘world of Death,’ and thus do whatever they did in this life without taking rebirth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཚེ་ འདི འི་ རྣམ་པར་ ཤེས་པ་ མ་ འགགས་པ ར་ རྣམ་པར་ ཤེས་པ ས་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nor can one say that consciousness takes rebirth without any halt to the consciousness one has in the present life.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འདི་ དང་ ཕ་རོལ་ གཉི་ག ར་ ཕུང་པོ་ དུས་ གཅིག་ ཡོད་ ཅེས་ ཟེར་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One cannot say that the aggregates of this life and the next exist at the same time.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>གྲུམ་པོ་ ལས་ གྲུམ་པོ ར་ སྐྱེ །_ |#| དཀར་པོ་ ལས་ དཀར་པོ ར་ སྐྱེ་ ཞེས་ བྱ་བ་ ལ་སོགས་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nor can one say that the lame are reborn lame, the fair are reborn fair, and so forth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ལྷ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཡང་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ འོ །_། |#| མི་ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ཡང་ མིར་ སྐྱེ འོ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>One cannot say that gods who have died are reborn as gods and that humans who have died are reborn as humans.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ ས་ ངན་སོང་ དང་ མི་དགེ་བ ས་ མཐོ་རིས་ སུ་ འགྲུབ་ ཅེས་ ཟེར་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Nor can one say that virtue leads to the lower realms and that nonvirtue leads to higher status.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཤེས་པ་ གཅིག་ ལས་ མང་པོ་ འཕེལ་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Many consciousnesses do not develop from one.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགེ་བ་ མ་ བྱས་ ཀྱང་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ་ དང་ །_ མི་དགེ་བ་ མ་ བྱས་ ཀྱང་ ངན་སོང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Beings are not reborn as gods without having practiced virtue, nor are they reborn in the lower realms without having committed some nonvirtuous deeds.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱེ་བ་ ནི་ བྱེད་པ་པོ ས་ བྱས་པ་ ཡང་ མ་ ཡིན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Rebirth is not brought about through the actions of an external agent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་དག་ ཅིའི་ཕྱིར་ མ་ ཡིན་ ཞེ་ན །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$64 “Let us suppose someone asks why these things are not the case.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཁ་ཏོན་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ ལ་ གང་དག་ གིས་ རྣམ་པར་ ཤེས་ པ་ འདི་ མ་ འགགས་པ ར་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་ ནོ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ འི་ སྐྱོན་ བསལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ས་བོན་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Here is what we would reply. |#| Someone might say about the analogy of a recitation that it shows that one takes rebirth in the next life without the consciousness of this life perishing. |#| To eliminate this misinterpretation we put forth the analogy of the seed.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ས་བོན་ དེ་ མ་ རུལ་བ ར་ མྱུ་གུ་ སྐྱེ་ ན་ |#| ནི་ བདག་ ཏུ་ སྨྲ་བ་ དག་ བདེན་ ན་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Indeed, if a sprout were to be produced without the seed being destroyed, then the positions of those who accept real selves would be right.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ས་བོན་ དེ་ རུལ་ ནས་ སྔ་མ་ ལས་ གྱུར་ ཏེ་ |#| མི་ འདྲ་བ ར་ གྱུར་པ་ ལས་ མྱུ་གུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>However, the sprout is produced upon the destruction of the seed—that is, from something that has changed from what it was earlier on.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མར་མེ འི་ དཔེ་ ལ་ གང་ གིས་ མར་མེ་ གཅིག་ ལས་ གཅིག་ སྦར་ ན་ གཉི་ག་ ཡོད་པ ས་ འདི་ དང་ ཕ་རོལ་ གཉི་ག ར་ ཕུང་པོ་ དུས་ གཅིག་ ཡོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$65 “Someone might say about the analogy of the lamp that it shows that the aggregates of this life and the next exist at one and the same time, because when one lamp is lit from another they both exist at the same time.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ འི་ སྐྱོན་ བསལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ སྒྲ འི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>It is in order to rule out this misinterpretation that we put forth the analogy of echoing sound.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བྲག་ཅ་ ནི་ མིས་ མ་ བརྗོད་པ ར་ སྒྲ་ མི་ གྲག་ སྟེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>An echo does not resound without a person having first spoken and does not occur at the same time as that speech.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དུས་ གཅིག་ ཏུ་ མི་ འབྱུང་བ ས་ ཕུང་པོ་ ཡང་ དུས་ [154b]  གཅིག་ ཏུ་ མི་ འབྱུང་ ངོ་ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>So the aggregates do not exist at the same time. [154.b].</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ལོང་ གི་ དཔེ་ ལ་ འདྲ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ གྲུམ་པོ་ ལས་ གྲུམ་པོ ར་ སྐྱེ་བ་ དག་ དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ མེ་ཤེལ་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$66 “About the illustration of the mirror, it might be said that lame people are born from lame people because of the similarity the mirror illustrates.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ཤེལ་ ལས་ དེ་ དང་ མི་ འདྲ་བ འི་ མེ་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute such ideas we put forth the analogy of the magnifying glass, for a magnifying glass gives rise to a fire from which it is dissimilar.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>རྒྱ འི་ དཔེ་ ནི་ ལྷ་ ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ །_ |#| མི་ཚེ་ འཕོས་པ་ མིར་ སྐྱེ འོ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ བསལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ ཁ་ཏོན་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_ |#| འདི འི་ དཔེ་ ནི་ བླ་མ་ ཡིན་ ལ །_ ཕ་རོལ་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ ནི་ སློབ་མ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$67 “Someone might say that the analogy of the stamp shows that dead gods are born as gods and dead people as people. |#| To rule this out we put forth the analogy of a recitation: what illustrates the present life is the teacher and what illustrates the next life is the student;</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཐ་དད་ པས་ བླ་མ་ ཡང་སློབ་ མ་མ་ ཡིན །_ |#| སློབ་མ་ ཡང་ བླ་མ་ མ་ཡིན་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>as they are different, the teacher is not the student, nor the student the teacher.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མེ་ཤེལ་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ ལ་ མི་ འདྲ་བ འི་ དཔེ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ |#| དགེ་བ ས་ ངན་སོང་ མི་དགེ་བ ས་ མཐོ་ རིས་ སོ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$68 “About the analogy of the magnifying glass, someone might say that it is an illustration of dissimilarity and thus shows that virtue leads to lower states and nonvirtue to higher states.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ མར་མེ འི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To rule this out we put forth the analogy of a lamp.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>མར་མེ་ ལས་མ ར་ མེ་ མི་ འདྲ་བ་ མི་ འབྱུང་ གི _། མར་མེ་ ལས་མ ར་ མེ་ འབྱུང་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>A lamp does not give rise to something dissimilar to a lamp, but rather to a lamp.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཞིན་ དགེ་བ ས་ མཐོ་རིས་ མི་དགེ་བ ས་ ངན་སོང་ ནི་ རིགས་པ འོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>Similarly, it is logical that virtue gives rise to high status and nonvirtue to lower states.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ས་བོན་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ ལ་ ཤེས་པ་ འཕེལ་ ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$69 “As for the analogy of the seed, someone might say that it shows that [many different] consciousnesses develop.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ རྒྱ འི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_ |#| རྒྱ འི་ རི་མོ་ ཅི་འདྲ་བ་ དེ་ལས་ འཇིམ་པ འི་ གོང་བུ་ ལ་ ཡང་ རི་མོ་ གཞན་ མི་ འབྱུང་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To rule this out we put forth the analogy of the stamp, for the image produced in the lump of clay is not other than that of the stamp.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྐྱུར་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ ལས་ གང་དག་ གིས་ ལྷ འི་ ལོ་རྒྱུས་ མྱོང་བ་ དག་ དགེ་བ་ མ་ བྱས་ ཀྱང་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ དུ་ ལྷ ར་ སྐྱེ །_ |#| ངན་སོང་ གི་ ལོ་རྒྱུས་ མྱོང་བ་ དག་ མི་དགེ་བ་ མ་ བྱས་ ཀྱང་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ངན་སོང་ དུ་ སྐྱེ འོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་ དག་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$70 “Because of the analogy of the sour taste, someone might say that those who experience a history of birth as gods will always be born as gods, in spite of doing no virtue, and that those who experience a history of birth in the lower realms will always be born in lower realms, though they have done no nonvirtue.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དགག་པ འི་ ཕྱིར་ མེ་ལོང་ གི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_ |#| མེ་ལོང་ ལ་ བཞིན་ ཅི་འདྲ་བ་ སྣང་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ དགེ་བ་ དང་ མི་དགེ་བ འི་ འབྲས་བུ་ འདྲ་བ་ བསྣོལ་ ནས་ མི་ འདྲ་བ ར་ སྦྱོར་བ་ འགལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ རོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To refute this we put forth the illustration of the mirror, for just as a face appears in a mirror as it is, so too the similar results of virtue and nonvirtue would match [their respective causes] and it would thus be contradictory to make them dissimilar.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྒྲ འི་ དཔེ་ ལ་ ནི་ བྱེད་པ་པོ ས་ བྱས་པ་ མ་ ཡིན་ ཏེ །_ |#| མིས་ སྐད་ མ་ བསྒྲགས་པ ར་ བྲག་ཅ་ མི་ འབྱུང་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$71 “Some might say, with regard to the analogy of echoing sound, that echoes do not come about unless they are made by an external agent—that is, unless someone shouts.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཞིན་ དུ་ བྱེད་པ་པོ ས་ མ་ བྱས་པ ར་ སེམས་ཅན་ རྣམས་ མི་ སྐྱེ འོ །_། |#| ཞེས་ ཟེར་བ་</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>And analogously, so it might be said, beings are not born unless made by an external agent.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>དེ་བ ས་ ལ་བ འི་ ཕྱིར་ སྐྱུར་ གྱི་ དཔེ་ བསྟན་ ཏེ །_</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>To rule out that misinterpretation we put forth the illustration of the sour taste.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>སྔར་ འཐུངས་པ་ དང་ ཟ་ མྱོང་བ ས་ ཕྱིས་ བརྗོད་པ ས་ འགྲམ་ཆུ་ ལྡང་བ་ བཞིན་ དུ་ ལས་ དང་ ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ སྔར་ སྤྱད་པ འི་ དབང་ གིས་ ཕྱིས་ སྐྱེ་བ་ ལེན་ ནོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The point is that it is those who have previously had the experience of eating or drinking something who will later salivate when it is described, and likewise, it is because of previously engaging in actions and afflictions that one will later take rebirth.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>ཀྱེ་ རྒྱལ་པོ་ ཆེན་པོ་ སེམས་ཅན་ སྐྱེ་བ་ དང་ །_ འཇིག་པ་ དང་ །_ འདི་ དང་ ཕ་རོལ་ ཏུ་ འཕོ་བ་ དང་ །_ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ དག་ ནི་ དེ་ལྟ ར་ མཁྱེན་པ ར་ མཛོད་ ཅིག _།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$72 “O Great King, let it be known that such are the ways sentient beings take birth, perish, and transmigrate from this life to the next.”</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ ཀྱིས་ དེ་སྐད་ ཅེས་ བཀའ་ སྩལ་པ་ ལ་ འཁོར་ འདུས་ [155a]  པ་ ཐམས་ཅད་ ཡི་ རངས་ ཏེ་ མངོན་པར་ བསྟོད་ དོ །_།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$73 All the retinue [155.a] then rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>འཆི་ འཕོ་བ་ ཇི་ལྟ ར་ འགྱུར་བ་ བསྟན་པ འི་ མདོ་ རྫོགས་ སོ །།_།།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>$74 Thus ends “ The Sūtra of the Teaching Regarding Death and Transmigration .”#49</seg></tuv>
</tu>
<tu><prop type="x-sentbreak">|#|</prop>
	<tuv xml:lang="bo"><seg>བསྟན་པ་ སྔ་དར་བ འི་ ཚེ་ འགྱུར་བ་ ལས་ སྐད་ གསར་ ཆད་ ཀྱིས་ ཀྱང་ མ་བཅོས་པ འོ །།_།།</seg></tuv>
	<tuv xml:lang="en"><seg>The translation done at the time of the earlier dissemination of the teaching has not been modified at all with revised terminology.</seg></tuv>
</tu>
</body>
</tmx>
